<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Photoplethysmography | Peter Charlton</title>
    <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/category/photoplethysmography/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterhcharlton.github.io/category/photoplethysmography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Photoplethysmography</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Peter Charlton</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/media/icon_hu5d370b2f3224e8711b194d151b733caa_16531_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Photoplethysmography</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/category/photoplethysmography/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>VascAgeNet Photoplethysmography Group</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/vascagenet_ppg_group/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/vascagenet_ppg_group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vascular ageing is a natural process by which the function and structure of blood vessels degrade over time. It can manifest as elevated blood pressure, increased arterial stiffness, and atherosclerosis. Current approaches to assess vascular age have been found to be predictive of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality, but are often not convenient enough for widespread use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This group of European researchers is investigating the use of photoplethysmography to assess vascular age. Photoplethysmography is a non-invasive optical technique for measuring the arterial pulse wave, providing information on the state of the heart and blood vessels. The group is part of the wider &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet network&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;work-to-date&#34;&gt;Work to date&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group have co-authored several publications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;group-papers&#34;&gt;Group papers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review&#34;&gt;Assessing hemodynamics from the photoplethysmogram to gain insights into vascular age: A review from VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A review of techniques to assess vascular age from the photoplethysmogram. Co-authored by 16 researchers from 11 countries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/best_practices_ppg/&#34;&gt;Establishing best practices in photoplethysmography signal acquisition and processing&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;An editorial on whether it would be possible and beneficial to establish best practices for photoplethysmography signal acquisition and processing. Co-authored by 3 group members.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaborative-research&#34;&gt;Collaborative research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_bp_estimation/&#34;&gt;Blood Pressure Estimation Based on Photoplethysmography: Finger versus Wrist&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Comparing blood pressure estimates obtained from finger and wrist sensors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaborative-reviews&#34;&gt;Collaborative reviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A comprehensive overview of the state-of-the-art of wearable photoplethysmography devices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_review&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography for cardiovascular monitoring&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A review of wearable photoplethysmgoraphy, considering the technology, signal processing, and clinical applications.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;invited-talks&#34;&gt;Invited Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following speakers gave invited talks to the group in 2021:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kevin Kotzen&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Benchmarking Photoplethysmography Peak Detection Algorithms Using the Electrocardiogram Signal as a Reference&lt;/em&gt;, 7 October 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Birute Paliakaite&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Blood Pressure Estimation Based on Photoplethysmography: Finger versus Wrist&lt;/em&gt;, 28 October 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc21_bp_estimation/&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wan-Hua Lin&lt;/strong&gt; (Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Science, China): &lt;em&gt;Investigating the physiological mechanisms of the photoplethysmogram features for blood pressure estimation&lt;/em&gt;, 18 November 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6579/ab7d78&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philip Aston&lt;/strong&gt; (National Physical Laboratory, UK): 9 December 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022 group members have given talks in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_webinars/&#34;&gt;public webinar series on Photoplethysmography&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Allen&lt;/strong&gt;: presented on &lt;em&gt;Further explorations in photoplethysmography for the detection of occlusive peripheral arterial disease&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Panicos Kyriacou&lt;/strong&gt;: presented on &lt;em&gt;Non-invasive optical monitoring of Intracranial Pressure in Traumatic Brain Injury patients&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serena Zanelli&lt;/strong&gt;: will present on &lt;em&gt;Deep learning approach to detect signal quality from clinical to non-clinical PPG devices&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/EMBC46164.2021.9629640&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;short-term-scientific-mission&#34;&gt;Short-Term Scientific Mission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Peter Charlton spent 5 days at Kaunas University of Technology (KTU), hosted by Prof Vaidotas Marozas, Director of the Institute of Biomedical Engineering. During this STSM, Vaidotas, Peter and Birute Paliakaite worked with colleagues at KTU towards harmonising photoplethysmography-based techniques for the assessment of vascular ageing. This was funded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/short-term-scientific-missions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-members&#34;&gt;Group Members&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work of the group would not be possible without the hard work of its members, who include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Peter Charlton&lt;/a&gt; is a Biomedical Engineer specialising in signal processing techniques for the photoplethysmogram (PPG), including estimating respiratory rate and assessing vascular age from the PPG. He presently holds a British Heart Foundation Fellowship at the University of Cambridge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=YtQF4uUAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Birute Paliakaite&lt;/a&gt; is a researcher specialising in PPG signal processing and modelling, and has made key contributions on acquiring haemodynamic parameters from wearables, and detecting and modelling arrhythmias in the PPG.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=IJ5MsM4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Kristjan Pilt&lt;/a&gt; has developed novel techniques to assess vascular age from the PPG in his research, and has demonstrated their potential clinical utility in diabetic patients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.at/citations?user=pHHJAv4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Martin Bachler&lt;/a&gt; is a research engineer in the field of clinical diagnostics and therapy support, and specialises in biomedical signal analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vascagenet.eu/what-are-you-working-on-serena-zanelli&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Serena Zanelli&lt;/a&gt; develops machine learning and deep learning models to detect cardiovascular disease from PPG signals acquired by wearables, working in both academic and clinical settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vascagenet.eu/what-are-you-working-on-dr-daniel-kulin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Daniel Kulin&lt;/a&gt; is a medical doctor, researcher and entrepreneur in the field of PPG-based pulse wave analysis and in the development of remote patient monitoring systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.co.uk/citations?user=-GsW3HsAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof John Allen&lt;/a&gt; is a leading researcher in the field of photoplethysmography. He has worked on assessing vascular age from the PPG for approximately 30 years. He has strong experience on developing PPG-based techniques, and translating them towards clinical practice. His seminal review on photoplethysmography has been cited over 3,000 times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Magid-Hallab&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Magid Hallab&lt;/a&gt; is a physician, inventor of pOpmetre, a device for PPG-based pulse wave velocity measurement, and CEO of Axelife, the company who sell the pOpmetre device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.it/citations?user=rQqSulEAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Elisabetta Bianchini&lt;/a&gt; works in the field of ultrasound imaging and cardiovascular bioengineering, with strong interests in technology transfer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.at/citations?user=gRActvYAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Christopher Mayer&lt;/a&gt; conducts research in the field of biomedical signal processing, including simulation and pulse wave analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=w1KRD3gAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Dimitrios Terentes-Printzios&lt;/a&gt; is a Cardiologist with research interests in hypertension and microvascular dysfunction. He conducted his PhD on vascular ageing and has co-organised and large multicentre studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/verena-dittrich-1876a989/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Verena Dittrich&lt;/a&gt; is Co-Founder and CEO of Redwave Medical, a company specialising in algorithms for cardiovascular assessment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=VP9nyHAAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Bernhard Hametner&lt;/a&gt; is a mathematician developing methods for pulse wave analysis, and is involved in the analysis of cardiovascular parameters obtained in clinical studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Z_Fojr4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mr Dave Veerasingam&lt;/a&gt; is a Consultant Cardiothoracic Surgeon, and is involved in the cardiac Medtech industry. His research interests include the association between vascular ageing and target organ damage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Dejan-Zikic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Dejan Zikic&lt;/a&gt; is an Associate Professor in Biophysics, with research interests including modelling pulse wave propagation and pulse wave analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.lt/citations?user=yQcWpoIAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Vaidotas Marozas&lt;/a&gt; is Director of the Biomedical Engineering Institute at Kaunas Institute of Technology, and has conducted research into PPG modelling, analysis, and acquisition using wearables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webinars on Photoplethysmography</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_webinars/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_webinars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Photoplethysmography is widely used for physiological monitoring in clinical and consumer devices. It is a highly active area of research, with many important developments being made each year. In 2022 we will hold monthly webinars to showcase the latest research and thinking on key topics within the field of photoplethysmography. Each webinar will consist of a series of talks from leaders in the field. All are welcome to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mailing-list&#34;&gt;Mailing List&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please subscribe to this mailing list if you would like to be kept informed of upcoming webinars:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jiscmail.ac.uk/cgi-bin/webadmin?SUBED1=PHOTOPLETHYSMOGRAPHY&amp;amp;A=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Subscribe to Mailing List&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;upcoming-webinars&#34;&gt;Upcoming Webinars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;photoplethysmography-signal-processing&#34;&gt;Photoplethysmography signal processing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;15 September 2022, 14:00 British Summer Time (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/british-summer-time-bst?t=14&amp;amp;d=2022-06-09&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Hosted by the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/what-s-on/ipem-events/webinar-photoplethysmography-signal-processing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Book now&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal contains a wealth of information. However, there are several challenges to extracting physiological measurements from the PPG. Firstly, the PPG is highly susceptible to noise, which can corrupt the information in the signal. Consequently, much research has focused on assessing PPG signal quality and reducing motion artifact. Secondly, the PPG is often only indirectly affected by the physiology of interest, making it a challenge to extract physiological measurements such as blood pressure. This webinar will feature talks from researchers in the field of PPG signal processing, providing an overview of current work in the field and future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Xiaorong Ding (University of Electronic Science and Technology of China)&lt;/strong&gt; will present on &lt;em&gt;Exploiting Photoplethysmogram Features for Cuffless Blood Pressure Estimation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ariane Morassi-Sasso (Hasso Plattner Institute)&lt;/strong&gt; will present on &lt;em&gt;Predicting blood pressure from photoplethysmography&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serena Zanelli (Paris Sorbonne Nord University)&lt;/strong&gt; will present a &lt;em&gt;Deep learning approach to detect signal quality from clinical to non-clinical PPG devices&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/EMBC46164.2021.9629640&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-webinars&#34;&gt;Previous Webinars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-2&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinar 1: Simulating photoplethysmography signals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;webinar-1-simulating-photoplethysmography-signals&#34;&gt;Webinar 1: Simulating photoplethysmography signals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;27 January 2022, 14:00 GMT (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/greenwich-mean-time-gmt?t=14&amp;amp;d=2021-01-27&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Hosted by the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several techniques have recently been developed to simulate photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals, providing data with which to develop PPG signal processing algorithms, and providing insight into the physiological origins of the signal. This webinar will feature talks from researchers who have developed complementary techniques to simulate PPG signals. It will provide a comprehensive overview of the state-of-the-art, and highlight pressing directions for future research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrius Solosenko (Kaunas University of Technology)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on modelling photoplethysmogram signals during atrial fibrillation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheng Ding (Emory University)&lt;/strong&gt; presented a novel approach to simulating PPG signals using generative adversarial networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon (King&amp;rsquo;s College London)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on the role of &lt;em&gt;in silico&lt;/em&gt; pulse wave databases in machine learning-based pulse wave analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-3&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinar 2: Recent Advances in Photoplethysmography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;webinar-2-recent-advances-in-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;Webinar 2: Recent Advances in Photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;3 March 2022, 14:00 GMT (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/greenwich-mean-time-gmt?t=14&amp;amp;d=2022-03-03&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  Hosted by &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/journal/0967-3334&#34;&gt;Physiological Measurement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://register.gotowebinar.com/register/5108458986808048397&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Watch Again&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photoplethysmography is a non-invasive, optical measurement technique which is widely used for health monitoring. Much research focuses on how to leverage the wealth of information in the photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal, and how to use this information to inform clinical decisions. This webinar will feature talks from leaders in the field, on topics ranging from using photoplethysmography for cardiovascular risk assessment, for cuff-less blood pressure monitoring, and validating these technologies for clinical use. It will provide insight into the state-of-the-art and key directions for future research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rich Fletcher (Massachusetts Institute of Technology)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;&#39;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6579/abad48&#34;&gt;The use of multi-site photoplethysmography (PPG) as a screening tool for coronary arterial disease and atherosclerosis&lt;/a&gt;&#39;&lt;/em&gt;, which was recently published in &lt;em&gt;Physiological Measurement&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raquel Bailón Luesma, (University of Zaragoza)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Applications of PPG waveform decomposition analysis&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ramakrishna Mukkamala (University of Pittsburgh)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.121.17747&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Cuffless Blood Pressure Measurement Devices: Challenges and Proposals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, highlighting work which was recently published in &lt;em&gt;Hypertension&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Xiaoman Xing (Suzhou Institute of Biomedical Engineering and Technology)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;&#39;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6579/ac2a71&#34;&gt;Blood pressure assessment with in-ear photoplethysmography&lt;/a&gt;&#39;&lt;/em&gt;, which was recently published in &lt;em&gt;Physiological Measurement&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-4&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinar 3: Clinical applications of photoplethysmography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;clinical-applications-of-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;Clinical applications of photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;28 April 2022, 14:00 British Summer Time (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/british-summer-time-bst?t=14&amp;amp;d=2022-04-28&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Hosted by the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This webinar highlighted emerging clinical applications of photoplethysmography. Photoplethysmography has traditionally been used in pulse oximeters for oxygen saturation and heart rate monitoring. Recently, several additional clinical applications have been proposed, ranging from screening newborn infants for critical congenital heart disease, to sleep apnea assessment, to identifying atrial fibrillation in everyday life. This webinar featured talks from researchers who are pushing the boundaries of photoplethysmography, developing approaches to use it to enhance healthcare in a range of settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Allen (Coventry University)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Further explorations in photoplethysmography for the detection of occlusive peripheral arterial disease&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Panicos Kyriacou (City University of London)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Non-invasive optical monitoring of Intracranial Pressure in Traumatic Brain Injury patients&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-5&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinar 4: Developments in Photoplethysmography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;developments-in-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;Developments in Photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;7 July 2022, 14:00 British Summer Time (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/british-summer-time-bst?t=14&amp;amp;d=2022-07-07&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Hosted by the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photoplethysmography is an optical sensing technique that is widely used in clinical and consumer devices. It is a highly active area of research, with many important developments being made each year. In this webinar leaders in the field will present their latest research. Topics include extracting measurements of pulse rate variability from the photoplethysmogram (PPG) for applications such as stress monitoring, and using phantoms to investigate the origins of the PPG and develop new PPG sensing technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;James May (City, University of London)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Phantoms for In Vitro Investigations of PPG and PPG technology Development&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elisa Mejia-Mejia (City, University of London)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Photoplethysmography-based pulse rate variability: standardisation of the technique using simulated signals&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;James Anibal (University of Oxford)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Attention methods for longer PPG sequences&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-want-your-input&#34;&gt;We want your input&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to present at a webinar then please email Peter Charlton:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:pete@oxon.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Register your interest in presenting&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to see your favourite PPG topics (and speakers) included in the webinar series, then please give your suggestions in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdlzKlZi1wVezPwibpWuoxRh6hrV9QJrwjcos5NAa4sUvQCEA/viewform?usp=sf_link&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;anonymous form&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdlzKlZi1wVezPwibpWuoxRh6hrV9QJrwjcos5NAa4sUvQCEA/viewform?usp=sf_link&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Suggest Topics and Speakers&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photoplethysmography Textbook</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_book/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new textbook, titled &lt;em&gt;Photoplethysmography&lt;/em&gt;, is due to be published in late 2021. Several experts in the field have contributed to the textbook, which is intended to provide a comprehensive summary of the theory, principles and technology of photoplethysmography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sample-chapters&#34;&gt;Sample Chapters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following sample chapters are available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/&#34;&gt;Photoplethysmography signal processing and synthesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A comprehensive overview of signal processing techniques for the photoplethysmogram signal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A comprehensive overview of the state-of-the-art of wearable photoplethysmography devices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;link-to-published-version&#34;&gt;Link to Published Version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The published version of the textbook is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/books/photoplethysmography/kyriacou/978-0-12-823374-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and can be previewed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/_/d8wnEAAAQBAJ?gbpv=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. (Note that some of the images in the preview version are in black and white, whereas the sample chapters above contain full colour images.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
