<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Peter Charlton</title>
    <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterhcharlton.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Peter Charlton</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Peter Charlton</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/media/icon_hu5d370b2f3224e8711b194d151b733caa_16531_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Peter Charlton</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Screening for AF - questions and potential answers</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/screening-for-af-questions-and-potential-answers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/screening-for-af-questions-and-potential-answers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following resources accompany this talk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/screening_for_af_q_a_transcript/&#34;&gt;The transcript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/reviewing_ecgs/&#34;&gt;The accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.phpc.cam.ac.uk/people/pcu-group/pcu-senior-academic-staff/jonathan-mant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof Jonathan Mant&lt;/a&gt;, who leads the SAFER Programme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/about-us/research-team/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SAFER Research Team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The NIHR and BHF, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Beauty of Biomedical Engineering</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/the-beauty-of-biomedical-engineering/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/the-beauty-of-biomedical-engineering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;transcript&#34;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transcript for the talk is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/beauty_biomed_eng_transcript/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Beauty of Biomedical Engineering</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/beauty_biomed_eng_transcript/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/beauty_biomed_eng_transcript/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This transcript accompanies &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/the-beauty-of-biomedical-engineering/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the transcript content is reproduced from Peter Charlton&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cont_resp_monitoring/&#34;&gt;PhD thesis&lt;/a&gt; under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;initial-spoken-content&#34;&gt;Initial spoken content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On receiving &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ipem_early_career_award/&#34;&gt;this prize&lt;/a&gt;, it might seem appropriate to give a whistle-stop tour of the engineering projects that I&amp;rsquo;ve been involved in. My apologies to anyone expecting this, if you&amp;rsquo;re really interested you can read all about our work on &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this website&lt;/a&gt;. Instead I&amp;rsquo;m going to share a few thoughts on why Biomedical Engineering is a fantastic field to work in. So, the beauty of Biomedical Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-colleagues&#34;&gt;The colleagues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the colleagues. I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate to work with great colleagues, who have been an inspiration to me throughout my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was particularly struck by one encounter early in my career. One morning, probably around 10am, a few of us were meeting to discuss a new approach to a problem. An intensive care consultant arrived dressed in scrubs and clutching a cup of coffee. It transpired that he had been on call the previous day, had been up most of the night, and here he was having just handed over, ready to engage in the mathematics of a new signal processing technique, which in the very distant future could potentially help identify the early signs of sepsis. I was inspired by this colleague&amp;rsquo;s dedication, which encourages me to work hard on clinical problems to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long later, I was in the same room being introduced to an engineer who had developed a health-monitoring system for jet engines, providing real-time information to ensure the safe passage of air passengers. Now he had turned his attention to a health-monitoring system for people, aiming to spot clinical deteriorations from subtle changes in vital signs. I was inspired by his skill, translating complex analytical techniques across fields, for the benefit of patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year or so later I was at a conference in a mega venue in Brussels, which seemed better suited to debating Members of Parliament than researchers with poster tubes tucked under their arms. One talk described a research study conducted across multiple countries, which had investigated the use of fluid resuscitation to treat children with shock. Whereas this intervention was used everyday in adult intensive care to save lives, the study found it increased mortality in this population - a finding that had apparently baffled the intensive care world. Later that day I attended another session in what felt like a debating chamber, each seat equipped with its own microphone. The chair had asked everyone to speak into their microphones when asking questions. Both the chair and audience quickly became frustrated when one attendee was unable to find the large orange button directly in front of them, with which to turn on their microphone. It was the researcher who&amp;rsquo;d managed to conduct the baffling study in children across several countries, who finally pointed out that this attendee simply couldn&amp;rsquo;t see their microphone button because their laptop was covering it. I was inspired by her &amp;lsquo;smartness&amp;rsquo;, shown by her ability to conduct excellent research, and to solve simple problems which left the rest of us frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So - the first reason Biomedical Engineering is fantastic - the colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-patients&#34;&gt;The patients&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the patients. Many, many patients have contributed their time and effort to the research studies I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on. Several years ago I helped run a study investigating the use of wearables for monitoring hospital patients. Initially, we expected to equip patients with a miniature gadget, perhaps in the form of a lapel badge, which would transmit their vital signs in real-time to an all-knowing computer, which would quickly identify any problems as they developed. It turned out, in the early 2010s, that such gadgets didn&amp;rsquo;t exist. Instead, we used the existing telemetry devices to monitor patients. These were large devices, about the size of a bag of sugar, that you either had to carry round in your hand, or wear in a shoulder bag slung across your chest. Needless to say, there was a mixed reaction, demonstrated by three patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One patient tolerated the sensor poorly, until it detected that they were having a cardiac arrest and arguably saved their life. Thereafter they tolerated the sensor very well indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One patient was very talkative before their operation, and despite wearing the sensor, died tragically young a few days later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, one patient, who probably didn&amp;rsquo;t need a sensor, ended up practically dancing around the ward whilst wearing it. I can still see them stood at the nurses station, laughing and joking with the staff on the ward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So - the second reason Biomedical Engineering is fantastic - the patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-engineering-problems&#34;&gt;The Engineering Problems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the engineering problems. Biomedical engineering problems have all the hallmarks of an exciting engineering project: a problem which we don&amp;rsquo;t understand well, a plethora of innovative solutions, and the potential to save lives. I&amp;rsquo;ll give a very brief example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;slide-respiratory-rate&#34;&gt;Slide: Respiratory Rate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Respiratory rate (RR), the number of breaths taken in a minute, is used in a range of clinical settings for diagnosis and prognosis. [click] Normal RRs lie between 12 and 20 breaths per minute. [click] Elevated RRs have been found to be associated with: [click] COVID-19 diagnosis; [click] admission to intensive care with COVID-19 [click]; and death in hospital with COVID-19. Consequently, it may be helpful to monitor RR to tackle COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;slide-wearables-for-monitoring-respiratory-rate&#34;&gt;Slide: Wearables for monitoring Respiratory Rate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wearables provide a potential opportunity to monitor RR unobtrusively in daily life. [click] Many wearables monitor the pulse at the wrist by measuring an optical signal, the photoplethysmogram (or PPG for short). [click] This signal exhibits a pulse wave for each heart beat, [click] and is also subtly influenced by breathing. Consequently, much research has been conducted on estimating RR from this signal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;slide-errors-are-not-normally-distributed&#34;&gt;Slide: Errors are not normally distributed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often when taking measurements, such as measuring time or length, one might expect measurement errors to be normally distributed. However, when developing algorithms to estimate RR from wearable sensors, I&amp;rsquo;ve been struck that the errors are not necessarily normally distributed. For instance, these plots show the reference RR on the x-axis, and the RR provided by an algorithm on the y-axis. I&amp;rsquo;ve repeated the experiment on three different datasets, providing the three plots. Most of the points are clustered around the line of identity, as expected if errors are normally distributed. However, [click] some measurements are very inaccurate, providing erroneously low RRs, which could potentially trigger erroneous clinical responses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Click] In this second algorithm, the errors are more normally distributed without the highly erroneous outliers. However, the errors tend to be greater. So we have two algorithms with differing performance characteristics. For this particular problem, it turns out that by combining the two algorithms, one can improve performance, using the upper algorithm to avoid large errors, and the second algorithm to minimise errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;closing-slide&#34;&gt;Closing Slide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently refining the algorithms [click] for use in daily life, and it is my hope that this work will be of great benefit to society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you&amp;rsquo;re interested in this particular problem, you can read more about it and our other work at this website [click]. So - the third reason Biomedical Engineering is fantastic - the challenging problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to conclude, I think Biomedical Engineering [click] is a fantastic field to work in because of the inspirational colleagues, generous patients, and intriguing engineering challenges. I&amp;rsquo;d like to thank [click] my funders, and thank IPEM for this prize and the continued support throughout my career.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcript for: Screening for AF - questions and potential answers</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/screening_for_af_q_a_transcript/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/screening_for_af_q_a_transcript/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This transcript accompanies &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/screening-for-af-questions-and-potential-answers/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the transcript content is reproduced from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/reviewing_ecgs/&#34;&gt;accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt; under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;title-slide&#34;&gt;Title Slide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topic for today:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Screening for atrial fibrillation: questions and potential answers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;clinical-problem-undiagnosed-af&#34;&gt;Clinical Problem: undiagnosed AF&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Click] If atrial fibrillation was adequately treated in England, then it&amp;rsquo;s estimated that this could save [click] 2,000 lives per year, [click] prevent 7,000 strokes, and result in an additional 425,000 diagnoses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;potential-solution-af-screening&#34;&gt;Potential Solution: AF screening&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been proposed that undiagnosed AF could be identified through screening. However, &amp;ldquo;it is unclear whether there is a benefit of formal screening programmes for AF over and above diagnosis of AF only through routine clinical practice&amp;rdquo; [&lt;a href=&#34;https://view-health-screening-recommendations.service.gov.uk/atrial-fibrillation/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK National Screening Committee, 2019&lt;/a&gt;]. The ongoing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SAFER Trial&lt;/a&gt; [click] aims to determine whether screening for AF is effective and cost-effective in reducing stroke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-introduction&#34;&gt;Personal Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To introduce myself [click], my name&amp;rsquo;s Peter Charlton, and I&amp;rsquo;m a researcher in Biomedical Engineering. I develop techniques to analyse physiological signals, such as the ECGs acquired in screening studies, to aid clinical decision making. I initially conducted my research here at St Thomas&#39; Hospital in London, working with clinicians to develop techniques to identify the early signs of clinical deterioration from wearable sensor signals. Since then, I&amp;rsquo;ve been analysing ECG data [click] collected by the SAFER Research Team, at the University of Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-1&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk I&amp;rsquo;ll look at three key questions and potential answers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is screening for AF effective?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can today&amp;rsquo;s screening be optimised?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What might tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s screening look like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, an introduction to AF screening and the SAFER Programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;atrial-fibrillation&#34;&gt;Atrial Fibrillation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AF is one of the most common arrhythmias, diagnosed in 3% of UK people over the age of 35 [&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1136/heartjnl-2018-312977&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Adderley &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]. It is associated with a fivefold increase in stroke risk [&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/0.1161/01.str.22.8.983&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wolf &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]. If AF is recognised then the risk of stroke can be reduced by 60-70% through anticoagulation [&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17577005&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hart &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1161/JAHA.116.003725&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Yao &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]. AF is currently diagnosed opportunistically in primary care, and verified by ECG. Whilst some cases of AF are persistent [click], meaning that the patient is in AF all the time, others are paroxysmal [click], meaning there are only intermittent episodes of AF which could be missed in a one-off ECG test. Furthermore, AF can be asymptomatic [click], meaning testing may not be indicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-safer-programme&#34;&gt;The SAFER Programme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SAFER Programme of research, led by Prof Jonathan Mant, aims to determine [click] whether screening for AF is effective and cost-effective in reducing stroke and other key outcomes compared to current practice. It consists of [click] four parts [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/about-screenforaf/aims-and-objectives/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SAFER Website&lt;/a&gt;]:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feasibility study 1:&lt;/strong&gt; A study in 10 GP Practices, including a face-to-face appointment, which 2,141 participants took part in. This has finished, confirming that it is feasible to deliver an AF screening programme in general practice, and that high numbers of patients accept an offer of AF screening and go on to complete the screening process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feasibility study 2:&lt;/strong&gt; When the COVID-19 pandemic struck, it became clear that screening could not be delivered in the practice. An additional feasibility study was conducted with participants from 3 GP Practices, in which the screening was delivered remotely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal pilot study:&lt;/strong&gt; The first phase of the trial is now underway. An internal pilot study is being conducted in 36 practices, consisting of 12 intervention practices where patients will be offered screening, and 24 control practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cluster randomised controlled trial:&lt;/strong&gt; Following the pilot, we expect to move straight into the remainder of the trial, including a further 324 practices. The whole trial, including the internal pilot, will enrol approximately 126,000 patients from 360 practices, a third of whom will be offered screening. They will be followed up for an average of 5 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-screening-process&#34;&gt;The Screening Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three main steps of the screening process which I&amp;rsquo;ll refer to are as follows [click]:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ECGs recorded at home:&lt;/strong&gt; Firstly, participants are sent a handheld device which takes 30-second ECG recordings between two thumbs. Participants are asked to record an ECG 4 times per day, for 3 weeks [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/for-patients/screening-process/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SAFER Website&lt;/a&gt;], producing approximately 84 ECGs per participant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automated analysis:&lt;/strong&gt; Secondly, the ECG recordings are automatically analysed to identify any that may contain AF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical review:&lt;/strong&gt; Thirdly, those ECGs which may contain AF are sent for clinical review to make a final diagnosis. Any participants diagnosed with AF then discuss possible anticoagulation with their GP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-screening-for-af-effective&#34;&gt;Is screening for AF effective?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the first question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-screening-for-af-effective-and-cost-effective-in-reducing-stroke-and-other-key-outcomes-compared-to-current-practice&#34;&gt;Is screening for AF effective and cost effective in reducing stroke and other key outcomes compared to current practice?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question hasn&amp;rsquo;t yet been answered in the ongoing SAFER Trial. However, results were recently published for the STROKESTOP trial, a trial using the same handheld devices in Sweden [&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140-6736%2821%2901637-8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;]. There was a &amp;ldquo;small net benefit&amp;rdquo; to screening, as shown by the significantly lower number of events in those invited to screening, compared to the control group. Although there were some differences in trial design, the trial does provide some useful learning points for SAFER, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For screening to be effective, a high proportion of those invited to screening have to participate, since the endpoint was calculated using the intention-to-treat analysis, as is the case in SAFER. In STROKESTOP, of those invited to screening, 51.3% participated. Indeed, those who &amp;ldquo;declined the invitation for screening &amp;hellip; had higher &amp;hellip; stroke risk&amp;rdquo; [&lt;a href=&#34;10.1016/s0140-6736%2821%2901750-5&#34;&gt;Lowres &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]. As noted in the accompanying commentary, &amp;ldquo;A different approach is being adopted in the SAFER study, in which patients in general practices are invited to join the study, and practices are only randomly assigned to screening or control after a sufficient number of patients consent, which should obviate the design problem of dilution by non-participants&amp;rdquo; [&lt;a href=&#34;10.1016/s0140-6736%2821%2901750-5&#34;&gt;Lowres &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]. Qualitative researchers in the SAFER team are collecting feedback from non-participants to understand why people decline the invitation to screening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[click] The results also show promise for the choice of combined ischaemic and haemorrhagic stroke as the primary endpoint in SAFER. Both of these endpoints showed a signal towards a difference, although this was not significant difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-todays-screening-be-optimised-outline&#34;&gt;How can today&amp;rsquo;s screening be optimised? (outline)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the second question: How can today&amp;rsquo;s screening be optimised? My colleagues and I have been working on optimising the acquisition of ECGs, and their automated review. I&amp;rsquo;ll present preliminary analyses on these two aspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ecgs-recorded-at-home&#34;&gt;ECGs recorded at home&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, [click] we are establishing criteria to prompt a telephone call from the research team to participants to provide additional training when required on taking ECGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Click] Many of the ECGs collected in SAFER are of high quality, such as this ECG here. However, [click] some ECGs are of low quality. These are often difficult, if not impossible, to interpret. Consequently, if a participant records too many low quality ECGs then it may not be possible to accurately identify AF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Click] In a retrospective analysis of data from the first SAFER Feasibility Study, we investigated the performance of different criteria for identifying participants who would record a high proportion of low quality ECGs. The analysis was performed on 1,486 participants, who each recorded at least 56 ECGs. The criteria were applied to ECGs received during the first 10 days (i.e. the first half) of screening. We aimed for a high sensitivity to participants with less than 75% high quality ECGs, and a low alert rate to minimise the workload associated with the additional calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Click] Here are the results for three candidate criteria. For each criterion, a threshold was learnt from the data. The third criterion, which consisted of triggering a call if more than 25% of a participant&amp;rsquo;s ECGs were of low quality, resulted in a high sensitivity at the desired alert rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;effectiveness-of-criterion-to-prompt-a-training-call&#34;&gt;Effectiveness of criterion to prompt a training call&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Click] The effectiveness of this criterion was then assessed when it was used in the second SAFER Feasibility Study. This study was smaller, with &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; participants. &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; of these participants received a telephone call - reassuringly, this indicates an alert rate of approximately 4% as desired. It&amp;rsquo;s testament to the SAFER Team that these calls resulted in a reduction in the percentage of low quality recordings, as shown in this box plot. &lt;em&gt;(describe reduction shown in plot)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we have found that training calls can be targeted to those participants who would benefit most from them, and that they are effective in improving the quality of ECG recordings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;automated-analysis&#34;&gt;Automated analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second analysis which informed the Trial&amp;rsquo;s methodology was an assessment of the performance of algorithm tags for identifying AF, and the workload associated with reviewing ECGs classified with each tag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll briefly summarise how the algorithm works. [Click] Each ECG is analysed by [click] detecting heartbeats, [click] analysing the heart rhythm, and assessing [click] whether P-waves are present or not. A key question [click] is: which tags should be used to identify ECGs for review?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[click] In a retrospective analysis, I assessed the sensitivity of each tag to AF, and its positive predictive value. This was performed using manual annotations of 911 ECGs containing AF provided by cardiologists. Six tags showed reasonable performance (shown in bold). These were considered as candidates to identify ECGs for clinical review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[click] In a second analysis, I investigated the workload and effectiveness of the combination of tags used in this Feasibility Study, and all possible combinations of the candidate tags. The combination of tags used in the study, shown in the first row, was particularly comprehensive, and resulted in 23,000 ECGs being sent for review. Through this process 54 participants were diagnosed with AF. The remaining rows show selected combinations using subsets of these tags. As the number of tags is reduced, the number of ECGs sent for review is reduced. Only in the last combination, the irregular sequence tag on its own, was there an impact on the diagnosis of AF, with one participant being missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on this, I recommended that the irregular sequence and fast regular tags be used in SAFER, which in this analysis would have substantially reduced the workload associated with ECG reviewing, whilst maintaining the number of AF diagnoses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-todays-screening-be-optimised&#34;&gt;How can today&amp;rsquo;s screening be optimised?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;rsquo;ve presented preliminary results on questions relating to optimising the current approach to screening, specifically on: training calls, and the automated analysis of ECGs. In addition, I am particularly interested in the following additional questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can ECGs be ordered according to their likelihood of exhibiting AF?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the level of inter-reviewer agreement in diagnoses?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many reviewers should review each patient?s data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we develop a library of ECGs with which to train new reviewers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-might-tomorrows-screening-look-like-outline&#34;&gt;What might tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s screening look like? (outline)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the third question: What might tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s screening look like? As an engineer, it is my hope that the data collected in both the SAFER Programme and follow-on studies will be useful for informing tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s approach to screening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;could-consumer-devices-be-used-for-clinical-decision-making&#34;&gt;Could consumer devices be used for clinical decision making?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key question going forward will be: Could consumer devices be used for clinical decision making?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devices like those shown here are commercially available, including the AliveCor device (left), which allows users to record their ECG with a small add-on to their smartphone. Watches by Withings [click], such as that shown here, also allow users to record a 30-second ECG. And, fitness trackers and smartwatches which measure the arterial pulse wave are now commonplace [click], some of which can identify an irregular pulse which may be indicative of AF. We are starting the SAFER Wearables study, a study to assess the acceptability and performance of wearables such as those shown here for identifying AF in older adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-consumer-devices-to-identify-af&#34;&gt;Using consumer devices to identify AF&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it has already been shown that smartwatches could potentially be used to unobtrusively check for AF in daily life as follows. In [click] a normal rhythm, [click] the beat-to-beat intervals are fairly consistent. In contrast, [click] in atrial fibrillation the beat-to-beat intervals are irregular [click]. Potentially, a consumer wearable could be used to identify possible AF episodes in this manner. Indeed, the potential utility of an Apple Watch to identify AF was recently assessed in the Apple Heart Study in over 400,000 individuals. Key results included a reassuringly low alert rate [click], a high positive predictive value of alerts [click], and a much longer monitoring time [click] than could be achieved at scale in clinical practice. In this study, possible AF episodes prompted further monitoring using the gold standard of an ECG-based wearable in order to confirm a diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SAFER Wearables Study will add to this evidence by assessing the performance of the technology in older adults, and daily life - two aspects that in our opinion, require further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.phpc.cam.ac.uk/people/pcu-group/pcu-senior-academic-staff/jonathan-mant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof Jonathan Mant&lt;/a&gt;, who leads the SAFER Programme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/about-us/research-team/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SAFER Research Team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The NIHR and BHF, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evidence is emerging showing the clinical benefit of AF screening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trials are ongoing, which will also assess the cost-effectiveness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If wearables are used to identify AF, they should be like a harness: highly reliable, and for a specified purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please see the links above for the resources accompanying this talk. During the talk, you will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The event poll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the talk, you may be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_transcript/&#34;&gt;The transcript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;The accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;, and accompanying &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Photoplethysmography Peak Detection Algorithms Using the Electrocardiogram Signal as a Reference</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_beat_detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_beat_detection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-text&#34;&gt;Full text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The published version will be available soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blood Pressure Estimation Based on Photoplethysmography: Finger versus Wrist</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_bp_estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_bp_estimation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-text&#34;&gt;Full text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The published version will be available soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The functionality of consumer wearables</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/functionality_of_wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/functionality_of_wearables/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently had a look into the functionality of consumer wearables to understand the state-of-the-art. This post summarises the findings, and further details are provided in the following book chapter: &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;Wearable Photoplethysmography Devices&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;functionality&#34;&gt;Functionality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The functionality of selected consumer wearables is summarised in the table below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Wearable&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Form factor&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;HR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;irreg.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SpO2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;RR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;BP&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;sleep&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;calories&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;VO2 max&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;ECG&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;steps&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;elevation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;temp&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apple Watch Series 6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist watch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Withings Scanwatch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist watch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Samsung Galaxy Watch3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist watch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fitbit Sense&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist watch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Garmin Forerunner 945&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist watch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Amazfit GTR 2e&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist watch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Huawei Watch GT2 Pro (ECG)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist watch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fossil Gen 5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist watch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WHOOP Strap 3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist strap&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Biostrap Evo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist band&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oura Ring&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;finger ring&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jabra Elite Sport&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ear buds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bodytrak&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ear buds + case&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cosinuss Two&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ear wrap around&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Owlet Smart Sock Baby Monitor 3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ankle sock&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AIO Sleeve 2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;arm sleeve&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Polar OH1 Sensor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;armband OR goggles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aktiia.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Aktiia Bracelet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wrist band&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Y&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defintions: irreg. - irregular pulse detection; RR - respiratory rate; BP - blood pressure; temp - temperature.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adapted under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt; from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seshadri, D.R. et al., &amp;lsquo;Wearable sensors for COVID-19: a call to action to harness our digital infrastructure for remote patient monitoring and virtual assessments.&amp;rsquo; Front. Digit. Heal. 2020, 2, 1-11, DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3389/fdgth.2020.00008&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10.3389/fdgth.2020.00008&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Original source (reproduced under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;P. H. Charlton, &amp;lsquo;Wearable sensor images.&amp;rsquo; Zenodo, 2021. DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.798234&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10.5281/zenodo.798234&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version: 12 March 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-reading&#34;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further information on the state-of-the-art in wearable photoplethysmography devices, please see the following book chapter: &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;Wearable Photoplethysmography Devices&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Academic Early Career Award</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ipem_early_career_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ipem_early_career_award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;recognition-from-the-institute-of-physics-and-engineering-in-medicine&#34;&gt;Recognition from the Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2021, Peter Charlton received the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/AboutIPEM/PrizesandAwards.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Academic Early Career Award&lt;/a&gt; from the Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine. This award recognises his contribution to academic practice, including his research, generating income, collaboration, engagement with the scientific community, and his teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The President of the Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine, Professor O&amp;rsquo;Connor said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;This award highlights an early career member of IPEM who is destined to go far in their academic career. Peter has had a distinguished career to date and is a worthy winner.&#39;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details of the award are available on the Institute&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/NewsExternalAffairs/LatestNews/TabId/366/ArtMID/1595/ArticleID/612/Gold-Medal-and-Early-Career-awards-for-IPEM-members.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-resources&#34;&gt;Further resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As detailed on the Institute&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/AboutIPEM/PrizesandAwards.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;, individuals can apply for this award each year. Any potential applicants may be interested to read the content of my application &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/info/tips/past_applications/ipem_academic_early_career_award&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photoplethysmography Textbook</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_book/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new textbook, titled &lt;em&gt;Photoplethysmography&lt;/em&gt;, is due to be published in late 2021. Several experts in the field have contributed to the textbook, which is intended to provide a comprehensive summary of the theory, principles and technology of photoplethysmography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sample-chapters&#34;&gt;Sample Chapters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following sample chapters are available (pre-publication manuscripts):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/&#34;&gt;Photoplethysmography signal processing and synthesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A comprehensive overview of signal processing techniques for the photoplethysmogram signal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A comprehensive overview of the state-of-the-art of wearable photoplethysmography devices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;link-to-published-version&#34;&gt;Link to Published Version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The published version of the textbook will be made available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/books/photoplethysmography/kyriacou/978-0-12-823374-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photoplethysmography Signal Processing and Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;links-to-full-text&#34;&gt;Links to full text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The published version will be made available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/books/photoplethysmography/kyriacou/978-0-12-823374-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The accepted manuscript is freely available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/PPG_sig_proc_Chapter_20210612.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wearable photoplethysmography devices</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;links-to-full-text&#34;&gt;Links to full text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The published version will be made available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/books/photoplethysmography/kyriacou/978-0-12-823374-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The accepted manuscript is freely available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/Wear_PPG_Chapter_20210323.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using consumer devices for clinical assessment</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/using-consumer-devices-for-clinical-assessment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2021 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/using-consumer-devices-for-clinical-assessment/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing wearables - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/safer-wearables/&#34;&gt;SAFER Wearables Study&lt;/a&gt; aims to assess the performance and acceptability of wearables for atrial fibrillation screening. It is important that the wearables are able to capture data in everyday life when &lt;em&gt;unmonitored&lt;/em&gt; (unsupervised by the researchers - &lt;em&gt;left to their own devices&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post describes initial testing of candidate devices for the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;devices&#34;&gt;Devices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devices under test, shown at the top of this page, were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference ECG chest-patch&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://shop.bittium.com/product/36/bittium-faros-180-solution-pack&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bittium Faros 180&lt;/a&gt; was used with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ambu.com/cardiology/ecg-electrodes/product/ambu-bluesensor-vlc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;long-term electrodes&lt;/a&gt;. It was worn on the sternum, with one electrode placed at the top of the sternum, and the other placed towards the bottom of the sternum (the green, F/LL electrode was not attached). It was set to record a single-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) signal at 125 Hz, with no additional recording (such as accelerometry) or analysis (such as RR-interval derivation). Data were stored on the device for retrospective download via USB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photoplethysmography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maximintegrated.com/en/products/interface/sensor-interface/MAX-HEALTHBAND.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Max-Health-Band&lt;/a&gt; was used to record photoplethysmogram (PPG) and accelerometry (accel) signals at the wrist. PPG signals were sampled at 25 Hz (green and ambient), and tri-axis accel signals were also sampled at 25 Hz. The data are initially stored on the device, and transmitted via Bluetooth to a mobile phone for long-term storage (due to limited on-device memory).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electrocardiography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.withings.com/uk/en/move-ecg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Withings Move ECG&lt;/a&gt; device was used to acquire 30-second ECG recordings on demand (when the user activated the ECG recording).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile phone&lt;/strong&gt;: A &amp;lsquo;Motorola Moto G8 Power Lite&amp;rsquo; Android mobile phone was used to store signals from the two wristbands. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.macrodroid.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Macrodroid&lt;/a&gt; was used to open and close two apps in turn to download signals from the PPG and ECG wristbands (the &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pulseon.com/tech/ohr-tracker&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PulseOn Demo&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.withings.wiscale2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Withings Health Mate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; apps respectively). The PPG app was opened twice per hour, for 14 minutes each time, and the ECG app was opened once per hour, for 14 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;protocol&#34;&gt;Protocol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single user attempted to wear the devices for seven days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference ECG chest-patch&lt;/strong&gt;: The user changed electrodes if necessary (due to discomfort), but otherwise the device was unattended. The user shaved prior to application, and removed the device for showering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photoplethysmography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: This device was removed and charged each day (typically for 1-2 hours, until it indicated it was fully charged). It was also removed when showering and washing. The device appeared to freeze at one point, so was reset. Otherwise, it was unattended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electrocardiography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: ECG recordings were acquired each day (somewhat sporadically).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile phone&lt;/strong&gt;: The mobile phone was kept on charge in a room where the user spent several hours each day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;outcomes&#34;&gt;Outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;user-acceptability&#34;&gt;User acceptability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devices were worn for approximately 6.5 days. They were removed early because the ECG chest-patch was sounding a low battery alarm. The user changed one of the chest-patch electrodes twice during the study, and the other one was not changed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-acquisition&#34;&gt;Data acquisition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Signal samples:&lt;/strong&gt; Samples of ECG chest-patch and PPG wristband signals are shown below. These samples were recorded at night, explaining the low heart rate and relatively high signal quality. The PPG signals did not appear to degrade over time. The ECG signals on days 1-3 clearly show P waves, QRS complexes, and T-waves. Several of the PPG signals show two peaks (a systolic and a diastolic peak). This plot demonstrates that it is possible to obtain high quality signals using these devices. However, the ECG signals did appear to be of lower quality from day 5 onwards. Possible explanations for this include: (i) the electrode contact degraded over time (particularly as one of the electrodes was not replaced over the course of the 7 days); and (ii) there was mains interference (such as on Day 6).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-signal-samples-over-the-7-days-of-testing-left-the-reference-ecg-chest-patch-right-the-ppg-wristband&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**Signal samples over the 7 days of testing:** (left) the reference ECG chest patch; (right) the PPG wristband.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/sig_samples_hu15ad6f5060b9a6bf10cfc1396fe41f75_183156_5fc46b0903d22784a8c111f9d556bda0.png 400w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/sig_samples_hu15ad6f5060b9a6bf10cfc1396fe41f75_183156_00ad3b5778b4648d897ea36a640b9318.png 760w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/sig_samples_hu15ad6f5060b9a6bf10cfc1396fe41f75_183156_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/sig_samples_hu15ad6f5060b9a6bf10cfc1396fe41f75_183156_5fc46b0903d22784a8c111f9d556bda0.png&#34;
               width=&#34;568&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Signal samples over the 7 days of testing:&lt;/strong&gt; (left) the reference ECG chest patch; (right) the PPG wristband.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inter-beat intervals:&lt;/strong&gt; Minute-long samples of ECG chest-patch and PPG wristband signals are shown below, as well as inter-beat intervals derived from the signals. The close agreement between inter-beat intervals derived from the two signals shows that it is possible to obtain reliable inter-beat intervals from these devices.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-signals-and-inter-beat-intervals-obtained-from-i-the-ppg-wristband-ii-the-reference-ecg-chest-patch&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**Signals and inter-beat intervals:** obtained from (i) the PPG wristband; (ii) the reference ECG chest patch.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/IBI_samples_hue438850cab77d7624a51639d2ff3b18f_126745_480ee227d7af7bf2cbb09ed8d887ab91.png 400w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/IBI_samples_hue438850cab77d7624a51639d2ff3b18f_126745_9fcec4a4b4a6de4500398bd49ecffc03.png 760w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/IBI_samples_hue438850cab77d7624a51639d2ff3b18f_126745_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/IBI_samples_hue438850cab77d7624a51639d2ff3b18f_126745_480ee227d7af7bf2cbb09ed8d887ab91.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;422&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Signals and inter-beat intervals:&lt;/strong&gt; obtained from (i) the PPG wristband; (ii) the reference ECG chest patch.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ecg-data-quality&#34;&gt;ECG data quality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon further inspection, it became clear that the ECG was of high quality until approximately 4 days (94 hours) into the recording. After then, the ECG was mostly of low quality. The change from high to low quality is shown in the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-ecg-signals-throughout-the-testing-short-2-second-samples-of-ecg-signals-obtained-through-the-65-days-of-testing-_defintion-hr---hour_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**ECG signals throughout the testing:** Short 2-second samples of ECG signals obtained through the 6.5 days of testing. _Defintion: Hr - hour_&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_samples_hu7bddf102370eae33f72f90eaa3a8be81_214949_b614c8f97d7417a1870908e39a61dd9a.png 400w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_samples_hu7bddf102370eae33f72f90eaa3a8be81_214949_0a90096b9a7caaa77f2ec68b39dc29c8.png 760w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_samples_hu7bddf102370eae33f72f90eaa3a8be81_214949_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_samples_hu7bddf102370eae33f72f90eaa3a8be81_214949_b614c8f97d7417a1870908e39a61dd9a.png&#34;
               width=&#34;568&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;ECG signals throughout the testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Short 2-second samples of ECG signals obtained through the 6.5 days of testing. &lt;em&gt;Defintion: Hr - hour&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-ecg-signals-during-the-second-half-of-testing-short-2-second-samples-of-ecg-signals-in-the-second-half-of-testing-most-samples-before-96-hours-were-of-high-quality-whereas-most-after-this-time-point-were-of-low-quality-_defintion-hr---hour_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**ECG signals during the second half of testing** Short 2-second samples of ECG signals in the second half of testing. Most samples before 96 hours were of high quality, whereas most after this time point were of low quality. _Defintion: Hr - hour_&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_change_qual_hu7134c3a1a4e33878ff44d89f1c092797_331333_853d642d745ad30f99245b3245630490.png 400w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_change_qual_hu7134c3a1a4e33878ff44d89f1c092797_331333_b4d02b105fbbeb220404c834099aa13d.png 760w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_change_qual_hu7134c3a1a4e33878ff44d89f1c092797_331333_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_change_qual_hu7134c3a1a4e33878ff44d89f1c092797_331333_853d642d745ad30f99245b3245630490.png&#34;
               width=&#34;568&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;ECG signals during the second half of testing&lt;/strong&gt; Short 2-second samples of ECG signals in the second half of testing. Most samples before 96 hours were of high quality, whereas most after this time point were of low quality. &lt;em&gt;Defintion: Hr - hour&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-points&#34;&gt;Learning points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learnt several things from the testing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low battery alarm&lt;/strong&gt;: The ECG chest-patch sounded a (loud) low battery alarm, waking up the user. I realised that this functionality could have been turned off, and this should be done in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Closing apps&lt;/strong&gt;: The process used to close apps was unreliable, and should be refined (perhaps by closing apps one at a time, rather than attempting to close them all using the &amp;lsquo;Close All&amp;rsquo; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ECG signal quality&lt;/strong&gt;: ECG signal quality may have degraded over the course of the study, so it would be helpful to investigate how often electrodes should be changed (and also whether the presence of mains devices affects ECG signal quality).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;remaining-questions&#34;&gt;Remaining questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ECG chest-patch battery life:&lt;/strong&gt; Although the device was removed early due to a low battery alarm, it is not clear whether the device could have continued recording for the remaining 0.5 days. When it was connected to a computer the device had approximately 35% battery remaining, indicated that perhaps it could last 7 days. The file size for the ECG signal was 140 MB (leaving over 3GB spare) indicating that the internal storage may be sufficient to store additional signals such as accelerometry, although it&amp;rsquo;s not clear whether turning on the accelerometry would reduce battery life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chest-patch connector&lt;/strong&gt;: The chest-patch connector had three electrode connections, but only two were used in this testing. It would be good to find out whether a connector with only two connections is available, which would avoid having a spare connector hanging loosely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having identified suitable devices for the SAFER Wearables Study, the next steps are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To purchase the necessary devices to start the study&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To amend the participant-facing documentation to include pictures and detailed instructions on how to use the devices (and submit this for ethical approval).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make the automated data acquisition process (streaming data from wristbands to the mobile phone) as robust as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To investigate whether the additional functionality of the ECG chest-patch could be used whilst still having enough battery life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The &#39;Respiratory rate algorithms for wearables&#39; project</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/the-respiratory-rate-algorithms-for-wearables-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/the-respiratory-rate-algorithms-for-wearables-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- &lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Click on the **Slides** button above to view the built-in slides feature. --&gt;
&lt;!--
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Realising the potential of wearables</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/realising_potential_wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/realising_potential_wearables/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Respiratory rate algorithms for wearables</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/rr-wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/rr-wearables/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The project aims to provide an algorithm to estimate respiratory rate from wearable photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals for use in daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details on the project are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/RRest/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Realising the potential of wearables for health monitoring</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/realising-the-potential-of-wearables-for-health-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/realising-the-potential-of-wearables-for-health-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- &lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Click on the **Slides** button above to view the built-in slides feature. --&gt;
&lt;!--
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SAFER Wearables Study</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/safer-wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/safer-wearables/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The SAFER Wearables Study:&lt;/strong&gt; A study of the acceptability and performance of wearables for atrial fibrillation screening in older adults&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atrial fibrillation (AF) is an irregular heart rhythm which causes a five-fold increase in the risk of stroke. Approximately one in ten people aged over 70 have AF. If AF is recognised then the risk of stroke can be reduced by taking tablets regularly. AF can be difficult to recognise as it can occur without symptoms and only intermittently. Consequently, AF is not recognised in many people, meaning they live with an increased risk of stroke. Therefore, it is important to find ways to identify AF more reliably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, wearable devices have been developed which could be useful for identifying AF. Several devices can monitor heart activity in daily life, including wristbands, smart watches and chest patch monitors. The aim of this study is to assess the acceptability and performance of wearables for use in AF screening in older adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary objective is to determine the feasibility of measuring inter-beat-intervals using a wristband.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secondary objectives are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To determine the acceptability of wearables,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To determine the acceptability of the screening approach,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To assess the performance of wearables for acquiring signals,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To assess the performance of signal processing algorithms,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To assess the performance of wearables for AF screening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;who-can-participate&#34;&gt;Who can participate?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selected people who have previously participated in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SAFER Programme&lt;/a&gt; can participate in this study. The Investigators (at the University of Cambridge) will invite previous SAFER Programme participants to also participate in this study, aiming to enrol 65 without AF, and 65 with AF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-does-the-study-involve&#34;&gt;What does the study involve?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will be asked to wear three devices for seven days: Two wristbands (like watches), and one chest patch (like a plaster). These devices will collect measurements of their heart&amp;rsquo;s activity. The Investigators will also ask participants to tell them how they found wearing the devices by completing a questionnaire. The Investigators will compare how participants found wearing each device, and how accurately each device identifies AF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;further-information&#34;&gt;Further Information&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further information on the study can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04715555&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An impedance pneumography signal quality index: Design, assessment and application to respiratory rate monitoring</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/imp_sqi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/imp_sqi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acquiring wearable photoplethysmography data in daily life: The PPG Diary Pilot Study</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_diary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_diary/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Screening for atrial fibrillation: Improving efficiency of manual review of handheld electrocardiograms</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/reviewing_ecgs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/reviewing_ecgs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conducting a systematic review</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/systematic_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/systematic_review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When looking for articles on a particular subject, search engines can quickly produce a wealth of information at our fingertips: 15,400 results in just 0.1 seconds in the search below. In this post I explore the challenge of using search engines to find as much useful literature as possible, whilst not spending all day (or in this case, several months) doing it!&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-quick-search-reveals-thousands-and-thousands-and-thousands-of-results&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A quick search reveals thousands and thousands and thousands of results.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/systematic_review/featured_hu7fd5934ada8eac26f64bcb39704ecc10_238125_aac4b19007ec4bc96aa7c3a35866a672.png 400w,
               /post/systematic_review/featured_hu7fd5934ada8eac26f64bcb39704ecc10_238125_ad4d8f8052d919057ef1045aa376753e.png 760w,
               /post/systematic_review/featured_hu7fd5934ada8eac26f64bcb39704ecc10_238125_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/systematic_review/featured_hu7fd5934ada8eac26f64bcb39704ecc10_238125_aac4b19007ec4bc96aa7c3a35866a672.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;393&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A quick search reveals thousands and thousands and thousands of results.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my &lt;a href=&#34;https://theses.eurasip.org/theses/829/continuous-respiratory-rate-monitoring-to-detect/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PhD&lt;/a&gt; I spent many a happy hour looking through the literature on algorithms to estimate respiratory rate from two signals often measured by wearables: the photoplethysmogram and the electrocardiogram. I wanted to find the best algorithm out there, which I assumed meant trawling through every last bit of literature until I found it. In 2017 we published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/RBME.2017.2763681&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;systematic review&lt;/a&gt; of these algorithms, and two of the lessons I learnt stick with me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not all search engines are created equal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One search engine just isn&amp;rsquo;t enough (but how many are?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need lots of search terms (but if you&amp;rsquo;re not careful you&amp;rsquo;ll get lots of junk)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the rest of this post I provide insights into these two dilemmas, drawing on the results from our systematic review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;not-all-search-engines-are-created-equal&#34;&gt;Not all search engines are created equal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our review we used five search engines, and our own manual searching, to find the 196 publications included in the review. The five search engines returned vastly different proportions of the 196 publications that were eventually included:&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-coverage-of-the-five-search-engines-the-percentage-of-the-publications-which-were-included-in-the-review-returned-by-each-search-engine&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The coverage of the five search engines: the percentage of the publications which were included in the review returned by each search engine.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/systematic_review/search_engine_coverage_hu0f2718ad2fdfbf44821fe0ba76762b20_52154_4c6331d09eb762fce451bfcdaa3d00ed.png 400w,
               /post/systematic_review/search_engine_coverage_hu0f2718ad2fdfbf44821fe0ba76762b20_52154_9be67b1800f73cfc1e8455ea3ab9e44a.png 760w,
               /post/systematic_review/search_engine_coverage_hu0f2718ad2fdfbf44821fe0ba76762b20_52154_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/systematic_review/search_engine_coverage_hu0f2718ad2fdfbf44821fe0ba76762b20_52154_4c6331d09eb762fce451bfcdaa3d00ed.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;380&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The coverage of the five search engines: the percentage of the publications which were included in the review returned by each search engine.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one end, Scopus returned 61% of the publications (119 out of the 196 included publications). At the other end, Science Direct returned only 10%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take home message:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;A single search engine probably won&amp;rsquo;t return all the results of interest.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in how much time it takes to download the results from each search engine. In our review we downloaded the results as text files from four of the search engines, and manually copied out the results for one search engine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Search Engine&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Method used to download results&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Copied by hand as no convenient method was available to download results&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IEEE Xplore&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Downloaded as CSV (comma-separated values) file&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pubmed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Downloaded as CSV (comma-separated values) file&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Science Direct&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Downloaded as .bib (Bibtex) file&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Scopus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Downloaded as CSV (comma-separated values) file&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take home message:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Some search engines allow you to easily download the results, others don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have your results, you then need to screen them to identify the relevant publications for inclusion in the review. This can be time-consuming, so ideally you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want to have to screen too many publications for each one finally included. The number of publications we screened per relevant result also varied greatly between search engines:&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-number-of-publications-which-had-to-be-screened-to-obtain-each-relevant-result-for-each-search-engine&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The number of publications which had to be screened to obtain each relevant result, for each search engine.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/systematic_review/number_screened_hua6bbd43f4693f9ea2c27e2d89257c8b2_52336_839c9237ee3e5ea34d14610377523dc4.png 400w,
               /post/systematic_review/number_screened_hua6bbd43f4693f9ea2c27e2d89257c8b2_52336_39d7367124be84a324b75945ab07033b.png 760w,
               /post/systematic_review/number_screened_hua6bbd43f4693f9ea2c27e2d89257c8b2_52336_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/systematic_review/number_screened_hua6bbd43f4693f9ea2c27e2d89257c8b2_52336_839c9237ee3e5ea34d14610377523dc4.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;380&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The number of publications which had to be screened to obtain each relevant result, for each search engine.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take home message:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;The time taken to screen results varies greatly between search engines.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you must use only one search engine, choose well, as their performance and ease of use differ greatly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-search-engine-just-isnt-enough-but-how-many-are&#34;&gt;One search engine just isn&amp;rsquo;t enough (but how many are?)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most comprehensive results came from Scopus, which found 119 out of the 196 publications, but if we&amp;rsquo;d only used that then we&amp;rsquo;d have missed nearly 40% of the articles we were looking for. So, one search engine just isn&amp;rsquo;t enough &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how many are? Google Scholar returned a huge 383 potentially relevant results, which were copied down by hand (as they couldn&amp;rsquo;t be exported). In the end, only 14% of these were relevant (it took a while to find that out). At this rate, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t keen to add more search engines in to the mix. I looked back at how many results we would have obtained when using different numbers of search engines:&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-number-of-relevant-results-that-we-would-have-obtained-according-to-how-many-search-engines-were-used&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The number of relevant results that we would have obtained, according to how many search engines were used.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/systematic_review/number_search_engines_hu83d8c0c3d1a06287842925adccfc7d7b_40453_cb733644c2edf9ea28374242acadbcb5.png 400w,
               /post/systematic_review/number_search_engines_hu83d8c0c3d1a06287842925adccfc7d7b_40453_4dfa8384654005b935c86b14db306e03.png 760w,
               /post/systematic_review/number_search_engines_hu83d8c0c3d1a06287842925adccfc7d7b_40453_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/systematic_review/number_search_engines_hu83d8c0c3d1a06287842925adccfc7d7b_40453_cb733644c2edf9ea28374242acadbcb5.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;380&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The number of relevant results that we would have obtained, according to how many search engines were used.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how many search engines are enough? In this search there was some benefit to increasing the number of search engines from one to four, but there was no benefit to using a fifth search engine. You&amp;rsquo;ll note that even all the search engines together returned only 150 out of 196 of the relevant publications included in the review: the remainder were identified manually (through web searching and reading the literature).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take home message:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;It is advisable to use several search engines alongside manual searching.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-need-lots-of-search-terms-but-if-youre-not-careful-youll-get-lots-of-junk&#34;&gt;You need lots of search terms (but if you&amp;rsquo;re not careful you&amp;rsquo;ll get lots of junk)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this review we aimed to obtain as many relevant results as possible from search engines, whilst minimising the amount of work required to screen the results. This meant choosing the search terms carefully. To do so we:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performed an initial manual search:&lt;/strong&gt; this identified 90 relevant publications, which were mostly already known to us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identified key themes from publication titles:&lt;/strong&gt; we reviewed the titles of these 90 publications to identify three key themes contained within the titles:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the process of respiration (e.g. &lt;em&gt;breathing&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a mathematical process (e.g. &lt;em&gt;algorithm&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the input signal (e.g. &lt;em&gt;photoplethysmogram&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identified keywords for each theme:&lt;/strong&gt; we identified keywords corresponding to each theme which occurred in at least 5% of titles. We found:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 keywords for &amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;the process of respiration&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15 keywords for &amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;a mathematical process&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9 keywords for &amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;the input signal&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eliminated keywords which did not add value:&lt;/strong&gt; we then looked at the proportion of publications which would have been identified had we insisted on the titles containing at least one keyword from each theme (76.7%). We then eliminated 10 keywords which, individually, did not add value to this search.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finalised the search strategy:&lt;/strong&gt; The final search strategy, which encompassed 75.6% of the 90 manually identified publications was to insist on a publication containing at least one of the following keywords for each theme:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Theme&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Keywords&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;respiration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;breathing, respiration, respiratory&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mathematical process&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;derivation, derived, estimation, extraction, methods, rate, rates&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;input signal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ECG, electrocardiogram, photoplethysmogram, photoplethysmographic, photoplethysmography, PPG, pulse&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result was that our search identified 642 publications, 31% of which were deemed to be relevant, leading to the 196 publications which were finally included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take home message:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Choose keywords carefully to avoid getting too much junk.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested to find out more then you can read the review &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/RBME.2017.2763681&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the content for this post was adapted under the &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 3.0 Licence&lt;/a&gt; from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P. H. Charlton et al., &amp;lsquo;&#39;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/RBME.2017.2763681&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Breathing rate estimation from the electrocardiogram and photoplethysmogram: a review&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rsquo;&#39; &lt;em&gt;IEEE Rev. Biomed. Eng.&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 11, pp. 2-20, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;appendix-reproducing-the-results&#34;&gt;Appendix: reproducing the results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This appendix describes how to reproduce the results described and illustrated in this blog, and also the results presented in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/RBME.2017.2763681&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;review paper&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;NB: You will need Matlab software to reproduce these results. The files required are available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3741463&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3741463&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;optimising-the-search-strategy&#34;&gt;Optimising the search strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/3741463/files/BRLitReviewSearchStrategy.m?download=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BRLitReviewSearchStrategy.m&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; script reproduces the analysis used to optimise the search strategy, and generate the search strings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conducting-the-search&#34;&gt;Conducting the search&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the _&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/3741463/files/BR_lit_review_suppl_mat.pdf?download=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BR_lit_review_suppl_mat.pdf&lt;/a&gt; file (Section S1.D) within the article&amp;rsquo;s supplementary material for details of how to reproduce the search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;analysing-the-search-results&#34;&gt;Analysing the search results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/3741463/files/BRReviewAnalyses.m?download=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BRReviewAnalyses.m&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to obtain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The screening process results (as described in the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/3741463/files/BR_lit_review_suppl_mat.pdf?download=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BR_lit_review_suppl_mat.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; file (Section S1.C) within the article&amp;rsquo;s supplementary material).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The plots in this blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The results of the analysis of individual articles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will also need the &lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/3741463/files/BRReviewScreeningResults.xlsx?download=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BRReviewScreeningResults.xlsx&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/3741463/files/BRReviewMethodologiesData.xlsx?download=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BRReviewMethodologiesData.xlsx&lt;/a&gt; files to reproduce these results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling arterial pulse waves in healthy aging: a database for in silico evaluation of hemodynamics and pulse wave indexes</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;prize&#34;&gt;Prize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awarded the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kcl.ac.uk/news/biomedeng18-peter-charlton-wins-early-career-researcher-award-copy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Best Early Career Researcher Award&lt;/a&gt; for a presentation on this work at the &lt;em&gt;BioMedEng18&lt;/em&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathing rate estimation from the electrocardiogram and photoplethysmogram: a review</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;prize&#34;&gt;Prize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awarded the 3rd Prize in the 2021 IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Prize Paper Award.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcript for: An Introduction to Pulse Wave Modelling</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_transcript/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_transcript/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This transcript accompanies &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the transcript content is reproduced from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt; under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;title-slide&#34;&gt;Title Slide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topic for today:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using modelling to simulate pulse waves for research and development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal introduction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biomedical engineer specialising in signal processing for wearables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Institutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Current interests, and interests in vascular ageing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-pulse-wave-modelling-using-a-1d-model&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Pulse Wave Modelling using a 1D Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve used modelling in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;my research&lt;/a&gt; to simulate pulse waves, to investigate how vascular age can be assessed from arterial pulse waves. I&amp;rsquo;ve found it a useful tool for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding physiological mechanisms&lt;/strong&gt;: Investigating what physiological mechanisms cause the changes in pulse waves that occur with age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Designing algorithms&lt;/strong&gt;: Designing algorithms to assess vascular age, by developing them using data from simulated subjects across a wide range of ages, and a wide range of cardiovascular properties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investigating algorithm performance&lt;/strong&gt;: Investigating which cardiovascular properties can affect algorithm performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this session I&amp;rsquo;ll provide a brief overview of how this particular model works, and then demonstrate its utility through case studies. I&amp;rsquo;ll conclude with some thoughts on the limitations, benefits and opportunities of this type of modelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may find it helpful to have the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; in front of you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the session I&amp;rsquo;ll ask a few questions, which you can contribute to either verbally, or through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;online poll&lt;/a&gt;. Do feel free to interrupt at any point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1d-modelling&#34;&gt;1D Modelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model that I have used in my work is summarised in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-one-dimensional-model-of-pulse-wave-propagation-a-and-simulated-pulse-waves-b-_source-ph-charlton-et-al-doi-101152ajpheart002182019httpsdoiorg101152ajpheart002182019-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420001.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;**The one-dimensional model of pulse wave propagation (A) and simulated pulse waves (B).** _Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: [10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019](https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019) ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;The one-dimensional model of pulse wave propagation (A) and simulated pulse waves (B).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-model&#34;&gt;The Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This 1D model simulates blood flow, starting with flow into the aorta, then through the major arteries, and finally into the microcirculation. It consists of three main parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aortic Inflow:&lt;/strong&gt; The flow from the left ventricle into the aorta is specified. It is defined by several parameters, as illustrated in the image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arterial Network:&lt;/strong&gt; The larger arteries of the body are specified in the model. The arteries are assumed to be thin, deformable, cylindrical tubes. They have a specified length, luminal diameter, and wall properties (such as arterial stiffness).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vascular Beds:&lt;/strong&gt; The vascular beds are themselves modelled using 0D (Windkessel) models, each with a specified resistance and compliance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;simulated-pulse-waves&#34;&gt;Simulated Pulse Waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulse waves can be simulated at any of the large arteries, as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-pressure-p-and-flow-velocity-u-luminal-area-a-and-photoplethysmogram-ppg-pulse-waves-simulated-at-common-measurements-sites-_source-ph-charlton-et-al-doi-101152ajpheart002182019httpsdoiorg101152ajpheart002182019-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420005.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Pressure (P) and flow velocity (U), luminal area (A) and photoplethysmogram (PPG) pulse waves simulated at common measurements sites. _Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: [10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019](https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019) ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Pressure (P) and flow velocity (U), luminal area (A) and photoplethysmogram (PPG) pulse waves simulated at common measurements sites. &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image shows the different types of waveforms which the model can simulate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blood pressure (P)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blood flow velocity (U):&lt;/strong&gt; The speed at which blood flows through an artery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luminal area (A):&lt;/strong&gt; The cross-sectional area of an artery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photoplethysmogram (PPG):&lt;/strong&gt; An optical measure of blood volume in a vascular bed, commonly measured by pulse oximeters and digital wearable devices (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; smartwatches and fitness trackers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the benefits of this type of modelling is that it allows waveforms to be simulated at multiple sites, and, it also captures the pulse transit times between different sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model-limitations&#34;&gt;Model Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;What are the limitations of the model?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;possible-limitations&#34;&gt;Possible Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;A few thoughts&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Periodic inflow, as opposed to normal heart rate variability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specified arterial properties, which may not be representative of a particular individual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not able to model venous flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;input-parameters&#34;&gt;Input Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model requires a plethora of &amp;lsquo;input parameters&amp;rsquo; (&lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;settings&amp;rsquo;), such as the heart rate, stiffness of each artery, and systemic vascular resistance. Some of these parameters have a marked impact on the simulated pulse waves, whereas others have only a small impact. For instance, the image below shows how the variation of each of the following input parameters impacts the simulated carotid and radial waveforms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HR: heart rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SV: stroke volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LVET: left ventricular ejection time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PFT: time of peak aortic flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RFV: reverse flow volume caused by aortic valve closure at the end of systole&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Length: the length of the ascending aorta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diam: the diameters of the largest arteries (aorta and carotid)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PWV: pulse wave velocities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MAP: mean blood pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PVC: peripheral vascular compliance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt; Which parameters would be most interesting to change, and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt; Which parameters are most relevant to vascular ageing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-2&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (2)&lt;/h2&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-pulse-waves-pws-for-the-25-yr-old-subject-at-the-carotid-artery-a-and-the-radial-artery-b-the-waves-shown-are-at-baseline-black-and-those-obtained-when-increasing-blue-and-decreasing-red-each-parameter-independently-by-1-sd-from-its-baseline-value-_source-ph-charlton-et-al-doi-101152ajpheart002182019httpsdoiorg101152ajpheart002182019-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420003.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;**Pulse waves (PWs) for the 25-yr-old subject at the carotid artery (A) and the radial artery (B).** The waves shown are at baseline (black), and those obtained when increasing (blue) and decreasing (red) each parameter independently by 1 SD from its baseline value. _Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: [10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019](https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019) ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Pulse waves (PWs) for the 25-yr-old subject at the carotid artery (A) and the radial artery (B).&lt;/strong&gt; The waves shown are at baseline (black), and those obtained when increasing (blue) and decreasing (red) each parameter independently by 1 SD from its baseline value. &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discuss figure: which parameters strongly influence the waves, and which don&amp;rsquo;t?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-3&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (3)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A set of input parameters suitable for simulating pulse waves for young adults was proposed by (amongst others) &lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/10.1007/s10439-015-1313-8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mynard and Smolich&lt;/a&gt;. We extended this by proposing a range of parameters to simulate pulse waves for healthy subjects aged 25-75, exhibiting a range of cardiovascular properties. Our proposed ranges of parameters are shown below:&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-proposed-parameters-to-model-healthy-ageing-and-normal-variation-in-cardiovascular-properties-the-mean-solid-line-and-sd-dashed-lines-indicating-1771-and-1772-sd-values-are-shown-for-each-parameter-the-positive-and-negative-sd-values-for-carotid-femoral-pulse-wave-velocities-pwvs-are-different-to-capture-the-positive-skewness-of-this-variables-distribution-the-final-wave-speed-plot-shows-the-baseline-wave-speed-as-a-function-of-diameter-for-each-age-_source-ph-charlton-et-al-doi-101152ajpheart002182019httpsdoiorg101152ajpheart002182019-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420002.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;**Proposed parameters to model healthy ageing and normal variation in cardiovascular properties:** The mean (solid line) and SD (dashed lines indicating &amp;amp;#177;1 and &amp;amp;#177;2 SD) values are shown for each parameter. The positive and negative SD values for carotid-femoral pulse wave velocities (PWVs) are different to capture the positive skewness of this variable&amp;#39;s distribution. The final wave speed plot shows the baseline wave speed as a function of diameter for each age. _Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: [10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019](https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019) ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Proposed parameters to model healthy ageing and normal variation in cardiovascular properties:&lt;/strong&gt; The mean (solid line) and SD (dashed lines indicating ±1 and ±2 SD) values are shown for each parameter. The positive and negative SD values for carotid-femoral pulse wave velocities (PWVs) are different to capture the positive skewness of this variable&amp;rsquo;s distribution. The final wave speed plot shows the baseline wave speed as a function of diameter for each age. &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ranges of parameters are based on a review of those reported in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-set-of-virtual-subjects&#34;&gt;A set of Virtual Subjects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aimed to create a set of virtual subjects representative of a sample of healthy subjects aged 25-75 years old. To do so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baseline subject at each age:&lt;/strong&gt; We created a baseline subject for each age (25 to 75, in 10 year intervals), using the mean value of each parameter at that age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Varying parameters at each age:&lt;/strong&gt; We then created an additional 728 virtual subjects at each age by varying each parameter by ±1 SD from the mean, and creating a subject with each possible combination of parameters. Only the six most influential parameters were varied (HR, SV, LVET, Diam, PWV, PVR).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database of simulated pulse waves:&lt;/strong&gt; We created a &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;database&lt;/a&gt; of simulated pulse waves for 4,374 virtual subjects (consisting of 729 at each of the six age groups). The database and accompanying code are publicly available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;comparison-with-_in-vivo_-data&#34;&gt;Comparison with &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We verified this approach for simulating pulse waves for subjects of different ages by comparing the simulated pulse waves with &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; pulse waves, as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-comparison-between-simulated-and-in-vivo-pulse-wave-pw-shapes-each-pair-of-plots-shows-in-vivo-pws-on-the-left-and-simulated-pws-on-the-right-pws-are-shown-for-different-ages-in-each-plot-offset-and-normalized-legends-indicate-ages-_source-ph-charlton-et-al-doi-101152ajpheart002182019httpsdoiorg101152ajpheart002182019-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40-some-of-the-in-vivo-data-were-obtained-from-fluck-et-al-doi-103389fphys201400049httpsdoiorg103389fphys201400049-cc-by-30httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby30_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420006.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;**A comparison between simulated and in vivo pulse wave (PW) shapes. Each pair of plots shows in vivo PWs on the left, and simulated PWs on the right. PWs are shown for different ages in each plot, offset and normalized. Legends indicate ages. _Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: [10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019](https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019) ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/)). Some of the in vivo data were obtained from Fluck et al. (doi: [10.3389/fphys.2014.00049](https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2014.00049); [CC-BY 3.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/))_&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      **A comparison between simulated and in vivo pulse wave (PW) shapes. Each pair of plots shows in vivo PWs on the left, and simulated PWs on the right. PWs are shown for different ages in each plot, offset and normalized. Legends indicate ages. &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;). Some of the in vivo data were obtained from Fluck et al. (doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2014.00049&#34;&gt;10.3389/fphys.2014.00049&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&#34;&gt;CC-BY 3.0&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How well did the model perform?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;thoughts-on-performance&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;A few thoughts&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Captured increase in amplitude of second systolic peaks with age in carotid, aortic root and radial pressure waveforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Captured disappearance of second peak of finger PPG waveform with age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonetheless, some marked differences between &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; and simulated waveforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details of the verification of this approach are provided in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2&#34;&gt;Part 2:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-assessing-arterial-stiffness-from-the-photoplethysmogram&#34;&gt;Case Study: Assessing Arterial Stiffness from the Photoplethysmogram&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;digital-wearable-device&#34;&gt;Digital Wearable Device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the limitations of some current techniques for assessing arterial stiffness is that they require specialist equipment and/or specialist operators. A potential alternative is to acquire pulse waves using consumer devices worn in daily life, such as smartwatches or fitness trackers (shown below).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-wrist-worn-device-which-acquires-pulse-waves-by-photoplethysmography-_source-ph-charlton-max-health-bandhttpscommonswikimediaorgwikicategoryfiles_by_peter_h_charltonmediafilemax_health_bandjpg-wikimedia-commons-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/dc/Max_Health_Band.jpg/640px-Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;**A wrist-worn device which acquires pulse waves by photoplethysmography.** _Source: PH Charlton, [Max-Health-Band](https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Files_by_Peter_H_Charlton#/media/File:Max_Health_Band.jpg), Wikimedia Commons ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;A wrist-worn device which acquires pulse waves by photoplethysmography.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton, &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Files_by_Peter_H_Charlton#/media/File:Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34;&gt;Max-Health-Band&lt;/a&gt;, Wikimedia Commons (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-photoplethysmogram-ppg&#34;&gt;The Photoplethysmogram (PPG)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital wearable devices typically use photoplethysmography to acquire pulse waves:&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-simplified-origins-of-the-photoplethysmogram-ppg-signal-arterial-blood-venous-blood-and-other-tissues-_source-ph-charlton-photoplethysmogram-signal-componentshttpscommonswikimediaorgwikifilephotoplethysmogram_signal_componentssvg-wikimedia-commons-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg/640px-Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;**Simplified origins of the photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal: arterial blood, venous blood and other tissues.** _Source: PH Charlton, [Photoplethysmogram signal components](https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg), Wikimedia Commons ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Simplified origins of the photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal: arterial blood, venous blood and other tissues.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton, &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg&#34;&gt;Photoplethysmogram signal components&lt;/a&gt;, Wikimedia Commons (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;changes-in-ppg-pulse-wave-shape&#34;&gt;Changes in PPG Pulse Wave Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many approaches have been proposed to assess arterial stiffness from the photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal, based on the observation that the PPG pulse wave changes shape with age:&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-classes-of-photoplethysmogram-ppg-pulse-wave-shape-examples-of-the-four-classes-of-pulse-wave-shape-proposed-by-dawber-et-al-generally-the-higher-classes-are-associated-with-older-adults-_source-ph-charlton-classes-of-photoplethysmogram-ppg-pulse-wave-shapehttpscommonswikimediaorgwikifileclasses_of_photoplethysmogram_ppg_pulse_wave_shapesvg-wikimedia-commons-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ed/Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg/640px-Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;**Classes of photoplethysmogram (PPG) pulse wave shape:** Examples of the four classes of pulse wave shape proposed by Dawber et al. Generally, the higher classes are associated with older adults. _Source: PH Charlton, [Classes of photoplethysmogram (PPG) pulse wave shape](https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_(PPG)_pulse_wave_shape.svg), Wikimedia Commons ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Classes of photoplethysmogram (PPG) pulse wave shape:&lt;/strong&gt; Examples of the four classes of pulse wave shape proposed by Dawber et al. Generally, the higher classes are associated with older adults. &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton, &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_(PPG)_pulse_wave_shape.svg&#34;&gt;Classes of photoplethysmogram (PPG) pulse wave shape&lt;/a&gt;, Wikimedia Commons (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessing-arterial-stiffness&#34;&gt;Assessing Arterial Stiffness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods for assessing arterial stiffness from the PPG mostly consist of two steps (as shown below):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying fiducial points (left)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extracting pulse wave features (right)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-pulse-wave-analysis-illustrated-for-a-simulated-pressure-wave-at-the-radial-artery-_source-ph-charlton-et-al-doi-101152ajpheart002182019httpsdoiorg101152ajpheart002182019-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420004.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;**Pulse wave analysis:** Illustrated for a simulated pressure wave at the radial artery. _Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: [10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019](https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019) ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Pulse wave analysis:&lt;/strong&gt; Illustrated for a simulated pressure wave at the radial artery. &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following three indices were extracted from PPG pulse waves in this case study:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reflection Index (RI, illustrated)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stiffness Index (SI)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modified Aging Index (AGImod)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were calculated for each virtual subject, and then their correlation with the reference aortic PWV was assessed. In addition, we investigated the cardiovascular determinants of each index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-correlation-of-photoplethysmogram-ppg-derived-pulse-wave-pw-indexes-with-aortic-pulse-wave-velocity-pwv-a-and-their-physiological-determinants-b-data-derived-for-all-virtual-subjects-are-shown-in-black-whereas-red-indicates-data-from-45-yr-old-subjects-_source-ph-charlton-et-al-doi-101152ajpheart002182019httpsdoiorg101152ajpheart002182019-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420009.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;The correlation of photoplethysmogram (PPG)-derived pulse wave (PW) indexes with aortic pulse wave velocity (PWV; A), and their physiological determinants (B). Data derived for all virtual subjects are shown in black, whereas red indicates data from 45-yr-old subjects. _Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: [10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019](https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019) ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The correlation of photoplethysmogram (PPG)-derived pulse wave (PW) indexes with aortic pulse wave velocity (PWV; A), and their physiological determinants (B). Data derived for all virtual subjects are shown in black, whereas red indicates data from 45-yr-old subjects. &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overall performance across all ages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance within an individual age group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Influence of not only PWV, but other CV properties (note difference in influence of &amp;lsquo;diam&amp;rsquo;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications&#34;&gt;Implications:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clinical studies should investigate performance over a small age range as well as over the entire cohort to assess the potential utility of indexes for stratifying patients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indexes can also be influenced by HR and SV, indicating that it may be beneficial to assess performance when these CV properties are varied &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would you think of using this technology to assess vascular age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How might it compare to other technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How could one assess the relative performance of such technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WG3 PPG group currently has a paper under review titled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assessing Vascular Age from the Photoplethysmogram: A Systematic Review from VascAgeNet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-3&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-changes-in-pulse-pressure-amplification-with-age&#34;&gt;Case Study: Changes in Pulse Pressure Amplification with Age&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pulse-pressure-amplification&#34;&gt;Pulse Pressure Amplification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\mathrm{Pulse \ Pressure \ Amplification} = \frac{\mathrm{brachial \ pulse \ pressure}}{\mathrm{aortic \ pulse \ pressure}}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does pulse pressure amplification change with age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case study, we investigated the determinants of changes in PPamp with age. To do so, we assessed the effects of age on early systolic amplification and late systolic aortic pressure augmentation, calculated using the aortic PP at P1 and P2, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-1&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-causes-of-changes-in-pulse-pressure-pp-amplification-ppamp-with-age-_source-ph-charlton-et-al-doi-101152ajpheart002182019httpsdoiorg101152ajpheart002182019-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420008.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;The causes of changes in pulse pressure (PP) amplification (PPamp) with age. _Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: [10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019](https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019) ([CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/))._&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The causes of changes in pulse pressure (PP) amplification (PPamp) with age. &lt;br&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: PH Charlton et al., doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt; In A and B: how does the pulse wave change shape with distance from the aortic root to the finger? How does this differ with age?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The profiles demonstrate that two mechanisms influence PPamp (PPamp / PPb/PPa; subscripts &amp;ldquo;a&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;b&amp;rdquo; indicate aortic and brachial, respectively):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The early systolic portion was amplified in both subjects, causing SBPb to be greater than SBPa and therefore PPamp &amp;gt; 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Late systolic aortic pressure augmentation (the increase in pressure from P1a to P2a) was higher in older subjects, increasing PPa and decreasing PPamp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contributions of these mechanisms to PPamp for the whole database are illustrated in panel C. The amplification of the early systolic portion increased with age, as shown in red by PPb/(P1a &amp;gt; DBPa). In contrast, the increase in late systolic aortic pressure augmentation with age (in blue) caused a decrease in PPb/(P2a &amp;gt; DBPa) with age. The effect of aortic pressure augmentation outweighed that of early systolic amplification, meaning PPamp decreased substantially with age, in keeping with in vivo studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early systolic amplification was determined primarily by the diameter of the larger arteries, and late systolic aortic pressure augmentation was largely determined by PWV and LVET, as shown in panels D and E. Indeed, since PPamp was primarily determined by late systolic aortic pressure augmentation, it was largely determined by arterial stiffness (i.e., PWV) and LVET, as shown in panel F. The change in PPamp observed with age was primarily due to changes in aortic pressure wave morphology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications-1&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database can be used to gain insight into the CV determinants of mechanisms of blood flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-4&#34;&gt;Part 4&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;potential-studies-using-blood-flow-modelling&#34;&gt;Potential studies using blood flow modelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;exploring-potential-studies&#34;&gt;Exploring potential studies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a study in which pulse wave modelling could be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would need to be simulated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under what conditions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In which ways would the model need to be particularly accurate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;limitations&#34;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dependent on model accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which in turn, is dependent on input parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often requires specialist knowledge to perform studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allows pulse waves to be simulated under different conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control of physiology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free of measurement error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potentially cheap, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t require participant involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;opportunities&#34;&gt;Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preliminary pilot work in technology development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inform the design of &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the potential shortcomings of existing technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the mechanisms underlying haemodynamic observations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-reading-and-resources&#34;&gt;Further Reading and Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Continuous respiratory rate monitoring to detect clinical deteriorations using wearable sensors</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cont_resp_monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cont_resp_monitoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-text&#34;&gt;Full text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The published version is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://theses.eurasip.org/theses/829/continuous-respiratory-rate-monitoring-to-detect/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extraction of respiratory signals from the electrocardiogram and photoplethysmogram: technical and physiological determinants</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/resp_sig_extraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/resp_sig_extraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;recognition&#34;&gt;Recognition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Featured in &lt;em&gt;Physiological Measurement&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/journal/0967-3334/page/Highlights_of_2017&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Highlights of 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves&#34;&gt;An introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Charlton, University of Cambridge, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;peterhcharlton.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To do:&lt;/strong&gt; Please go to this website, find this talk under &amp;lsquo;Talks&amp;rsquo;, and see the accompanying resources.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-find-simulated-pulse-waves-useful-for&#34;&gt;I find simulated pulse waves useful for:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding physiological mechanisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigating algorithm performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;: click to expand images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The event poll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt; (from which much content in this presentation is reproduced under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-pulse-wave-modelling-using-a-1d-model&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Pulse Wave Modelling using a 1D Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-model&#34;&gt;The Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420001.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420001.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;simulated-pulse-waves&#34;&gt;Simulated Pulse Waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420005.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420005.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Example simulated pulse waves&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model-limitations&#34;&gt;Model Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;What are the limitations of the model?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;possible-limitations&#34;&gt;Possible Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Periodic inflow, as opposed to normal heart rate variability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specified arterial properties, which may not be representative of a particular individual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not able to model venous flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;input-parameters&#34;&gt;Input Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HR: heart rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SV: stroke volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LVET: left ventricular ejection time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PFT: time of peak aortic flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RFV: reverse flow volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diam: the diameters of the largest arteries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PWV: pulse wave velocities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MAP: mean blood pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PVC: peripheral vascular compliance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which parameters would be most interesting to change, and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which are most relevant to vascular ageing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-2&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (2)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420003.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420003.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-3&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (3)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420002.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420002.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;virtual-subjects&#34;&gt;Virtual Subjects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We created:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baseline virtual subject at each age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual subjects at each age with varying cardiovascular properties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A publicly available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;database&lt;/a&gt; of simulated pulse waves for 4,374 virtual subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparison-with-_in-vivo_-data&#34;&gt;Comparison with &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How well did the model perform?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420006.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420006.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;thoughts-on-performance&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase in amplitude of second systolic peaks with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disappearance of second peak of finger PPG with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonetheless, some marked differences between &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; and simulated waveforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further details of the verification see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-assessing-arterial-stiffness-from-the-photoplethysmogram&#34;&gt;Case Study: Assessing Arterial Stiffness from the Photoplethysmogram&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;digital-wearable-device&#34;&gt;Digital Wearable Device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/dc/Max_Health_Band.jpg/640px-Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/dc/Max_Health_Band.jpg/640px-Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-photoplethysmogram-ppg&#34;&gt;The Photoplethysmogram (PPG)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg/640px-Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg/640px-Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;changes-in-ppg-pulse-wave-shape&#34;&gt;Changes in PPG Pulse Wave Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ed/Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg/640px-Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ed/Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg/640px-Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessing-arterial-stiffness&#34;&gt;Assessing Arterial Stiffness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420004.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420004.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420009.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420009.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Age range&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Influence of HR and SV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would you think of using this technology to assess vascular age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How might it compare to other technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How could one assess the relative performance of such technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assessing Vascular Age from the Photoplethysmogram: A Systematic Review from VascAgeNet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-3&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-changes-in-pulse-pressure-amplification-with-age&#34;&gt;Case Study: Changes in Pulse Pressure Amplification with Age&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pulse-pressure-amplification&#34;&gt;Pulse Pressure Amplification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\mathrm{Pulse \ Pressure \ Amplification} = \frac{\mathrm{brachial \ pulse \ pressure}}{\mathrm{aortic \ pulse \ pressure}}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does pulse pressure amplification change with age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigated the effects of age on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early systolic amplification (P1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Late systolic pressure augmentation (P2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;at the aorta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-1&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420008.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420008.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications-1&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database can be used to gain insight into the CV determinants of mechanisms of blood flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When might this be helpful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How should this approach be used:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instead of clinical studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as well as clinical studies, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not at all?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;related-work&#34;&gt;Related Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following for similar work, investigating the accuracy of methods for assessing pulse wave velocity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willemet M &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;A database of virtual healthy subjects to assess the accuracy of foot-to-foot pulse wave velocities for estimation of aortic stiffness&lt;/em&gt;, doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00175.2015&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00175.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-4&#34;&gt;Part 4&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;potential-studies-using-blood-flow-modelling&#34;&gt;Potential studies using blood flow modelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;exploring-potential-studies&#34;&gt;Exploring potential studies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a study in which pulse wave modelling could be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would need to be simulated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under what conditions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In which ways would the model need to be particularly accurate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;limitations&#34;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dependent on model accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which in turn, is dependent on input parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often requires specialist knowledge to perform studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allows pulse waves to be simulated under different conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control of physiology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free of measurement error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potentially cheap, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t require participant involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;opportunities&#34;&gt;Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preliminary pilot work in technology development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inform the design of &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the potential shortcomings of existing technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the mechanisms underlying haemodynamic observations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-resources&#34;&gt;Further Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-you&#34;&gt;Thank you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;peterhcharlton.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See this website for resources.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making reproducible research as natural as breathing</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/reproducible_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/reproducible_research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Peter Charlton whilst a PhD student at King&amp;rsquo;s College London, working on the Hospital of the Future (HotF) project. The overall aim of the HotF project is to provide early identification of hospital patients who are deteriorating. Peter&amp;rsquo;s work focuses on using wearable sensors to continuously assess patients&#39; health.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key aims of the HotF project is to develop a technique to continuously monitor a patient&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;respiratory rate&amp;rdquo;: how often they breathe. Respiratory rate often changes early in the progression of a deterioration, giving advanced warning of a severe event such as a heart attack. However, it is currently measured by hand by counting the number of times a patient breathes in a set period of time. This approach is time-consuming, inaccurate, and only provides intermittent measurements. The alternative approach which I&amp;rsquo;m working on is to estimate respiratory rate from a small, unobtrusive, wearable sensor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wearable sensors are currently routinely used to monitor heart rate and blood oxygenation levels. It turns out that the signals which provide these measurements are subtly influenced by respiration, as demonstrated below. If these subtle changes can be extracted reliably, then we could monitor respiratory rate &amp;ldquo;for free&amp;rdquo;, without the need for any additional sensors. This may provide all-important information on changes in a patient&amp;rsquo;s health, allowing clinicians to identify deteriorating patients earlier.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-heart-rate-is-clearly-visible-in-this-signal-since-each-spike-corresponds-to-a-heart-beat-the-spikes-also-vary-in-height-with-each-of-the-four-breaths-these-subtle-changes-can-be-used-to-estimate-respiratory-rate&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The heart rate is clearly visible in this signal since each spike corresponds to a heart beat. The spikes also vary in height with each of the four breaths. These subtle changes can be used to estimate respiratory rate.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/reproducible_research/featured_hu3e1360d471515a27bee2f20ca91ea161_3104_0ffb3831007b38b75c5015a9f4545527.png 400w,
               /post/reproducible_research/featured_hu3e1360d471515a27bee2f20ca91ea161_3104_3b97e3567e5d0068c43b9679cf0c80f8.png 760w,
               /post/reproducible_research/featured_hu3e1360d471515a27bee2f20ca91ea161_3104_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/reproducible_research/featured_hu3e1360d471515a27bee2f20ca91ea161_3104_0ffb3831007b38b75c5015a9f4545527.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;214&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The heart rate is clearly visible in this signal since each spike corresponds to a heart beat. The spikes also vary in height with each of the four breaths. These subtle changes can be used to estimate respiratory rate.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s all this got to do with reproducible research? Well, over the past few decades over 100 papers have been written describing methods for estimating respiratory rate electronically from signals that are already monitored by wearable sensors. If you read them (it takes a long time) then you find that hundreds of methods have been described. The key questions are: which method is the best, and is it good enough to use in clinical practice? Answering these questions can be a daunting task given how many different methods there are. Very few of the methods are publicly available, so to answer these questions you&amp;rsquo;d have to implement each of the methods yourself. Even once you have done this, you&amp;rsquo;d need to try them out on some data. Collecting this data is no easy task. Altogether, reproducing scientist&amp;rsquo;s previous work on this problem is quite difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m hoping that this won&amp;rsquo;t be such a problem in the future. We have recently implemented many of the methods, collected a benchmark dataset on which to test the methods, and reported the results. All of this is publicly available. What&amp;rsquo;s more, you can &lt;a href=&#34;http://peterhcharlton.github.io/RRest/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;download it all for free&lt;/a&gt;, from the methods, to the data, to the article describing the results. So in a few clicks you can catch up, reproduce our research, and start making progress yourself, even producing methods like this:&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-estimating-respiratory-rate-from-the-electrocardiogram-ecg-and-photoplethysmogram-ppg-signals-a-surrogate-respiratory-signal-can-be-extracted-from-each-of-the-ecg-and-ppg-signals-which-looks-similar-to-a-reference-respiratory-signal-resp-shown-above&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**Estimating respiratory rate from the electrocardiogram (ECG) and photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals:** A surrogate respiratory signal can be extracted from each of the ECG and PPG signals, which looks similar to a reference respiratory signal (Resp), shown above.&#34;
           src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/reproducible_research/petercharlton_resp_video_gif_red.gif&#34;
           loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Estimating respiratory rate from the electrocardiogram (ECG) and photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals:&lt;/strong&gt; A surrogate respiratory signal can be extracted from each of the ECG and PPG signals, which looks similar to a reference respiratory signal (Resp), shown above.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, nearly &amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;ve written a &lt;a href=&#34;http://peterhcharlton.github.io/RRest/waveform_analysis.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on the methods, which is due to be published in a textbook soon. This work can be reproduced exactly. Since then we have extended the range of publicly available resources by adding more methods, and the new benchmark dataset. This most recent work can&amp;rsquo;t be reproduced exactly since we had to make a few changes before making it publicly available. I intend to make future work on this topic fully reproducible so that researchers can build on our work. Who knows, perhaps this will contribute towards earlier identification of deteriorating patients in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally published &lt;a href=&#34;https://kingsimaging.wordpress.com/2016/05/11/making-reproducible-research-as-natural-as-breathing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An assessment of algorithms to estimate respiratory rate from the electrocardiogram and photoplethysmogram</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_algs_assessment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_algs_assessment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;prize&#34;&gt;Prize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awarded the &lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/journal/0967-3334/page/Martin_Black_award&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Martin Black Prize&lt;/a&gt; for the best paper published in &lt;em&gt;Physiological Measurement&lt;/em&gt; in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
