<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>vascular ageing | Peter Charlton</title>
    <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/vascular-ageing/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/vascular-ageing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>vascular ageing</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Peter Charlton</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/media/icon_hu5d370b2f3224e8711b194d151b733caa_16531_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>vascular ageing</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/vascular-ageing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing vascular ageing</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/vascular-ageing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/vascular-ageing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to develop techniques to assess vascular ageing in daily life, providing information on the state of the blood vessels which could be used to personalise cardiovascular treatments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vascular age is an emerging indicator of cardiovascular health that is indicative of cardiovascular risk, and can prompt clinical intervention. The function and structure of blood vessels naturally degrade with age. This process, known as vascular aging, can ultimately result in damage to the heart, kidney, and brain. Indicators of vascular aging have been found to be predictive of cardiovascular morbidity and all-cause mortality, so may be useful for cardiovascular risk stratification. &lt;em&gt;Source: modified from &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00392.2021&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Charlton P.H. et al.&lt;/a&gt;, under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to develop techniques to assess vascular ageing from the photoplethysmogram (PPG) - the pulse wave signal measured by smartwatches, activity trackers, and pulse oximeters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using both simulated and real-world data to design signal processing techniques to extract indicators of vascular ageing from the PPG, and to assess their potential clinical utility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial results are reported in the publications listed below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities for Photoplethysmography in Public Health</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/opportunities-for-photoplethysmography-in-public-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/opportunities-for-photoplethysmography-in-public-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6352971&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1fQ16Cdxxto&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VascAgeNet Photoplethysmography Group</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/vascagenet_ppg_group/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/vascagenet_ppg_group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vascular ageing is a natural process by which the function and structure of blood vessels degrade over time. It can manifest as elevated blood pressure, increased arterial stiffness, and atherosclerosis. Current approaches to assess vascular age have been found to be predictive of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality, but are often not convenient enough for widespread use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This group of European researchers is investigating the use of photoplethysmography to assess vascular age. Photoplethysmography is a non-invasive optical technique for measuring the arterial pulse wave, providing information on the state of the heart and blood vessels. The group is part of the wider &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet network&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;work-to-date&#34;&gt;Work to date&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group have co-authored several publications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;group-papers&#34;&gt;Group papers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review&#34;&gt;Assessing hemodynamics from the photoplethysmogram to gain insights into vascular age: A review from VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A review of techniques to assess vascular age from the photoplethysmogram. Co-authored by 16 researchers from 11 countries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/best_practices_ppg/&#34;&gt;Establishing best practices in photoplethysmography signal acquisition and processing&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;An editorial on whether it would be possible and beneficial to establish best practices for photoplethysmography signal acquisition and processing. Co-authored by 3 group members.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaborative-research&#34;&gt;Collaborative research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_bp_estimation/&#34;&gt;Blood Pressure Estimation Based on Photoplethysmography: Finger versus Wrist&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Comparing blood pressure estimates obtained from finger and wrist sensors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaborative-reviews&#34;&gt;Collaborative reviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A comprehensive overview of the state-of-the-art of wearable photoplethysmography devices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_review&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography for cardiovascular monitoring&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A review of wearable photoplethysmgoraphy, considering the technology, signal processing, and clinical applications.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;invited-talks&#34;&gt;Invited Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following speakers gave invited talks to the group in 2021:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kevin Kotzen&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Benchmarking Photoplethysmography Peak Detection Algorithms Using the Electrocardiogram Signal as a Reference&lt;/em&gt;, 7 October 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Birute Paliakaite&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Blood Pressure Estimation Based on Photoplethysmography: Finger versus Wrist&lt;/em&gt;, 28 October 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc21_bp_estimation/&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wan-Hua Lin&lt;/strong&gt; (Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Science, China): &lt;em&gt;Investigating the physiological mechanisms of the photoplethysmogram features for blood pressure estimation&lt;/em&gt;, 18 November 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6579/ab7d78&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philip Aston&lt;/strong&gt; (National Physical Laboratory, UK): 9 December 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022 group members have given talks in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_webinars/&#34;&gt;public webinar series on Photoplethysmography&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Allen&lt;/strong&gt;: presented on &lt;em&gt;Further explorations in photoplethysmography for the detection of occlusive peripheral arterial disease&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Panicos Kyriacou&lt;/strong&gt;: presented on &lt;em&gt;Non-invasive optical monitoring of Intracranial Pressure in Traumatic Brain Injury patients&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serena Zanelli&lt;/strong&gt;: will present on &lt;em&gt;Deep learning approach to detect signal quality from clinical to non-clinical PPG devices&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/EMBC46164.2021.9629640&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;short-term-scientific-mission&#34;&gt;Short-Term Scientific Mission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Peter Charlton spent 5 days at Kaunas University of Technology (KTU), hosted by Prof Vaidotas Marozas, Director of the Institute of Biomedical Engineering. During this STSM, Vaidotas, Peter and Birute Paliakaite worked with colleagues at KTU towards harmonising photoplethysmography-based techniques for the assessment of vascular ageing. This was funded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/short-term-scientific-missions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-members&#34;&gt;Group Members&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work of the group would not be possible without the hard work of its members, who include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Peter Charlton&lt;/a&gt; is a Biomedical Engineer specialising in signal processing techniques for the photoplethysmogram (PPG), including estimating respiratory rate and assessing vascular age from the PPG. He presently holds a British Heart Foundation Fellowship at the University of Cambridge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=YtQF4uUAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Birute Paliakaite&lt;/a&gt; is a researcher specialising in PPG signal processing and modelling, and has made key contributions on acquiring haemodynamic parameters from wearables, and detecting and modelling arrhythmias in the PPG.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=IJ5MsM4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Kristjan Pilt&lt;/a&gt; has developed novel techniques to assess vascular age from the PPG in his research, and has demonstrated their potential clinical utility in diabetic patients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.at/citations?user=pHHJAv4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Martin Bachler&lt;/a&gt; is a research engineer in the field of clinical diagnostics and therapy support, and specialises in biomedical signal analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vascagenet.eu/what-are-you-working-on-serena-zanelli&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Serena Zanelli&lt;/a&gt; develops machine learning and deep learning models to detect cardiovascular disease from PPG signals acquired by wearables, working in both academic and clinical settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vascagenet.eu/what-are-you-working-on-dr-daniel-kulin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Daniel Kulin&lt;/a&gt; is a medical doctor, researcher and entrepreneur in the field of PPG-based pulse wave analysis and in the development of remote patient monitoring systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.co.uk/citations?user=-GsW3HsAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof John Allen&lt;/a&gt; is a leading researcher in the field of photoplethysmography. He has worked on assessing vascular age from the PPG for approximately 30 years. He has strong experience on developing PPG-based techniques, and translating them towards clinical practice. His seminal review on photoplethysmography has been cited over 3,000 times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Magid-Hallab&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Magid Hallab&lt;/a&gt; is a physician, inventor of pOpmetre, a device for PPG-based pulse wave velocity measurement, and CEO of Axelife, the company who sell the pOpmetre device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.it/citations?user=rQqSulEAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Elisabetta Bianchini&lt;/a&gt; works in the field of ultrasound imaging and cardiovascular bioengineering, with strong interests in technology transfer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.at/citations?user=gRActvYAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Christopher Mayer&lt;/a&gt; conducts research in the field of biomedical signal processing, including simulation and pulse wave analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=w1KRD3gAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Dimitrios Terentes-Printzios&lt;/a&gt; is a Cardiologist with research interests in hypertension and microvascular dysfunction. He conducted his PhD on vascular ageing and has co-organised and large multicentre studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/verena-dittrich-1876a989/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Verena Dittrich&lt;/a&gt; is Co-Founder and CEO of Redwave Medical, a company specialising in algorithms for cardiovascular assessment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=VP9nyHAAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Bernhard Hametner&lt;/a&gt; is a mathematician developing methods for pulse wave analysis, and is involved in the analysis of cardiovascular parameters obtained in clinical studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Z_Fojr4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mr Dave Veerasingam&lt;/a&gt; is a Consultant Cardiothoracic Surgeon, and is involved in the cardiac Medtech industry. His research interests include the association between vascular ageing and target organ damage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Dejan-Zikic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Dejan Zikic&lt;/a&gt; is an Associate Professor in Biophysics, with research interests including modelling pulse wave propagation and pulse wave analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.lt/citations?user=yQcWpoIAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Vaidotas Marozas&lt;/a&gt; is Director of the Biomedical Engineering Institute at Kaunas Institute of Technology, and has conducted research into PPG modelling, analysis, and acquisition using wearables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing hemodynamics from the photoplethysmogram to gain insights into vascular age: A review from VascAgeNet</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/vascagenet_ppg_group/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for further details of VascAgeNet and the PPG group which conducted this work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging the potential of machine learning for assessing vascular ageing: state-of-the-art and future research</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ml_vasc_age_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ml_vasc_age_review/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please see the links above for the resources accompanying this talk. During the talk, you will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The event poll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the talk, you may be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_transcript/&#34;&gt;The transcript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;The accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;, and accompanying &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photoplethysmography in a minute (and a bit)</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/photoplethysmography-in-a-minute-and-a-bit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/photoplethysmography-in-a-minute-and-a-bit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6193070&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HnXDvN4WNX8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A database for developing pulse wave analysis algorithms</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/a-database-for-developing-pulse-wave-analysis-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/a-database-for-developing-pulse-wave-analysis-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please see the links above for the resources accompanying this talk, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/1413662/files/20180907%20Pulse%20Wave%20Database%20%28Public%29.pdf?download=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X8aPZFs8c08&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;The accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;, and accompanying &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves&#34;&gt;An introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Charlton, University of Cambridge, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;peterhcharlton.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To do:&lt;/strong&gt; Please go to this website, find this talk under &amp;lsquo;Talks&amp;rsquo;, and see the accompanying resources.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-find-simulated-pulse-waves-useful-for&#34;&gt;I find simulated pulse waves useful for:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding physiological mechanisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigating algorithm performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;: click to expand images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The event poll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt; (from which much content in this presentation is reproduced under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-pulse-wave-modelling-using-a-1d-model&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Pulse Wave Modelling using a 1D Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-model&#34;&gt;The Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420001.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420001.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;simulated-pulse-waves&#34;&gt;Simulated Pulse Waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420005.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420005.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Example simulated pulse waves&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model-limitations&#34;&gt;Model Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;What are the limitations of the model?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;possible-limitations&#34;&gt;Possible Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Periodic inflow, as opposed to normal heart rate variability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specified arterial properties, which may not be representative of a particular individual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not able to model venous flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;input-parameters&#34;&gt;Input Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HR: heart rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SV: stroke volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LVET: left ventricular ejection time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PFT: time of peak aortic flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RFV: reverse flow volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diam: the diameters of the largest arteries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PWV: pulse wave velocities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MAP: mean blood pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PVC: peripheral vascular compliance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which parameters would be most interesting to change, and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which are most relevant to vascular ageing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-2&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (2)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420003.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420003.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-3&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (3)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420002.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420002.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;virtual-subjects&#34;&gt;Virtual Subjects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We created:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baseline virtual subject at each age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual subjects at each age with varying cardiovascular properties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A publicly available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;database&lt;/a&gt; of simulated pulse waves for 4,374 virtual subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparison-with-_in-vivo_-data&#34;&gt;Comparison with &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How well did the model perform?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420006.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420006.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;thoughts-on-performance&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase in amplitude of second systolic peaks with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disappearance of second peak of finger PPG with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonetheless, some marked differences between &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; and simulated waveforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further details of the verification see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-assessing-arterial-stiffness-from-the-photoplethysmogram&#34;&gt;Case Study: Assessing Arterial Stiffness from the Photoplethysmogram&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;digital-wearable-device&#34;&gt;Digital Wearable Device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/dc/Max_Health_Band.jpg/640px-Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/dc/Max_Health_Band.jpg/640px-Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-photoplethysmogram-ppg&#34;&gt;The Photoplethysmogram (PPG)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg/640px-Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg/640px-Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;changes-in-ppg-pulse-wave-shape&#34;&gt;Changes in PPG Pulse Wave Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ed/Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg/640px-Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ed/Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg/640px-Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessing-arterial-stiffness&#34;&gt;Assessing Arterial Stiffness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420004.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420004.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420009.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420009.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Age range&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Influence of HR and SV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would you think of using this technology to assess vascular age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How might it compare to other technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How could one assess the relative performance of such technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assessing Vascular Age from the Photoplethysmogram: A Systematic Review from VascAgeNet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-3&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-changes-in-pulse-pressure-amplification-with-age&#34;&gt;Case Study: Changes in Pulse Pressure Amplification with Age&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pulse-pressure-amplification&#34;&gt;Pulse Pressure Amplification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\mathrm{Pulse \ Pressure \ Amplification} = \frac{\mathrm{brachial \ pulse \ pressure}}{\mathrm{aortic \ pulse \ pressure}}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does pulse pressure amplification change with age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigated the effects of age on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early systolic amplification (P1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Late systolic pressure augmentation (P2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;at the aorta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-1&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420008.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420008.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications-1&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database can be used to gain insight into the CV determinants of mechanisms of blood flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When might this be helpful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How should this approach be used:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instead of clinical studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as well as clinical studies, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not at all?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;related-work&#34;&gt;Related Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following for similar work, investigating the accuracy of methods for assessing pulse wave velocity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willemet M &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;A database of virtual healthy subjects to assess the accuracy of foot-to-foot pulse wave velocities for estimation of aortic stiffness&lt;/em&gt;, doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00175.2015&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00175.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-4&#34;&gt;Part 4&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;potential-studies-using-blood-flow-modelling&#34;&gt;Potential studies using blood flow modelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;exploring-potential-studies&#34;&gt;Exploring potential studies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a study in which pulse wave modelling could be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would need to be simulated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under what conditions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In which ways would the model need to be particularly accurate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;limitations&#34;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dependent on model accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which in turn, is dependent on input parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often requires specialist knowledge to perform studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allows pulse waves to be simulated under different conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control of physiology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free of measurement error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potentially cheap, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t require participant involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;opportunities&#34;&gt;Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preliminary pilot work in technology development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inform the design of &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the potential shortcomings of existing technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the mechanisms underlying haemodynamic observations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-resources&#34;&gt;Further Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-you&#34;&gt;Thank you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;peterhcharlton.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See this website for resources.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
