<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>open research | Peter Charlton</title>
    <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/open-research/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/open-research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>open research</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Peter Charlton</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/media/icon_hu5d370b2f3224e8711b194d151b733caa_16531_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>open research</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/open-research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal signal processing and learning for wearables</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/multimodal-signal-processing-and-learning-for-wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/multimodal-signal-processing-and-learning-for-wearables/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resources used in this workshop will be made available here in due course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;workshop-synopsis&#34;&gt;Workshop Synopsis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interactive, online workshop providing an introduction to the fundamentals of biomedical signal processing and learning for wearable signals of multiple modalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital wearable devices have great potential to improve health and wellbeing by monitoring physiology in daily life. A key challenge is making wearable data as rich and accurate as possible. The aim of this workshop is to equip attendees with knowledge and skills in processing wearable data, benefiting researchers in academia, device designers in industry, and ultimately the millions of people who use wearables to monitor their health and fitness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will consist of three parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will be introduced to the signals measured by wearables, including photoplethysmogram and electrocardiogram signals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will learn fundamental techniques for processing wearable signals through interactive tutorials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will gain hands-on experience of signal processing and machine learning with wearable data through a group exercise, applying data analysis to real-world problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will use pre-prepared teaching materials consisting of online Jupyter notebooks running Python code on the cloud, so no installation is required on participants&#39; computers. The teaching materials are designed to be highly accessible to the non-specialist, while also providing opportunity for people with experience in the field to explore the topic more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;aiuk-2023&#34;&gt;AIUK 2023&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event is part of AI UK 2023. The Alan Turing Institute&amp;rsquo;s national showcase of data science, machine learning and artificial intelligence research and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a series of events between 6 - 31 March 2023, AI UK Fringe brings together leaders in academia from across the UK&amp;rsquo;s AI ecosystem to demonstrate, exhibit and update on their ground-breaking work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examining the current and future landscapes of data science and AI in real-world settings, leadings minds discuss solutions to the most pressing concerns of our times, from environmental sustainability and health and life sciences to national security, defence and a data-driven economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re excited to be part of AI UK Fringe this March and can&amp;rsquo;t wait for you to join our community and contribute to key conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find out more about AI UK at &lt;a href=&#34;ai-uk.turing.ac.uk&#34;&gt;ai-uk.turing.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open research in Biomedical Signal Processing - Cuffless Blood Pressure Estimation Using the MIMIC-IV Database</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/open-research-in-biomedical-signal-processing-cuffless-blood-pressure-estimation-using-the-mimic-iv-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/open-research-in-biomedical-signal-processing-cuffless-blood-pressure-estimation-using-the-mimic-iv-database/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resources used in this workshop are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://wfdb.io/mimic_wfdb_tutorials/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;workshop-synopsis&#34;&gt;Workshop Synopsis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field of Biomedical Signal Processing stands to benefit greatly from open research. Reproducible studies, accompanied by code and data, allow others to build on the state-of-the-art and to quickly translate between academia and industry. Openly available tools are widely used. Indeed, the MIMIC Waveform Database (WFDB) was referenced in 125 EMBC papers between 2016 and 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this interactive workshop is to provide participants with the knowledge, skills and tools required to conduct open research in the field of Biomedical Signal Processing. It will include a formal announcement of the release of the MIMIC-IV Waveform Database, and hands-on experience of using MIMIC data for cuffless blood pressure estimation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the workshop will provide participants with an understanding of publicly available datasets containing physiological signals, focusing on those on PhysioNet. This will include an overview of the MIMIC Waveform Database, including its clinical context, structure and formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the workshop will provide participants with essential skills for conducting high quality research with openly available data. Participants will work through interactive tutorials in the Python programming language using the WFDB Toolbox, a library of Biomedical Signal Processing tools. The tutorials will introduce key aspects of signal processing, including: data exploration, selection and extraction; pre-processing; feature extraction; modelling; analysis; and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, participants will work in groups on a cuffless blood pressure estimation case study. This will provide hands-on experience and opportunity for networking. Example code will be provided, and researchers will be on hand to answer questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will be led by researchers who develop MIMIC and the WFDB toolboxes, and who have a track-record in reproducible research. It will be of great interest to students, researchers, and engineers: bring a laptop to participate fully.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
