<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>photoplethysmography | Peter Charlton</title>
    <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/photoplethysmography/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/photoplethysmography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>photoplethysmography</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Peter Charlton</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/media/icon_hu5d370b2f3224e8711b194d151b733caa_16531_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>photoplethysmography</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/photoplethysmography/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of Photoplethysmogram Signal Quality on Pulse Arrival Time during Polysomnography</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rinkevicius-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rinkevicius-2023/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smart wearable devices - gadgets or goldmines?</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/wearables_gadgets_goldmines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/wearables_gadgets_goldmines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece was originally published in the newsletter of the Department of Public Health and Primary Care at the University of Cambridge (Oct 2022).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade smart wearable devices such as smartwatches and fitness trackers have become widely used. From the early days, these gadgets could provide interesting physiological information, such as your heart rate, your sleeping patterns, and the number of steps you take. They make for interesting and healthy leisure activities, such as enabling leaderboards of the fastest runners on Strava, and even a recent Primary Care Unit step challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then smart wearables started appearing in high-profile publications ? the Lancet Digital Health reported on their potential utility for infectious disease surveillance; the New England Journal of Medicine presented impressive results on their use for detecting atrial fibrillation; and they have underpinned research from our Department on physical activity. So are these devices simply gadgets which might be confined to a drawer of discarded birthday presents, or are they goldmines of physiological information which could improve patient outcomes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/jproc.2022.3149785&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wearable Photoplethysmography for Cardiovascular Monitoring&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;, we explore the potential for one particular type of wearable to transform physiological monitoring. Photoplethysmography is the optical sensing technology used in smartwatches for heart rate monitoring. You might have seen little light sensor on the underside of a smartwatch. The sensor can be used to monitor heart rate and heart rhythm, which is of particular interest to us in the context of screening for atrial fibrillation. It can also be used to monitor stress, breathing, blood pressure, and blood oxygen saturation to name a few, with potential applications in identifying obstructive sleep apnea, identifying preeclampsia, and mental health assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do we realise the potential for wearables to improve patient outcomes? &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/jproc.2022.3149785&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wearable Photoplethysmography for Cardiovascular Monitoring&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; is our summary of: (i) the engineering principles behind photoplethysmography; (ii) its potential clinical applications; and (iii) pressing directions for future research in order to realise its full potential. The work is also summarised in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qnN39k26ymw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SleepPPG-Net: a deep learning algorithm for robust sleep staging from continuous photoplethysmography</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/kotzen-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/kotzen-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wearable devices for health monitoring</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-devices-for-health-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-devices-for-health-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, wearable photoplethysmography devices could be used to monitor the population&amp;rsquo;s health unobtrusively, helping prevent, identify and treat disease. Potential clinical applications for such devices have emerged in only ten years since they entered the consumer market, including detecting atrial fibrillation. Whilst the developments to date are a great achievement, there is potential for wearable photoplethysmography devices to be used for many more clinical applications. In this talk, Peter Charlton will firstly discuss potential future applications such as blood pressure monitoring, sleep apnea detection, and infectious disease surveillance. Second, he will outline key steps required to make these applications a reality: obtaining high quality photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals; reliably extracting physiological information from PPG signals; and using such information wisely to inform clinical decision making. Third, he will discuss challenges in the development of wearable photoplethysmography devices for clinical applications, and potential solutions. It is hoped that this vision will prompt dialogue about how to develop wearable photoplethysmography devices to be of the greatest possible benefit to society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7301838&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PPG Beat Detection</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/ppg-beats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/ppg-beats/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to develop a high-performance algorithm to detect heartbeats in photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals - the signals measured by smartwatches and pulse oximeters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smart wearables such as smartwatches and wrist-worn fitness trackers use photoplethysmography to monitor heart rate and rhythm. They do so by using an optical sensor to measure the photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal, and then analysing this signal to obtain heart rate or rhythm. A key step in analysing the signal is to identify individual heartbeats in the signal. Several approaches have previously been proposed to identify heartbeats in the signal, although it is not yet clear how well they perform, and whether they perform sufficiently well for clinical use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to identify, or develop, a high-performance algorithm to detect heartbeats in photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performance of existing PPG beat detection algorithms was assessed in different use cases, when using the algorithms with clinical monitoring data, and also wearable data. In addition, the impact of patient demographics and physiology was also assessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are available in detail in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/assess_ppg_beat_detectors&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;. They are summarised in the following leaderboards:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://paperswithcode.com/task/photoplethysmography-ppg-beat-detection&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PPG beat detection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://paperswithcode.com/task/photoplethysmography-ppg-heart-rate&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PPG heart rate estimation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study is accompanied by the following resources, which are being made available &lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/toolbox/ppg_beat_detectors&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PPG Beat Detection Algorithms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A selection of open-source algorithms for detecting beats in PPG signals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/toolbox/performance_assessment&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Performance Assessment Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Resources to assess the performance of PPG beat detectors, including:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/datasets/summary&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Datasets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: several publicly available datasets containing PPG and reference electrocardiogram (ECG) signals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/toolbox/performance_assessment&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: MATLAB code with which to assess performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/tutorials/summary&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tutorials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on how to use the algorithms, datasets, and code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting beats in the photoplethysmogram: benchmarking open-source algorithms</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/assess_ppg_beat_detectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/assess_ppg_beat_detectors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study used two key resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/datasets/summary/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MIMIC PERform&lt;/a&gt; datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;ppg-beats&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; toolbox of PPG beat detection algorithms and code to assess their performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reproducing-the-analysis&#34;&gt;Reproducing the analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analysis reported in this study can be reproduced by following these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;download-the-required-datasets&#34;&gt;Download the required datasets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The datasets used in the study are listed on &lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/datasets/summary/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;. Download each dataset in turn by following the instructions provided on each dataset&amp;rsquo;s page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;install-the-ppg-beats-toolbox&#34;&gt;Install the PPG-beats toolbox&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install the &lt;strong&gt;PPG-beats&lt;/strong&gt; toolbox by following the instructions on &lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/toolbox/getting_started/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assess-the-performance-of-ppg-beat-detectors-across-all-the-datasets&#34;&gt;Assess the performance of PPG beat detectors across all the datasets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the &lt;code&gt;assess_multiple_datasets.m&lt;/code&gt; script (within &lt;strong&gt;PPG-beats&lt;/strong&gt;) to assess the performance of PPG beat detectors across all of the datasets. To do so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edit the &lt;code&gt;assess_multiple_datasets.m&lt;/code&gt; script:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specify the path of the Matlab file for each dataset in the &lt;code&gt;specify_path_of_dataset_file&lt;/code&gt; function within the &lt;code&gt;assess_multiple_datasets.m&lt;/code&gt; script.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specify the folder in which to save results figures by modifying the &lt;code&gt;up.paths.plots_root_folder&lt;/code&gt; variable within the &lt;code&gt;setup_universal_params&lt;/code&gt; function within the &lt;code&gt;assess_multiple_datasets.m&lt;/code&gt; script.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specify the datasets to be analysed in the &lt;code&gt;setup_universal_params&lt;/code&gt; function within the &lt;code&gt;assess_multiple_datasets.m&lt;/code&gt; script:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;up.assessment_datasets = {&#39;capnobase&#39;, &#39;bidmc&#39;, &#39;mimic_train_all&#39;, &#39;mimic_test_all&#39;, &#39;wesad_meditation&#39;, &#39;wesad_amusement&#39;, &#39;wesad_baseline&#39;, &#39;wesad_stress&#39;, &#39;ppg_dalia_sitting&#39;, &#39;ppg_dalia_working&#39;, &#39;ppg_dalia_cycling&#39;, &#39;ppg_dalia_walking&#39;, &#39;ppg_dalia_lunch_break&#39;, &#39;ppg_dalia_car_driving&#39;, &#39;ppg_dalia_stair_climbing&#39;, &#39;ppg_dalia_table_soccer&#39;}; 
up.comparison_datasets = {&#39;mimic_B&#39;, &#39;mimic_W&#39;, &#39;mimic_test_a&#39;, &#39;mimic_test_n&#39;, &#39;mimic_non_af&#39;, &#39;mimic_af&#39;};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specify the beat detectors to be used in the &lt;code&gt;specify_options&lt;/code&gt; function within the &lt;code&gt;assess_multiple_datasets.m&lt;/code&gt; script:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;options.beat_detectors = {&#39;SWT&#39;, &#39;ATmax&#39;, &#39;SPAR&#39;, &#39;IMS&#39;, &#39;AMPD&#39;, &#39;MSPTD&#39;, &#39;ABD&#39;, &#39;qppgfast&#39;, &#39;HeartPy&#39;, &#39;COppg&#39;, &#39;PPGPulses&#39;, &#39;ERMA&#39;, &#39;PWD&#39;, &#39;PDA&#39;, &#39;WFD&#39;};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the &lt;code&gt;assess_multiple_datasets.m&lt;/code&gt; script, which will:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyse each dataset in turn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate results (in the command window) and results figures (saved in the specified folder)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;generate-additional-figures&#34;&gt;Generate additional figures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The additional figures in the manuscript can be generated as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 1&lt;/strong&gt; (Detecting beats in the photoplethysmogram): - run the &lt;code&gt;create_ppg_beat_detection_fig.m&lt;/code&gt; script.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 2&lt;/strong&gt; (Comparing PPG-derived beats with reference beats): - run the &lt;code&gt;make_plot_of_ecg_ppg_time_alignment.m&lt;/code&gt; script.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 5&lt;/strong&gt; (PPG beat detection during different activities): - run the &lt;code&gt;make_plot_of_ppg_beat_detection_challenges.m&lt;/code&gt; script.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wearable photoplethysmography devices for cardiovascular monitoring</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-photoplethysmography-devices-for-cardiovascular-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-photoplethysmography-devices-for-cardiovascular-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices, such as smartwatches and fitness bands, are now widely used. The photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal measured by these devices provides a unique opportunity to monitor cardiovascular health, as it contains a wealth of physiological information, and can be measured frequently in daily life. This talk will firstly summarise current evidence on the clinical utility of such devices, including perspectives on their use for atrial fibrillation detection. Secondly, emerging clinical use cases will be presented, such as infectious disease monitoring and sleep apnea detection. Thirdly, pressing directions for future work will be highlighted, including the need for standardisation of each stage of the PPG measurement process to ensure devices meet the standards required for clinical use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6826342&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qnN39k26ymw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open research in Biomedical Signal Processing - Cuffless Blood Pressure Estimation Using the MIMIC-IV Database</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/open-research-in-biomedical-signal-processing-cuffless-blood-pressure-estimation-using-the-mimic-iv-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/open-research-in-biomedical-signal-processing-cuffless-blood-pressure-estimation-using-the-mimic-iv-database/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resources used in this workshop are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://wfdb.io/mimic_wfdb_tutorials/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;workshop-synopsis&#34;&gt;Workshop Synopsis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field of Biomedical Signal Processing stands to benefit greatly from open research. Reproducible studies, accompanied by code and data, allow others to build on the state-of-the-art and to quickly translate between academia and industry. Openly available tools are widely used. Indeed, the MIMIC Waveform Database (WFDB) was referenced in 125 EMBC papers between 2016 and 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this interactive workshop is to provide participants with the knowledge, skills and tools required to conduct open research in the field of Biomedical Signal Processing. It will include a formal announcement of the release of the MIMIC-IV Waveform Database, and hands-on experience of using MIMIC data for cuffless blood pressure estimation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the workshop will provide participants with an understanding of publicly available datasets containing physiological signals, focusing on those on PhysioNet. This will include an overview of the MIMIC Waveform Database, including its clinical context, structure and formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the workshop will provide participants with essential skills for conducting high quality research with openly available data. Participants will work through interactive tutorials in the Python programming language using the WFDB Toolbox, a library of Biomedical Signal Processing tools. The tutorials will introduce key aspects of signal processing, including: data exploration, selection and extraction; pre-processing; feature extraction; modelling; analysis; and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, participants will work in groups on a cuffless blood pressure estimation case study. This will provide hands-on experience and opportunity for networking. Example code will be provided, and researchers will be on hand to answer questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will be led by researchers who develop MIMIC and the WFDB toolboxes, and who have a track-record in reproducible research. It will be of great interest to students, researchers, and engineers: bring a laptop to participate fully.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing vascular age from the photoplethysmogram</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/assessing-vascular-age-from-the-photoplethysmogram/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2022 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/assessing-vascular-age-from-the-photoplethysmogram/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Respiratory rate algorithms for wearables</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/rr-wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/rr-wearables/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the Respiratory Rate Estimation project is to develop and assess methods for automated respiratory rate (RR) monitoring. It consists of a series of studies of different algorithms for RR estimation from clinical data, complimented by the provision of publicly available datasets and resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C3JPImVkouc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This video&lt;/a&gt; provides an introduction to the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Respiratory rate is a widely used indicator of health, used by clinicians in conjunction with other parameters to assess the health of patients in hospitals, clinics, and the community. For instance, all acutely-ill hospital patients have their respiratory rate measured every few hours to facilitate early detection of clinical deteriorations (deteriorations in health). However, respiratory rate is usually measured manually, by counting the number of breaths a patient takes in a specific period of time, such as a minute. This can potentially be time-consuming and inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An alternative solution could be provided by developing an automated, electronic method for measuring respiratory rate using a device. To this end a plethora of algorithms have been proposed to estimate respiratory rate from several physiological signals, such as the electrocardiogram, photoplethysmogram, accelerometry signal, impedance pneumography signal, and so on. These signals can be easily measured, and in some scenarios are already measured for other purposes. Consequently, a robust, practicable algorithm for estimating respiratory rate from these signals could potentially benefit patients and healthcare providers alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;understanding-the-state-of-the-art&#34;&gt;Understanding the state-of-the-art&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_review/&#34;&gt;literature review&lt;/a&gt; was conducted to understand the state-of-the-art on algorithms to estimate RR from the ECG and PPG. Briefly, we found that RR algorithms had been described in over 196 publications. We also found that previous studies assessing algorithm performance focused mostly on developing novel algorithms, rather than comparing algorithms. In addition, we found that the majority of previous studies of algorithm performance used data from young adults and healthy subjects, rather than assessing performance in our target setting of older, unhealthy adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This helped refine our research questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well do respiratory rate algorithms perform in the target setting?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which algorithm performs best?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it clinically useful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;developing-a-toolbox-of-algorithms&#34;&gt;Developing a toolbox of algorithms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We implemented many of the RR algorithms described in the literature (which are now available in the &lt;a href=&#34;#toolbox-of-rr-algorithms&#34;&gt;toolbox&lt;/a&gt; detailed below). We verified their performance on ideal, simulated data in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_algs_assessment/&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessment&#34;&gt;Assessment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performance of RR algorithms was assessed on young, healthy volunteers in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_algs_assessment/&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;, and on hospital patients in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cont_resp_monitoring/&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;. Briefly, we found a wide variation in the performance of algorithms. Even the best algorithms can produce large errors, which would be clinically significant when compared to the normal RR range of 12-20 bpm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/resp_sig_extraction/&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt; we investigated technical and physiological factors which influence the performance of algorithms. This allowed us to provide recommendations on how to monitor RR using wearables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential clinical utility of algorithms for detecting acute deteriorations in ambulatory hospital patients was assessed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cont_resp_monitoring/&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;future-work&#34;&gt;Future work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, we would like to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement novel techniques designed to handle lower quality signals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assess the performance of algorithms in daily life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform a comprehensive evaluation of algorithm performance across different settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please see the publications below for results arising from the project. In addition, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qlt80ne0t-A&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of the work conducted to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toolbox-of-rr-algorithms&#34;&gt;Toolbox of RR Algorithms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research into respiratory rate algorithms has been hindered by a lack of open-source algorithms. Consequently, one aim of this project is to provide open-source algorithms to facilitate future research. As stated in the licence accompanying the source code, the algorithms are not intended to be fit for any purpose. Instead, they act as a platform from which researchers can develop algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following resources are provided:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/RRest/archive/master.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Algorithm Source Code&lt;/a&gt;: The latest version of the toolbox of algorithms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/RRest/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;: A helpful resource for new users of the toolbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/RRest&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github Repository&lt;/a&gt;: A repository of all versions of the toolbox, past and present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Screening for atrial fibrillation</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/screening-af/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/screening-af/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project we are using signal processing and machine learning techniques to develop strategies to screen for atrial fibrillation (AF) which are both effective (ensuring patients with AF are correctly identified), and cost-effective (minimising the clinical workload involved in screening).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A commonly used approach to screen for AF consists of asking subjects to use a handheld electrocardiogram (ECG) recorder to record a single-lead ECG for 30 seconds. Typically, they are asked to do this several times a day for several weeks, so that even infrequent paroxysmal AF episodes can be identified. This approach is being used in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SAFER Trial&lt;/a&gt;.














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-zenicor-ekg-device-and-recorded-ecgs-a-handheld-device-for-recording-single-lead-ecgs-_source-pandiaraja-m-_et-al_httpsdoiorg103390ecsa-7-08195-cc-by-40httpscreativecommonsorglicensesby40_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/reviewing_ecgs/featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;**Zenicor-EKG device and recorded ECGs**: A handheld device for recording single-lead ECGs. _Source: [Pandiaraja M. _et al._](https://doi.org/10.3390/ecsa-7-08195), [CC BY 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/)_&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Zenicor-EKG device and recorded ECGs&lt;/strong&gt;: A handheld device for recording single-lead ECGs. &lt;em&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3390/ecsa-7-08195&#34;&gt;Pandiaraja M. &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternative approaches to screen for AF using wearables are being explored in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/safer-wearables&#34;&gt;SAFER Wearables Study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atrial fibrillation (AF) is a heart arrhythmia which is associated with a fivefold increase in risk of stroke, and yet is undiagnosed in 425,000 people in England. We are investigating whether screening for AF could reduce the incidence of stroke in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SAFER Trial&lt;/a&gt;. During screening, patients use a handheld device to record their electrocardiogram (ECG) four times a day for three weeks. This results in a large number of ECG recordings, and it isn&amp;rsquo;t feasible to send all the ECGs for clinical review, as this would be highly costly and time-consuming. Therefore, there is a need to optimise strategies to screen for AF to ensure that subjects with AF are correctly identified, whilst minimising the number of ECGs sent for review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to optimise strategies to screen for atrial fibrillation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using both in-house data and publicly available data to design ECG signal processing algorithms which extract parameters such as inter-beat intervals from ECGs. We are using real-world screening data (from the SAFER Trial) to develop strategies to identify ECGs which exhibit possible AF, and therefore require clinical review. We are using the same data to investigate the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of such strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work is ongoing towards the following objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-selecting-ecgs-for-review&#34;&gt;1. Selecting ECGs for review&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Objective:&lt;/em&gt; To determine how best to select which ECGs should be clinically reviewed, using existing ECG analysis algorithms and novel approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Progress:&lt;/em&gt; To date, we have published on the potential benefits of excluding low quality ECGs from the review process in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/reviewing_ecgs/&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;. Work is ongoing to determine how best to select which ECGs out of the remainder to send for review. We are currently assessing how best to use existing ECG analysis algorithms to select which ECGs to review, aiming to send as few ECGs for review as possible (to minimise reviewing workload) whilst maintaining a high sensitivity to ECGs exhibiting AF. We are also comparing the characteristics of ECGs in AF and normal sinus rhythm to understand how algorithms could best discriminate between these two states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-prioritising-ecgs-for-review&#34;&gt;2. Prioritising ECGs for review&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Objective:&lt;/em&gt; To develop a model to prioritise ECGs for review based on their probability of exhibiting AF, using signal processing and machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Progress:&lt;/em&gt; To date, we have developed a simple model which uses RR-intervals to estimate the probability of an ECG containing AF (in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/prioritising_ecgs/&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;). Metrics describing RR-intervals (such as their mean and standard deviation) were used as inputs to a logistic regression model, which outputted a probability of AF. Work is ongoing to incorporate additional inputs to the model, and to use more complex modelling methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-visualising-ecgs-for-review&#34;&gt;3. Visualising ECGs for review&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Objective:&lt;/em&gt; To develop visualisation techniques to aid ECG interpretation using explainable artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Progress:&lt;/em&gt; This will be a key task in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/wd_armstrong_funding/&#34;&gt;this PhD&lt;/a&gt;. Briefly, we will examine different techniques for filtering ECGs to eliminate noise whilst maintaining physiological content, and we will look at approaches for annotating ECGs to explain to reviewers why they have been sent for review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-optimising-the-manual-review-process&#34;&gt;4. Optimising the manual review process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Objective:&lt;/em&gt; To optimise the process for manually reviewing ECGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Progress:&lt;/em&gt; Different approaches for manually reviewing ECGs were investigated in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/reviewing_ecgs/&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;, including the impact on workload of sending ECGs for review by one or two cardiologists. Ongoing work is further investigating the benefits and disadvantages of sending ECGs for review by multiple cardiologists. We are also aiming to develop tools to help train new reviewers of single-lead ECGs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing vascular ageing</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/vascular-ageing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/vascular-ageing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to develop techniques to assess vascular ageing in daily life, providing information on the state of the blood vessels which could be used to personalise cardiovascular treatments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vascular age is an emerging indicator of cardiovascular health that is indicative of cardiovascular risk, and can prompt clinical intervention. The function and structure of blood vessels naturally degrade with age. This process, known as vascular aging, can ultimately result in damage to the heart, kidney, and brain. Indicators of vascular aging have been found to be predictive of cardiovascular morbidity and all-cause mortality, so may be useful for cardiovascular risk stratification. &lt;em&gt;Source: modified from &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00392.2021&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Charlton P.H. et al.&lt;/a&gt;, under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to develop techniques to assess vascular ageing from the photoplethysmogram (PPG) - the pulse wave signal measured by smartwatches, activity trackers, and pulse oximeters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using both simulated and real-world data to design signal processing techniques to extract indicators of vascular ageing from the PPG, and to assess their potential clinical utility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial results are reported in the publications listed below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Establishing best practices in photoplethysmography signal acquisition and processing</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/best_practices_ppg/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/best_practices_ppg/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wearable photoplethysmography for health monitoring</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-photoplethysmography-for-health-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-photoplethysmography-for-health-monitoring/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wearable photoplethysmography for health monitoring</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-photoplethysmography-for-health-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-photoplethysmography-for-health-monitoring/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing software to monitor respiratory rate using wearable sensors</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/developing-software-to-monitor-respiratory-rate-using-wearable-sensors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/developing-software-to-monitor-respiratory-rate-using-wearable-sensors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- &lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Click on the **Slides** button above to view the built-in slides feature. --&gt;
&lt;!--
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities for Photoplethysmography in Public Health</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/opportunities-for-photoplethysmography-in-public-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/opportunities-for-photoplethysmography-in-public-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6352971&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1fQ16Cdxxto&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Photoplethysmography</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/understanding-ppg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/understanding-ppg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A set of resources to aid the beginner and expert alike in understanding photoplethysmography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;An introduction to photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A comprehensive overview:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_review/&#34;&gt;This review paper&lt;/a&gt; summarises the fundamentals of photoplethysmography, its use in wearables, signal processing, and its potential clinical applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A very quick overview:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HnXDvN4WNX8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This short video&lt;/a&gt; provides an introduction to photoplethysmography in a minute (and a bit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wearable-photoplethysmography-devices&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The state-of-the-art in wearable photoplethysmography:&lt;/strong&gt; Our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;book chapter on wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of the state-of-the-art.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;signal-processing&#34;&gt;Signal processing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A comprehensive overview of PPG signal processing:&lt;/strong&gt; Our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/&#34;&gt;book chapter on photoplethysmography signal processing&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of a wide range of techniques for processing the photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detecting heartbeats in PPG signals:&lt;/strong&gt; If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in detecting beats in PPG signals, then see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/ppg-beats/&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; on PPG beat detection, including open-source algorithms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Respiratory rate estimation:&lt;/strong&gt; If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in estimating respiratory rate from the PPG, then see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_review/&#34;&gt;review paper&lt;/a&gt; on the topic for an introduction, and our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/rr-wearables/&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; on respiratory rate estimation algorithms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vascular age:&lt;/strong&gt; If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in assessing vascular age from the PPG, then see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review/&#34;&gt;review paper&lt;/a&gt; on the topic. Includes: blood pressure estimation, assessing arterial stiffness, and identifying peripheral arterial disease. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in this topic, then you might consider joining &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/vascagenet_ppg_group/&#34;&gt;this working group&lt;/a&gt;, part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;, a network for research into vascular ageing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;clinical-applications&#34;&gt;Clinical applications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities for photoplethysmography in public health:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fQ16Cdxxto&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This presentation&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of some potential applications of photoplethysmography in Public Health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-latest-developments-in-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;The latest developments in photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinars:&lt;/strong&gt; To stay up to date with the latest developments in photoplethysmography by attending this &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_webinars/&#34;&gt;free webinar series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wearable photoplethysmography for cardiovascular monitoring</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;accompanying-blog-post&#34;&gt;Accompanying blog post&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/wearables_gadgets_goldmines/&#34;&gt;This blog post&lt;/a&gt; provides a brief overview of this article.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pulse Wave Database</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/pwdb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/pwdb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this project we created a database of simulated arterial pulse waves for in silico testing of pulse wave analysis algorithms. The database includes photoplethysmogram (PPG) pulse waves, which are widely measured by wearables such as smartwatches. It is a valuable resource for future research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details on the project are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PulseAnalyse</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/pulse-analyse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/pulse-analyse/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VascAgeNet Photoplethysmography Group</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/vascagenet_ppg_group/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/vascagenet_ppg_group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vascular ageing is a natural process by which the function and structure of blood vessels degrade over time. It can manifest as elevated blood pressure, increased arterial stiffness, and atherosclerosis. Current approaches to assess vascular age have been found to be predictive of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality, but are often not convenient enough for widespread use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This group of European researchers is investigating the use of photoplethysmography to assess vascular age. Photoplethysmography is a non-invasive optical technique for measuring the arterial pulse wave, providing information on the state of the heart and blood vessels. The group is part of the wider &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet network&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;work-to-date&#34;&gt;Work to date&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group have co-authored several publications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;group-papers&#34;&gt;Group papers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review&#34;&gt;Assessing hemodynamics from the photoplethysmogram to gain insights into vascular age: A review from VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A review of techniques to assess vascular age from the photoplethysmogram. Co-authored by 16 researchers from 11 countries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/best_practices_ppg/&#34;&gt;Establishing best practices in photoplethysmography signal acquisition and processing&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;An editorial on whether it would be possible and beneficial to establish best practices for photoplethysmography signal acquisition and processing. Co-authored by 3 group members.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaborative-research&#34;&gt;Collaborative research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_bp_estimation/&#34;&gt;Blood Pressure Estimation Based on Photoplethysmography: Finger versus Wrist&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Comparing blood pressure estimates obtained from finger and wrist sensors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaborative-reviews&#34;&gt;Collaborative reviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A comprehensive overview of the state-of-the-art of wearable photoplethysmography devices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_review&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography for cardiovascular monitoring&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A review of wearable photoplethysmgoraphy, considering the technology, signal processing, and clinical applications.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;invited-talks&#34;&gt;Invited Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following speakers gave invited talks to the group in 2021:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kevin Kotzen&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Benchmarking Photoplethysmography Peak Detection Algorithms Using the Electrocardiogram Signal as a Reference&lt;/em&gt;, 7 October 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Birute Paliakaite&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Blood Pressure Estimation Based on Photoplethysmography: Finger versus Wrist&lt;/em&gt;, 28 October 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc21_bp_estimation/&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wan-Hua Lin&lt;/strong&gt; (Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology, Chinese Academy of Science, China): &lt;em&gt;Investigating the physiological mechanisms of the photoplethysmogram features for blood pressure estimation&lt;/em&gt;, 18 November 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6579/ab7d78&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philip Aston&lt;/strong&gt; (National Physical Laboratory, UK): 9 December 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022 group members have given talks in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_webinars/&#34;&gt;public webinar series on Photoplethysmography&lt;/a&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Allen&lt;/strong&gt;: presented on &lt;em&gt;Further explorations in photoplethysmography for the detection of occlusive peripheral arterial disease&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Panicos Kyriacou&lt;/strong&gt;: presented on &lt;em&gt;Non-invasive optical monitoring of Intracranial Pressure in Traumatic Brain Injury patients&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serena Zanelli&lt;/strong&gt;: will present on &lt;em&gt;Deep learning approach to detect signal quality from clinical to non-clinical PPG devices&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/EMBC46164.2021.9629640&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;short-term-scientific-mission&#34;&gt;Short-Term Scientific Mission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Peter Charlton spent 5 days at Kaunas University of Technology (KTU), hosted by Prof Vaidotas Marozas, Director of the Institute of Biomedical Engineering. During this STSM, Vaidotas, Peter and Birute Paliakaite worked with colleagues at KTU towards harmonising photoplethysmography-based techniques for the assessment of vascular ageing. This was funded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/short-term-scientific-missions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-members&#34;&gt;Group Members&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work of the group would not be possible without the hard work of its members, who include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Peter Charlton&lt;/a&gt; is a Biomedical Engineer specialising in signal processing techniques for the photoplethysmogram (PPG), including estimating respiratory rate and assessing vascular age from the PPG. He presently holds a British Heart Foundation Fellowship at the University of Cambridge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=YtQF4uUAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Birute Paliakaite&lt;/a&gt; is a researcher specialising in PPG signal processing and modelling, and has made key contributions on acquiring haemodynamic parameters from wearables, and detecting and modelling arrhythmias in the PPG.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=IJ5MsM4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Kristjan Pilt&lt;/a&gt; has developed novel techniques to assess vascular age from the PPG in his research, and has demonstrated their potential clinical utility in diabetic patients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.at/citations?user=pHHJAv4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Martin Bachler&lt;/a&gt; is a research engineer in the field of clinical diagnostics and therapy support, and specialises in biomedical signal analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vascagenet.eu/what-are-you-working-on-serena-zanelli&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Serena Zanelli&lt;/a&gt; develops machine learning and deep learning models to detect cardiovascular disease from PPG signals acquired by wearables, working in both academic and clinical settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vascagenet.eu/what-are-you-working-on-dr-daniel-kulin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Daniel Kulin&lt;/a&gt; is a medical doctor, researcher and entrepreneur in the field of PPG-based pulse wave analysis and in the development of remote patient monitoring systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.co.uk/citations?user=-GsW3HsAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof John Allen&lt;/a&gt; is a leading researcher in the field of photoplethysmography. He has worked on assessing vascular age from the PPG for approximately 30 years. He has strong experience on developing PPG-based techniques, and translating them towards clinical practice. His seminal review on photoplethysmography has been cited over 3,000 times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Magid-Hallab&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Magid Hallab&lt;/a&gt; is a physician, inventor of pOpmetre, a device for PPG-based pulse wave velocity measurement, and CEO of Axelife, the company who sell the pOpmetre device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.it/citations?user=rQqSulEAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Elisabetta Bianchini&lt;/a&gt; works in the field of ultrasound imaging and cardiovascular bioengineering, with strong interests in technology transfer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.at/citations?user=gRActvYAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Christopher Mayer&lt;/a&gt; conducts research in the field of biomedical signal processing, including simulation and pulse wave analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=w1KRD3gAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Dimitrios Terentes-Printzios&lt;/a&gt; is a Cardiologist with research interests in hypertension and microvascular dysfunction. He conducted his PhD on vascular ageing and has co-organised and large multicentre studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/verena-dittrich-1876a989/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Verena Dittrich&lt;/a&gt; is Co-Founder and CEO of Redwave Medical, a company specialising in algorithms for cardiovascular assessment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=VP9nyHAAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Bernhard Hametner&lt;/a&gt; is a mathematician developing methods for pulse wave analysis, and is involved in the analysis of cardiovascular parameters obtained in clinical studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Z_Fojr4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mr Dave Veerasingam&lt;/a&gt; is a Consultant Cardiothoracic Surgeon, and is involved in the cardiac Medtech industry. His research interests include the association between vascular ageing and target organ damage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Dejan-Zikic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Dejan Zikic&lt;/a&gt; is an Associate Professor in Biophysics, with research interests including modelling pulse wave propagation and pulse wave analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.lt/citations?user=yQcWpoIAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Vaidotas Marozas&lt;/a&gt; is Director of the Biomedical Engineering Institute at Kaunas Institute of Technology, and has conducted research into PPG modelling, analysis, and acquisition using wearables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webinars on Photoplethysmography</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_webinars/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_webinars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Photoplethysmography is widely used for physiological monitoring in clinical and consumer devices. It is a highly active area of research, with many important developments being made each year. In 2022 we will hold monthly webinars to showcase the latest research and thinking on key topics within the field of photoplethysmography. Each webinar will consist of a series of talks from leaders in the field. All are welcome to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mailing-list&#34;&gt;Mailing List&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please subscribe to this mailing list if you would like to be kept informed of upcoming webinars:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jiscmail.ac.uk/cgi-bin/webadmin?SUBED1=PHOTOPLETHYSMOGRAPHY&amp;amp;A=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Subscribe to Mailing List&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;upcoming-webinars&#34;&gt;Upcoming Webinars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;photoplethysmography-signal-processing&#34;&gt;Photoplethysmography signal processing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;15 September 2022, 14:00 British Summer Time (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/british-summer-time-bst?t=14&amp;amp;d=2022-06-09&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Hosted by the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/what-s-on/ipem-events/webinar-photoplethysmography-signal-processing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Book now&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal contains a wealth of information. However, there are several challenges to extracting physiological measurements from the PPG. Firstly, the PPG is highly susceptible to noise, which can corrupt the information in the signal. Consequently, much research has focused on assessing PPG signal quality and reducing motion artifact. Secondly, the PPG is often only indirectly affected by the physiology of interest, making it a challenge to extract physiological measurements such as blood pressure. This webinar will feature talks from researchers in the field of PPG signal processing, providing an overview of current work in the field and future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Xiaorong Ding (University of Electronic Science and Technology of China)&lt;/strong&gt; will present on &lt;em&gt;Exploiting Photoplethysmogram Features for Cuffless Blood Pressure Estimation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ariane Morassi-Sasso (Hasso Plattner Institute)&lt;/strong&gt; will present on &lt;em&gt;Predicting blood pressure from photoplethysmography&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serena Zanelli (Paris Sorbonne Nord University)&lt;/strong&gt; will present a &lt;em&gt;Deep learning approach to detect signal quality from clinical to non-clinical PPG devices&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/EMBC46164.2021.9629640&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-webinars&#34;&gt;Previous Webinars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-2&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinar 1: Simulating photoplethysmography signals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;webinar-1-simulating-photoplethysmography-signals&#34;&gt;Webinar 1: Simulating photoplethysmography signals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;27 January 2022, 14:00 GMT (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/greenwich-mean-time-gmt?t=14&amp;amp;d=2021-01-27&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Hosted by the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several techniques have recently been developed to simulate photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals, providing data with which to develop PPG signal processing algorithms, and providing insight into the physiological origins of the signal. This webinar will feature talks from researchers who have developed complementary techniques to simulate PPG signals. It will provide a comprehensive overview of the state-of-the-art, and highlight pressing directions for future research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrius Solosenko (Kaunas University of Technology)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on modelling photoplethysmogram signals during atrial fibrillation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheng Ding (Emory University)&lt;/strong&gt; presented a novel approach to simulating PPG signals using generative adversarial networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon (King&amp;rsquo;s College London)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on the role of &lt;em&gt;in silico&lt;/em&gt; pulse wave databases in machine learning-based pulse wave analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-3&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinar 2: Recent Advances in Photoplethysmography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;webinar-2-recent-advances-in-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;Webinar 2: Recent Advances in Photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;3 March 2022, 14:00 GMT (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/greenwich-mean-time-gmt?t=14&amp;amp;d=2022-03-03&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  Hosted by &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/journal/0967-3334&#34;&gt;Physiological Measurement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://register.gotowebinar.com/register/5108458986808048397&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Watch Again&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photoplethysmography is a non-invasive, optical measurement technique which is widely used for health monitoring. Much research focuses on how to leverage the wealth of information in the photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal, and how to use this information to inform clinical decisions. This webinar will feature talks from leaders in the field, on topics ranging from using photoplethysmography for cardiovascular risk assessment, for cuff-less blood pressure monitoring, and validating these technologies for clinical use. It will provide insight into the state-of-the-art and key directions for future research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rich Fletcher (Massachusetts Institute of Technology)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;&#39;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6579/abad48&#34;&gt;The use of multi-site photoplethysmography (PPG) as a screening tool for coronary arterial disease and atherosclerosis&lt;/a&gt;&#39;&lt;/em&gt;, which was recently published in &lt;em&gt;Physiological Measurement&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raquel Bailón Luesma, (University of Zaragoza)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Applications of PPG waveform decomposition analysis&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ramakrishna Mukkamala (University of Pittsburgh)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.121.17747&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Cuffless Blood Pressure Measurement Devices: Challenges and Proposals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, highlighting work which was recently published in &lt;em&gt;Hypertension&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Xiaoman Xing (Suzhou Institute of Biomedical Engineering and Technology)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;&#39;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6579/ac2a71&#34;&gt;Blood pressure assessment with in-ear photoplethysmography&lt;/a&gt;&#39;&lt;/em&gt;, which was recently published in &lt;em&gt;Physiological Measurement&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-4&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinar 3: Clinical applications of photoplethysmography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;clinical-applications-of-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;Clinical applications of photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;28 April 2022, 14:00 British Summer Time (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/british-summer-time-bst?t=14&amp;amp;d=2022-04-28&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Hosted by the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This webinar highlighted emerging clinical applications of photoplethysmography. Photoplethysmography has traditionally been used in pulse oximeters for oxygen saturation and heart rate monitoring. Recently, several additional clinical applications have been proposed, ranging from screening newborn infants for critical congenital heart disease, to sleep apnea assessment, to identifying atrial fibrillation in everyday life. This webinar featured talks from researchers who are pushing the boundaries of photoplethysmography, developing approaches to use it to enhance healthcare in a range of settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Allen (Coventry University)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Further explorations in photoplethysmography for the detection of occlusive peripheral arterial disease&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Panicos Kyriacou (City University of London)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Non-invasive optical monitoring of Intracranial Pressure in Traumatic Brain Injury patients&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-5&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinar 4: Developments in Photoplethysmography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;developments-in-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;Developments in Photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-desktop&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;7 July 2022, 14:00 British Summer Time (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dateful.com/convert/british-summer-time-bst?t=14&amp;amp;d=2022-07-07&#34;&gt;other time zones&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-user-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Hosted by the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photoplethysmography is an optical sensing technique that is widely used in clinical and consumer devices. It is a highly active area of research, with many important developments being made each year. In this webinar leaders in the field will present their latest research. Topics include extracting measurements of pulse rate variability from the photoplethysmogram (PPG) for applications such as stress monitoring, and using phantoms to investigate the origins of the PPG and develop new PPG sensing technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;James May (City, University of London)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Phantoms for In Vitro Investigations of PPG and PPG technology Development&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elisa Mejia-Mejia (City, University of London)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Photoplethysmography-based pulse rate variability: standardisation of the technique using simulated signals&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;James Anibal (University of Oxford)&lt;/strong&gt; presented on &lt;em&gt;Attention methods for longer PPG sequences&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-want-your-input&#34;&gt;We want your input&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to present at a webinar then please email Peter Charlton:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:pete@oxon.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Register your interest in presenting&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to see your favourite PPG topics (and speakers) included in the webinar series, then please give your suggestions in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdlzKlZi1wVezPwibpWuoxRh6hrV9QJrwjcos5NAa4sUvQCEA/viewform?usp=sf_link&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;anonymous form&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdlzKlZi1wVezPwibpWuoxRh6hrV9QJrwjcos5NAa4sUvQCEA/viewform?usp=sf_link&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Suggest Topics and Speakers&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing wearables - Part 2</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial testing of candidate devices for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/safer-wearables/&#34;&gt;SAFER Wearables Study&lt;/a&gt; was described in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;. Two of the key questions remaining after this initial testing were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How often should ECG electrodes be changed to ensure high signal quality?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long does ECG chest-patch battery last?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are chest-patch connectors available with only two electrodes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post describes a second round of testing designed to answer these questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;devices&#34;&gt;Devices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devices under test were the same as in the first round of testing, with the notable difference of using a different ECG electrode setup, and changing ECG electrodes every 2 days:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference ECG chest-patch&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://shop.bittium.com/product/36/bittium-faros-180-solution-pack&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bittium Faros 180&lt;/a&gt; was used with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ambu.com/cardiology/ecg-electrodes/product/ambu-bluesensor-vlc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;long-term electrodes&lt;/a&gt;. It was worn differently to in the first set of testing. Rather than being worn on the sternum, this time the electrode mounted on the device was attached just below the right clavicle, and one of the cable electrodes was attached just below the ribcage on the left hand side (the green cable was used). This created a lead-II type configuration. It was set to record a single-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) signal at 125 Hz, with no additional recording (such as accelerometry) or analysis (such as RR-interval derivation). The &amp;lsquo;battery alarm beep&amp;rsquo; was turned off, whereas in the first set of testing it had been turned on. Data were stored on the device for retrospective download via USB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photoplethysmography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maximintegrated.com/en/products/interface/sensor-interface/MAX-HEALTHBAND.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Max-Health-Band&lt;/a&gt; was used to record photoplethysmogram (PPG) and accelerometry (accel) signals at the wrist. PPG signals were sampled at 25 Hz (green and ambient), and tri-axis accel signals were also sampled at 25 Hz. The data are initially stored on the device, and transmitted via Bluetooth to a mobile phone for long-term storage (due to limited on-device memory).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electrocardiography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.withings.com/uk/en/move-ecg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Withings Move ECG&lt;/a&gt; device was used to acquire 30-second ECG recordings on demand (when the user activated the ECG recording).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile phone&lt;/strong&gt;: A &amp;lsquo;Motorola Moto G8 Power Lite&amp;rsquo; Android mobile phone was used to store signals from the two wristbands. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.macrodroid.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Macrodroid&lt;/a&gt; was used to open and close two apps in turn to download signals from the PPG and ECG wristbands (the &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pulseon.com/tech/ohr-tracker&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PulseOn Demo&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.withings.wiscale2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Withings Health Mate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; apps respectively). The PPG app was opened twice per hour, for 14 minutes each time, and the ECG app was opened once per hour, for 14 minutes. The WiFi was kept turned off (apart from a brief period of it being turned on, on the first day).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;protocol&#34;&gt;Protocol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single user attempted to wear the devices for seven days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference ECG chest-patch&lt;/strong&gt;: The user changed electrodes every two days, but otherwise the device was unattended. The user shaved prior to application, and removed the device for showering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photoplethysmography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: This device was removed and charged each day (typically for 1-2 hours, until it indicated it was fully charged). It was also removed when showering and washing. Otherwise, it was unattended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electrocardiography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: ECG recordings were acquired on an &lt;em&gt;ad-hoc&lt;/em&gt; basis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile phone&lt;/strong&gt;: The mobile phone was kept on charge in a room where the user spent several hours most days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;outcomes&#34;&gt;Outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;user-acceptability&#34;&gt;User acceptability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devices were worn for the full 7 days. ECG electrodes were changed every two days as planned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ecg-chest-patch-data-quality&#34;&gt;ECG Chest-Patch data quality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ECG chest-patch data appeared to remain high quality throughout the recordings, as shown by the snapshots of ECG signal below, from throughout the 7 days.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-ecg-signals-throughout-the-testing-short-2-second-samples-of-ecg-signals-obtained-through-the-7-days-of-testing-_defintion-hr---hour_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**ECG signals throughout the testing:** Short 2-second samples of ECG signals obtained through the 7 days of testing. _Defintion: Hr - hour_&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/safer_wearables_testing2/ecg_samples_pt2_hua523d781f9ceed0ea7d4fdc37f495076_187744_cbad5640fc9532252d51496d9ec4e2b6.png 400w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing2/ecg_samples_pt2_hua523d781f9ceed0ea7d4fdc37f495076_187744_761329d7cf77bee47e0ab693d8556b23.png 760w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing2/ecg_samples_pt2_hua523d781f9ceed0ea7d4fdc37f495076_187744_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing2/ecg_samples_pt2_hua523d781f9ceed0ea7d4fdc37f495076_187744_cbad5640fc9532252d51496d9ec4e2b6.png&#34;
               width=&#34;568&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;ECG signals throughout the testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Short 2-second samples of ECG signals obtained through the 7 days of testing. &lt;em&gt;Defintion: Hr - hour&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chest-patch-battery&#34;&gt;Chest-patch battery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the 7 days, the ECG chest-patch was disconnected. At this point the blue battery light was flashing, but the low battery alarm didn&amp;rsquo;t sound (as planned, because it was turned off). When the chest-patch was connected to a computer for data download, it said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11% charge remaining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;85% free memory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;leads-with-only-two-electrodes&#34;&gt;Leads with only two electrodes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the testing, we were able to purchase ECG leads with only two electrodes, removing the need for a third electrode. The leads purchased are not long enough for a lead-II configuration, so will be used across the sternum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-points&#34;&gt;Learning points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learnt several things from the testing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ECG signal quality&lt;/strong&gt;: The chest-patch ECG data was of high quality through this test, indicating that high quality data can be obtained for 7 days, and suggesting that it might be helpful to change the electrodes every 2 days to help ensure high quality data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chest-patch battery&lt;/strong&gt;: The chest-patch battery did last for the full 7 days (albeit the low battery light was flashing by the end), indicating that the battery can last for 7 days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chest-patch memory&lt;/strong&gt;: It appears that there is plenty of spare memory on the chest-patch device after a 7 day recording, so potentially accelerometry data could be acquired simultaneously (if that does not affect battery life too much).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;remaining-questions&#34;&gt;Remaining questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accelerometry&lt;/strong&gt;: Is it possible to acquire accelerometry data too, and still have enough battery lifetime for 7 days of data acquisition?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having identified suitable devices for the SAFER Wearables Study, the next steps are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To purchase the necessary devices to start the study&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To amend the participant-facing documentation to include pictures and detailed instructions on how to use the devices (and submit this for ethical approval).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make the automated data acquisition process (streaming data from wristbands to the mobile phone) as robust as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To investigate whether the additional functionality of the ECG chest-patch could be used whilst still having enough battery life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging the potential of machine learning for assessing vascular ageing: state-of-the-art and future research</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ml_vasc_age_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ml_vasc_age_review/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Beauty of Biomedical Engineering</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/the-beauty-of-biomedical-engineering/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/the-beauty-of-biomedical-engineering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;transcript&#34;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transcript for the talk is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/beauty_biomed_eng_transcript/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please see the links above for the resources accompanying this talk. During the talk, you will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The event poll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the talk, you may be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_transcript/&#34;&gt;The transcript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;The accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;, and accompanying &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Photoplethysmography Peak Detection Algorithms Using the Electrocardiogram Signal as a Reference</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_beat_detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_beat_detection/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blood Pressure Estimation Based on Photoplethysmography: Finger versus Wrist</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_bp_estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cinc2021_bp_estimation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photoplethysmography Textbook</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_book/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new textbook, titled &lt;em&gt;Photoplethysmography&lt;/em&gt;, is due to be published in late 2021. Several experts in the field have contributed to the textbook, which is intended to provide a comprehensive summary of the theory, principles and technology of photoplethysmography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sample-chapters&#34;&gt;Sample Chapters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following sample chapters are available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/&#34;&gt;Photoplethysmography signal processing and synthesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A comprehensive overview of signal processing techniques for the photoplethysmogram signal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A comprehensive overview of the state-of-the-art of wearable photoplethysmography devices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;link-to-published-version&#34;&gt;Link to Published Version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The published version of the textbook is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/books/photoplethysmography/kyriacou/978-0-12-823374-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and can be previewed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/_/d8wnEAAAQBAJ?gbpv=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. (Note that some of the images in the preview version are in black and white, whereas the sample chapters above contain full colour images.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photoplethysmography Signal Processing and Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;links-to-full-text&#34;&gt;Links to full text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/PPG_sig_proc_Chapter_20210612.pdf&#34;&gt;Accepted manuscript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The accepted version of the manuscript, freely available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-823374-0.00015-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Published manuscript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The published version, requiring access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/_/d8wnEAAAQBAJ?gbpv=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Books preview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: This version is limited as the images are in black and white.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/books/photoplethysmography/kyriacou/978-0-12-823374-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The entire book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The published version is available to purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-details-of-the-textbook&#34;&gt;Further details of the textbook&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details of the textbook are provided &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_book/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, including another freely available sample chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wearable photoplethysmography devices</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;links-to-full-text&#34;&gt;Links to full text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/Wear_PPG_Chapter_20210323.pdf&#34;&gt;Accepted manuscript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The accepted version of the manuscript, freely available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-823374-0.00011-6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Published manuscript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The published version, requiring access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/_/d8wnEAAAQBAJ?gbpv=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Books preview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: This version is limited as the images are in black and white.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/books/photoplethysmography/kyriacou/978-0-12-823374-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The entire book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The published version is available to purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-details-of-the-textbook&#34;&gt;Further details of the textbook&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details of the textbook are provided &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_book/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, including another freely available sample chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using consumer devices for clinical assessment</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/using-consumer-devices-for-clinical-assessment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2021 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/using-consumer-devices-for-clinical-assessment/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing wearables - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/safer-wearables/&#34;&gt;SAFER Wearables Study&lt;/a&gt; aims to assess the performance and acceptability of wearables for atrial fibrillation screening. It is important that the wearables are able to capture data in everyday life when &lt;em&gt;unmonitored&lt;/em&gt; (unsupervised by the researchers - &lt;em&gt;left to their own devices&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post describes initial testing of candidate devices for the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;devices&#34;&gt;Devices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devices under test, shown at the top of this page, were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference ECG chest-patch&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://shop.bittium.com/product/36/bittium-faros-180-solution-pack&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bittium Faros 180&lt;/a&gt; was used with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ambu.com/cardiology/ecg-electrodes/product/ambu-bluesensor-vlc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;long-term electrodes&lt;/a&gt;. It was worn on the sternum, with one electrode placed at the top of the sternum, and the other placed towards the bottom of the sternum (the green, F/LL electrode was not attached). It was set to record a single-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) signal at 125 Hz, with no additional recording (such as accelerometry) or analysis (such as RR-interval derivation). Data were stored on the device for retrospective download via USB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photoplethysmography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maximintegrated.com/en/products/interface/sensor-interface/MAX-HEALTHBAND.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Max-Health-Band&lt;/a&gt; was used to record photoplethysmogram (PPG) and accelerometry (accel) signals at the wrist. PPG signals were sampled at 25 Hz (green and ambient), and tri-axis accel signals were also sampled at 25 Hz. The data are initially stored on the device, and transmitted via Bluetooth to a mobile phone for long-term storage (due to limited on-device memory).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electrocardiography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.withings.com/uk/en/move-ecg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Withings Move ECG&lt;/a&gt; device was used to acquire 30-second ECG recordings on demand (when the user activated the ECG recording).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile phone&lt;/strong&gt;: A &amp;lsquo;Motorola Moto G8 Power Lite&amp;rsquo; Android mobile phone was used to store signals from the two wristbands. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.macrodroid.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Macrodroid&lt;/a&gt; was used to open and close two apps in turn to download signals from the PPG and ECG wristbands (the &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pulseon.com/tech/ohr-tracker&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PulseOn Demo&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.withings.wiscale2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Withings Health Mate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; apps respectively). The PPG app was opened twice per hour, for 14 minutes each time, and the ECG app was opened once per hour, for 14 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;protocol&#34;&gt;Protocol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single user attempted to wear the devices for seven days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference ECG chest-patch&lt;/strong&gt;: The user changed electrodes if necessary (due to discomfort), but otherwise the device was unattended. The user shaved prior to application, and removed the device for showering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photoplethysmography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: This device was removed and charged each day (typically for 1-2 hours, until it indicated it was fully charged). It was also removed when showering and washing. The device appeared to freeze at one point, so was reset. Otherwise, it was unattended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electrocardiography-based wristband&lt;/strong&gt;: ECG recordings were acquired each day (somewhat sporadically).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile phone&lt;/strong&gt;: The mobile phone was kept on charge in a room where the user spent several hours each day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;outcomes&#34;&gt;Outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;user-acceptability&#34;&gt;User acceptability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devices were worn for approximately 6.5 days. They were removed early because the ECG chest-patch was sounding a low battery alarm. The user changed one of the chest-patch electrodes twice during the study, and the other one was not changed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-acquisition&#34;&gt;Data acquisition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Signal samples:&lt;/strong&gt; Samples of ECG chest-patch and PPG wristband signals are shown below. These samples were recorded at night, explaining the low heart rate and relatively high signal quality. The PPG signals did not appear to degrade over time. The ECG signals on days 1-3 clearly show P waves, QRS complexes, and T-waves. Several of the PPG signals show two peaks (a systolic and a diastolic peak). This plot demonstrates that it is possible to obtain high quality signals using these devices. However, the ECG signals did appear to be of lower quality from day 5 onwards. Possible explanations for this include: (i) the electrode contact degraded over time (particularly as one of the electrodes was not replaced over the course of the 7 days); and (ii) there was mains interference (such as on Day 6).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-signal-samples-over-the-7-days-of-testing-left-the-reference-ecg-chest-patch-right-the-ppg-wristband&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**Signal samples over the 7 days of testing:** (left) the reference ECG chest patch; (right) the PPG wristband.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/sig_samples_hu15ad6f5060b9a6bf10cfc1396fe41f75_183156_5fc46b0903d22784a8c111f9d556bda0.png 400w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/sig_samples_hu15ad6f5060b9a6bf10cfc1396fe41f75_183156_00ad3b5778b4648d897ea36a640b9318.png 760w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/sig_samples_hu15ad6f5060b9a6bf10cfc1396fe41f75_183156_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/sig_samples_hu15ad6f5060b9a6bf10cfc1396fe41f75_183156_5fc46b0903d22784a8c111f9d556bda0.png&#34;
               width=&#34;568&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Signal samples over the 7 days of testing:&lt;/strong&gt; (left) the reference ECG chest patch; (right) the PPG wristband.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inter-beat intervals:&lt;/strong&gt; Minute-long samples of ECG chest-patch and PPG wristband signals are shown below, as well as inter-beat intervals derived from the signals. The close agreement between inter-beat intervals derived from the two signals shows that it is possible to obtain reliable inter-beat intervals from these devices.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-signals-and-inter-beat-intervals-obtained-from-i-the-ppg-wristband-ii-the-reference-ecg-chest-patch&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**Signals and inter-beat intervals:** obtained from (i) the PPG wristband; (ii) the reference ECG chest patch.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/IBI_samples_hue438850cab77d7624a51639d2ff3b18f_126745_480ee227d7af7bf2cbb09ed8d887ab91.png 400w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/IBI_samples_hue438850cab77d7624a51639d2ff3b18f_126745_9fcec4a4b4a6de4500398bd49ecffc03.png 760w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/IBI_samples_hue438850cab77d7624a51639d2ff3b18f_126745_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/IBI_samples_hue438850cab77d7624a51639d2ff3b18f_126745_480ee227d7af7bf2cbb09ed8d887ab91.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;422&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Signals and inter-beat intervals:&lt;/strong&gt; obtained from (i) the PPG wristband; (ii) the reference ECG chest patch.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ecg-data-quality&#34;&gt;ECG data quality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon further inspection, it became clear that the ECG was of high quality until approximately 4 days (94 hours) into the recording. After then, the ECG was mostly of low quality. The change from high to low quality is shown in the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-ecg-signals-throughout-the-testing-short-2-second-samples-of-ecg-signals-obtained-through-the-65-days-of-testing-_defintion-hr---hour_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**ECG signals throughout the testing:** Short 2-second samples of ECG signals obtained through the 6.5 days of testing. _Defintion: Hr - hour_&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_samples_hu7bddf102370eae33f72f90eaa3a8be81_214949_b614c8f97d7417a1870908e39a61dd9a.png 400w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_samples_hu7bddf102370eae33f72f90eaa3a8be81_214949_0a90096b9a7caaa77f2ec68b39dc29c8.png 760w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_samples_hu7bddf102370eae33f72f90eaa3a8be81_214949_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_samples_hu7bddf102370eae33f72f90eaa3a8be81_214949_b614c8f97d7417a1870908e39a61dd9a.png&#34;
               width=&#34;568&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;ECG signals throughout the testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Short 2-second samples of ECG signals obtained through the 6.5 days of testing. &lt;em&gt;Defintion: Hr - hour&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-ecg-signals-during-the-second-half-of-testing-short-2-second-samples-of-ecg-signals-in-the-second-half-of-testing-most-samples-before-96-hours-were-of-high-quality-whereas-most-after-this-time-point-were-of-low-quality-_defintion-hr---hour_&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**ECG signals during the second half of testing** Short 2-second samples of ECG signals in the second half of testing. Most samples before 96 hours were of high quality, whereas most after this time point were of low quality. _Defintion: Hr - hour_&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_change_qual_hu7134c3a1a4e33878ff44d89f1c092797_331333_853d642d745ad30f99245b3245630490.png 400w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_change_qual_hu7134c3a1a4e33878ff44d89f1c092797_331333_b4d02b105fbbeb220404c834099aa13d.png 760w,
               /post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_change_qual_hu7134c3a1a4e33878ff44d89f1c092797_331333_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_2.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/ecg_change_qual_hu7134c3a1a4e33878ff44d89f1c092797_331333_853d642d745ad30f99245b3245630490.png&#34;
               width=&#34;568&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;ECG signals during the second half of testing&lt;/strong&gt; Short 2-second samples of ECG signals in the second half of testing. Most samples before 96 hours were of high quality, whereas most after this time point were of low quality. &lt;em&gt;Defintion: Hr - hour&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-points&#34;&gt;Learning points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learnt several things from the testing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low battery alarm&lt;/strong&gt;: The ECG chest-patch sounded a (loud) low battery alarm, waking up the user. I realised that this functionality could have been turned off, and this should be done in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Closing apps&lt;/strong&gt;: The process used to close apps was unreliable, and should be refined (perhaps by closing apps one at a time, rather than attempting to close them all using the &amp;lsquo;Close All&amp;rsquo; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ECG signal quality&lt;/strong&gt;: ECG signal quality may have degraded over the course of the study, so it would be helpful to investigate how often electrodes should be changed (and also whether the presence of mains devices affects ECG signal quality).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;remaining-questions&#34;&gt;Remaining questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ECG chest-patch battery life:&lt;/strong&gt; Although the device was removed early due to a low battery alarm, it is not clear whether the device could have continued recording for the remaining 0.5 days. When it was connected to a computer the device had approximately 35% battery remaining, indicated that perhaps it could last 7 days. The file size for the ECG signal was 140 MB (leaving over 3GB spare) indicating that the internal storage may be sufficient to store additional signals such as accelerometry, although it&amp;rsquo;s not clear whether turning on the accelerometry would reduce battery life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chest-patch connector&lt;/strong&gt;: The chest-patch connector had three electrode connections, but only two were used in this testing. It would be good to find out whether a connector with only two connections is available, which would avoid having a spare connector hanging loosely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having identified suitable devices for the SAFER Wearables Study, the next steps are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To purchase the necessary devices to start the study&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To amend the participant-facing documentation to include pictures and detailed instructions on how to use the devices (and submit this for ethical approval).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make the automated data acquisition process (streaming data from wristbands to the mobile phone) as robust as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To investigate whether the additional functionality of the ECG chest-patch could be used whilst still having enough battery life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photoplethysmography in a minute (and a bit)</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/photoplethysmography-in-a-minute-and-a-bit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/photoplethysmography-in-a-minute-and-a-bit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6193070&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HnXDvN4WNX8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The &#39;Respiratory rate algorithms for wearables&#39; project</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/the-respiratory-rate-algorithms-for-wearables-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/the-respiratory-rate-algorithms-for-wearables-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- &lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Click on the **Slides** button above to view the built-in slides feature. --&gt;
&lt;!--
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Realising the potential of wearables</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/realising_potential_wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/realising_potential_wearables/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new framework to estimate breathing rate from electrocardiogram, photoplethysmogram, and blood pressure signals</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_framework/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SAFER Wearables Study</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/safer-wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/safer-wearables/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The SAFER Wearables Study:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;A study of the acceptability and performance of wearables for atrial fibrillation screening in older adults&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This page provides details of the study and links to study resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview of the Study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview-of-the-study&#34;&gt;Overview of the Study&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atrial fibrillation (AF) is an irregular heart rhythm which causes a five-fold increase in the risk of stroke. Approximately one in ten people aged over 70 have AF. If AF is recognised then the risk of stroke can be reduced by taking tablets regularly. AF can be difficult to recognise as it can occur without symptoms and only intermittently. Consequently, AF is not recognised in many people, meaning they live with an increased risk of stroke. Therefore, it is important to find ways to identify AF more reliably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, wearable devices have been developed which could be useful for identifying AF. Several devices can monitor heart activity in daily life, including wristbands, smart watches and chest patch monitors. The aim of this study is to assess the acceptability and performance of wearables for use in AF screening in older adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-wearable-devices-a-range-of-wearable-devices-could-potentially-be-used-in-af-screening&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing/featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;**Wearable devices**: A range of wearable devices could potentially be used in AF screening.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Wearable devices&lt;/strong&gt;: A range of wearable devices could potentially be used in AF screening.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary objective is to determine the feasibility of measuring inter-beat-intervals using a wristband.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secondary objectives are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To determine the acceptability of wearables,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To determine the acceptability of the screening approach,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To assess the performance of wearables for acquiring signals,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To assess the performance of signal processing algorithms,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To assess the performance of wearables for AF screening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-can-participate&#34;&gt;Who can participate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selected people who have previously participated in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;SAFER Programme&lt;/a&gt; can participate in this study. The Investigators (at the University of Cambridge) will invite previous SAFER Programme participants to also participate in this study, aiming to enrol 65 without AF, and 65 with AF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-does-the-study-involve&#34;&gt;What does the study involve?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will be asked to wear three devices for seven days: Two wristbands (like watches), and one chest patch (like a plaster). These devices will collect measurements of their heart&amp;rsquo;s activity. The Investigators will also ask participants to tell them how they found wearing the devices by completing a questionnaire. The Investigators will compare how participants found wearing each device, and how accurately each device identifies AF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-information&#34;&gt;Further Information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further information on the study can be found at ClinicalTrials.gov (&lt;a href=&#34;https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04715555&#34;&gt;NCT04715555&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Planning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;study-planning&#34;&gt;Study Planning&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;planning&#34;&gt;Planning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notebooks detailing the planning for the study are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/safer-wearables/tree/main/planning&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, the following notebooks may be of interest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nbviewer.org/github/peterhcharlton/safer-wearables/blob/main/planning/safer_wearables_planning.ipynb&#34;&gt;SAFER Wearables Planning notebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;equipment-testing&#34;&gt;Equipment Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details of equipment testing are provided in the following posts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing&#34;&gt;Testing wearables - Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/safer_wearables_testing2&#34;&gt;Testing wearables - Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equipment testing is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;standard-operating-procedures-sops&#34;&gt;Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SOPs providing fine detail on the practicalities of carrying out the study are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/info/safer_wearables/sops/sops.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details class=&#34;spoiler &#34;  id=&#34;spoiler-2&#34;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;study-methodology&#34;&gt;Study Methodology&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ethics-approval&#34;&gt;Ethics Approval&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details of the ethical approvals for the study are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/info/safer_wearables/details/approvals&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;documentation&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Study documentation will be made openly available in an online repository in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acquiring wearable photoplethysmography data in daily life: The PPG Diary Pilot Study</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_diary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_diary/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of mental stress on the pulse wave features of photoplethysmograms</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/mental_stress_clinical/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/mental_stress_clinical/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling arterial pulse waves in healthy aging: a database for in silico evaluation of hemodynamics and pulse wave indexes</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;prize&#34;&gt;Prize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awarded the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kcl.ac.uk/news/biomedeng18-peter-charlton-wins-early-career-researcher-award-copy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Best Early Career Researcher Award&lt;/a&gt; for a presentation on this work at the &lt;em&gt;BioMedEng18&lt;/em&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A database for developing pulse wave analysis algorithms</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/a-database-for-developing-pulse-wave-analysis-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/a-database-for-developing-pulse-wave-analysis-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please see the links above for the resources accompanying this talk, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/1413662/files/20180907%20Pulse%20Wave%20Database%20%28Public%29.pdf?download=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X8aPZFs8c08&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;The accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;, and accompanying &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathing rate estimation from the electrocardiogram and photoplethysmogram: a review</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;prize&#34;&gt;Prize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awarded the 3rd Prize in the 2021 IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Prize Paper Award.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing mental stress from the photoplethysmogram: a numerical study</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/mental_stress_numerical/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/mental_stress_numerical/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Continuous respiratory rate monitoring to detect clinical deteriorations using wearable sensors</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cont_resp_monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/cont_resp_monitoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-text&#34;&gt;Full text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The published version is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://theses.eurasip.org/theses/829/continuous-respiratory-rate-monitoring-to-detect/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extraction of respiratory signals from the electrocardiogram and photoplethysmogram: technical and physiological determinants</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/resp_sig_extraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/resp_sig_extraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;recognition&#34;&gt;Recognition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Featured in &lt;em&gt;Physiological Measurement&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/journal/0967-3334/page/Highlights_of_2017&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Highlights of 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves&#34;&gt;An introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Charlton, University of Cambridge, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;peterhcharlton.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To do:&lt;/strong&gt; Please go to this website, find this talk under &amp;lsquo;Talks&amp;rsquo;, and see the accompanying resources.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-find-simulated-pulse-waves-useful-for&#34;&gt;I find simulated pulse waves useful for:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding physiological mechanisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigating algorithm performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;: click to expand images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The event poll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt; (from which much content in this presentation is reproduced under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-pulse-wave-modelling-using-a-1d-model&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Pulse Wave Modelling using a 1D Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-model&#34;&gt;The Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420001.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420001.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;simulated-pulse-waves&#34;&gt;Simulated Pulse Waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420005.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420005.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Example simulated pulse waves&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model-limitations&#34;&gt;Model Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;What are the limitations of the model?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;possible-limitations&#34;&gt;Possible Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Periodic inflow, as opposed to normal heart rate variability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specified arterial properties, which may not be representative of a particular individual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not able to model venous flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;input-parameters&#34;&gt;Input Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HR: heart rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SV: stroke volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LVET: left ventricular ejection time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PFT: time of peak aortic flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RFV: reverse flow volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diam: the diameters of the largest arteries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PWV: pulse wave velocities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MAP: mean blood pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PVC: peripheral vascular compliance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which parameters would be most interesting to change, and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which are most relevant to vascular ageing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-2&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (2)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420003.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420003.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-3&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (3)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420002.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420002.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;virtual-subjects&#34;&gt;Virtual Subjects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We created:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baseline virtual subject at each age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual subjects at each age with varying cardiovascular properties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A publicly available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;database&lt;/a&gt; of simulated pulse waves for 4,374 virtual subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparison-with-_in-vivo_-data&#34;&gt;Comparison with &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How well did the model perform?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420006.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420006.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;thoughts-on-performance&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase in amplitude of second systolic peaks with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disappearance of second peak of finger PPG with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonetheless, some marked differences between &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; and simulated waveforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further details of the verification see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-assessing-arterial-stiffness-from-the-photoplethysmogram&#34;&gt;Case Study: Assessing Arterial Stiffness from the Photoplethysmogram&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;digital-wearable-device&#34;&gt;Digital Wearable Device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/dc/Max_Health_Band.jpg/640px-Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/dc/Max_Health_Band.jpg/640px-Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-photoplethysmogram-ppg&#34;&gt;The Photoplethysmogram (PPG)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg/640px-Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg/640px-Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;changes-in-ppg-pulse-wave-shape&#34;&gt;Changes in PPG Pulse Wave Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ed/Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg/640px-Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ed/Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg/640px-Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessing-arterial-stiffness&#34;&gt;Assessing Arterial Stiffness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420004.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420004.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420009.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420009.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Age range&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Influence of HR and SV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would you think of using this technology to assess vascular age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How might it compare to other technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How could one assess the relative performance of such technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assessing Vascular Age from the Photoplethysmogram: A Systematic Review from VascAgeNet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-3&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-changes-in-pulse-pressure-amplification-with-age&#34;&gt;Case Study: Changes in Pulse Pressure Amplification with Age&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pulse-pressure-amplification&#34;&gt;Pulse Pressure Amplification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\mathrm{Pulse \ Pressure \ Amplification} = \frac{\mathrm{brachial \ pulse \ pressure}}{\mathrm{aortic \ pulse \ pressure}}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does pulse pressure amplification change with age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigated the effects of age on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early systolic amplification (P1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Late systolic pressure augmentation (P2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;at the aorta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-1&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420008.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420008.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications-1&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database can be used to gain insight into the CV determinants of mechanisms of blood flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When might this be helpful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How should this approach be used:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instead of clinical studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as well as clinical studies, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not at all?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;related-work&#34;&gt;Related Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following for similar work, investigating the accuracy of methods for assessing pulse wave velocity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willemet M &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;A database of virtual healthy subjects to assess the accuracy of foot-to-foot pulse wave velocities for estimation of aortic stiffness&lt;/em&gt;, doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00175.2015&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00175.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-4&#34;&gt;Part 4&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;potential-studies-using-blood-flow-modelling&#34;&gt;Potential studies using blood flow modelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;exploring-potential-studies&#34;&gt;Exploring potential studies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a study in which pulse wave modelling could be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would need to be simulated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under what conditions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In which ways would the model need to be particularly accurate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;limitations&#34;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dependent on model accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which in turn, is dependent on input parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often requires specialist knowledge to perform studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allows pulse waves to be simulated under different conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control of physiology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free of measurement error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potentially cheap, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t require participant involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;opportunities&#34;&gt;Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preliminary pilot work in technology development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inform the design of &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the potential shortcomings of existing technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the mechanisms underlying haemodynamic observations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-resources&#34;&gt;Further Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-you&#34;&gt;Thank you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;peterhcharlton.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See this website for resources.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toward a robust estimation of respiratory rate from pulse oximeters</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/pimentel-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/pimentel-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic estimation of respiratory rate from wearable sensors</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/pimentel-2015-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/pimentel-2015-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photoplethysmographic derivation of respiratory rate: a review of relevant physiology</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/meredith-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/meredith-2012/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
