<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blood pressure | Peter Charlton</title>
    <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/blood-pressure/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/blood-pressure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>blood pressure</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Peter Charlton</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/media/icon_hu5d370b2f3224e8711b194d151b733caa_16531_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>blood pressure</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/blood-pressure/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal signal processing and learning for wearables</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/multimodal-signal-processing-and-learning-for-wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/multimodal-signal-processing-and-learning-for-wearables/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resources used in this workshop will be made available here in due course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;workshop-synopsis&#34;&gt;Workshop Synopsis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interactive, online workshop providing an introduction to the fundamentals of biomedical signal processing and learning for wearable signals of multiple modalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital wearable devices have great potential to improve health and wellbeing by monitoring physiology in daily life. A key challenge is making wearable data as rich and accurate as possible. The aim of this workshop is to equip attendees with knowledge and skills in processing wearable data, benefiting researchers in academia, device designers in industry, and ultimately the millions of people who use wearables to monitor their health and fitness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will consist of three parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will be introduced to the signals measured by wearables, including photoplethysmogram and electrocardiogram signals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will learn fundamental techniques for processing wearable signals through interactive tutorials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will gain hands-on experience of signal processing and machine learning with wearable data through a group exercise, applying data analysis to real-world problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will use pre-prepared teaching materials consisting of online Jupyter notebooks running Python code on the cloud, so no installation is required on participants&#39; computers. The teaching materials are designed to be highly accessible to the non-specialist, while also providing opportunity for people with experience in the field to explore the topic more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;aiuk-2023&#34;&gt;AIUK 2023&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event is part of AI UK 2023. The Alan Turing Institute&amp;rsquo;s national showcase of data science, machine learning and artificial intelligence research and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a series of events between 6 - 31 March 2023, AI UK Fringe brings together leaders in academia from across the UK&amp;rsquo;s AI ecosystem to demonstrate, exhibit and update on their ground-breaking work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examining the current and future landscapes of data science and AI in real-world settings, leadings minds discuss solutions to the most pressing concerns of our times, from environmental sustainability and health and life sciences to national security, defence and a data-driven economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re excited to be part of AI UK Fringe this March and can&amp;rsquo;t wait for you to join our community and contribute to key conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find out more about AI UK at &lt;a href=&#34;ai-uk.turing.ac.uk&#34;&gt;ai-uk.turing.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wearable devices for health monitoring</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-devices-for-health-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-devices-for-health-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, wearable photoplethysmography devices could be used to monitor the population&amp;rsquo;s health unobtrusively, helping prevent, identify and treat disease. Potential clinical applications for such devices have emerged in only ten years since they entered the consumer market, including detecting atrial fibrillation. Whilst the developments to date are a great achievement, there is potential for wearable photoplethysmography devices to be used for many more clinical applications. In this talk, Peter Charlton will firstly discuss potential future applications such as blood pressure monitoring, sleep apnea detection, and infectious disease surveillance. Second, he will outline key steps required to make these applications a reality: obtaining high quality photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals; reliably extracting physiological information from PPG signals; and using such information wisely to inform clinical decision making. Third, he will discuss challenges in the development of wearable photoplethysmography devices for clinical applications, and potential solutions. It is hoped that this vision will prompt dialogue about how to develop wearable photoplethysmography devices to be of the greatest possible benefit to society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7301838&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wearable photoplethysmography devices for cardiovascular monitoring</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-photoplethysmography-devices-for-cardiovascular-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/wearable-photoplethysmography-devices-for-cardiovascular-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices, such as smartwatches and fitness bands, are now widely used. The photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal measured by these devices provides a unique opportunity to monitor cardiovascular health, as it contains a wealth of physiological information, and can be measured frequently in daily life. This talk will firstly summarise current evidence on the clinical utility of such devices, including perspectives on their use for atrial fibrillation detection. Secondly, emerging clinical use cases will be presented, such as infectious disease monitoring and sleep apnea detection. Thirdly, pressing directions for future work will be highlighted, including the need for standardisation of each stage of the PPG measurement process to ensure devices meet the standards required for clinical use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6826342&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qnN39k26ymw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open research in Biomedical Signal Processing - Cuffless Blood Pressure Estimation Using the MIMIC-IV Database</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/open-research-in-biomedical-signal-processing-cuffless-blood-pressure-estimation-using-the-mimic-iv-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/open-research-in-biomedical-signal-processing-cuffless-blood-pressure-estimation-using-the-mimic-iv-database/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resources used in this workshop are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://wfdb.io/mimic_wfdb_tutorials/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;workshop-synopsis&#34;&gt;Workshop Synopsis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field of Biomedical Signal Processing stands to benefit greatly from open research. Reproducible studies, accompanied by code and data, allow others to build on the state-of-the-art and to quickly translate between academia and industry. Openly available tools are widely used. Indeed, the MIMIC Waveform Database (WFDB) was referenced in 125 EMBC papers between 2016 and 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this interactive workshop is to provide participants with the knowledge, skills and tools required to conduct open research in the field of Biomedical Signal Processing. It will include a formal announcement of the release of the MIMIC-IV Waveform Database, and hands-on experience of using MIMIC data for cuffless blood pressure estimation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the workshop will provide participants with an understanding of publicly available datasets containing physiological signals, focusing on those on PhysioNet. This will include an overview of the MIMIC Waveform Database, including its clinical context, structure and formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the workshop will provide participants with essential skills for conducting high quality research with openly available data. Participants will work through interactive tutorials in the Python programming language using the WFDB Toolbox, a library of Biomedical Signal Processing tools. The tutorials will introduce key aspects of signal processing, including: data exploration, selection and extraction; pre-processing; feature extraction; modelling; analysis; and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, participants will work in groups on a cuffless blood pressure estimation case study. This will provide hands-on experience and opportunity for networking. Example code will be provided, and researchers will be on hand to answer questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will be led by researchers who develop MIMIC and the WFDB toolboxes, and who have a track-record in reproducible research. It will be of great interest to students, researchers, and engineers: bring a laptop to participate fully.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities for Photoplethysmography in Public Health</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/opportunities-for-photoplethysmography-in-public-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/opportunities-for-photoplethysmography-in-public-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6352971&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1fQ16Cdxxto&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PulseAnalyse</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/pulse-analyse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/pulse-analyse/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel Pressure Wave Separation Analysis for Cardiovascular Function Assessment Highlights Major Role of Aortic Root</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/pressure_wave_separation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/pressure_wave_separation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please see the links above for the resources accompanying this talk. During the talk, you will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The event poll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the talk, you may be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/extras/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_transcript/&#34;&gt;The transcript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;The accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;, and accompanying &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photoplethysmography Signal Processing and Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;links-to-full-text&#34;&gt;Links to full text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/PPG_sig_proc_Chapter_20210612.pdf&#34;&gt;Accepted manuscript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The accepted version of the manuscript, freely available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-823374-0.00015-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Published manuscript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The published version, requiring access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/_/d8wnEAAAQBAJ?gbpv=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Books preview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: This version is limited as the images are in black and white.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elsevier.com/books/photoplethysmography/kyriacou/978-0-12-823374-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The entire book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The published version is available to purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-details-of-the-textbook&#34;&gt;Further details of the textbook&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details of the textbook are provided &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_book/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, including another freely available sample chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relationship between fiducial points on the peripheral and central blood pressure waveforms: rate of rise of the central waveform is a determinant of peripheral systolic blood pressure</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/li-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/li-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating central blood pressure from aortic flow: development and assessment of algorithms</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/estimating_cbp_flow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/estimating_cbp_flow/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling arterial pulse waves in healthy aging: a database for in silico evaluation of hemodynamics and pulse wave indexes</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;prize&#34;&gt;Prize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awarded the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kcl.ac.uk/news/biomedeng18-peter-charlton-wins-early-career-researcher-award-copy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Best Early Career Researcher Award&lt;/a&gt; for a presentation on this work at the &lt;em&gt;BioMedEng18&lt;/em&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A database for developing pulse wave analysis algorithms</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/a-database-for-developing-pulse-wave-analysis-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/a-database-for-developing-pulse-wave-analysis-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please see the links above for the resources accompanying this talk, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/record/1413662/files/20180907%20Pulse%20Wave%20Database%20%28Public%29.pdf?download=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X8aPZFs8c08&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;The accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;, and accompanying &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves&#34;&gt;An introduction to modelling arterial pulse waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Charlton, University of Cambridge, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;peterhcharlton.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To do:&lt;/strong&gt; Please go to this website, find this talk under &amp;lsquo;Talks&amp;rsquo;, and see the accompanying resources.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-find-simulated-pulse-waves-useful-for&#34;&gt;I find simulated pulse waves useful for:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding physiological mechanisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigating algorithm performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/slides/intro_to_pulse_wave_modelling_slides/&#34;&gt;The slides&lt;/a&gt;: click to expand images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The event poll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34;&gt;Accompanying paper&lt;/a&gt; (from which much content in this presentation is reproduced under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-pulse-wave-modelling-using-a-1d-model&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Pulse Wave Modelling using a 1D Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-model&#34;&gt;The Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420001.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420001.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;simulated-pulse-waves&#34;&gt;Simulated Pulse Waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420005.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420005.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Example simulated pulse waves&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model-limitations&#34;&gt;Model Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;What are the limitations of the model?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;possible-limitations&#34;&gt;Possible Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Periodic inflow, as opposed to normal heart rate variability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specified arterial properties, which may not be representative of a particular individual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not able to model venous flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;input-parameters&#34;&gt;Input Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HR: heart rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SV: stroke volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LVET: left ventricular ejection time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PFT: time of peak aortic flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RFV: reverse flow volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diam: the diameters of the largest arteries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PWV: pulse wave velocities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MAP: mean blood pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PVC: peripheral vascular compliance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which parameters would be most interesting to change, and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which are most relevant to vascular ageing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-2&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (2)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420003.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420003.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;changing-inputs-3&#34;&gt;Changing Inputs (3)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420002.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420002.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;virtual-subjects&#34;&gt;Virtual Subjects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We created:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baseline virtual subject at each age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual subjects at each age with varying cardiovascular properties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A publicly available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;database&lt;/a&gt; of simulated pulse waves for 4,374 virtual subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparison-with-_in-vivo_-data&#34;&gt;Comparison with &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poll Question:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.sli.do/event/1zunclmb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How well did the model perform?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420006.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420006.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A 1D Model&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;thoughts-on-performance&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase in amplitude of second systolic peaks with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disappearance of second peak of finger PPG with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonetheless, some marked differences between &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; and simulated waveforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further details of the verification see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-assessing-arterial-stiffness-from-the-photoplethysmogram&#34;&gt;Case Study: Assessing Arterial Stiffness from the Photoplethysmogram&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;digital-wearable-device&#34;&gt;Digital Wearable Device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/dc/Max_Health_Band.jpg/640px-Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/dc/Max_Health_Band.jpg/640px-Max_Health_Band.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-photoplethysmogram-ppg&#34;&gt;The Photoplethysmogram (PPG)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg/640px-Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/ad/Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg/640px-Photoplethysmogram_signal_components.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;changes-in-ppg-pulse-wave-shape&#34;&gt;Changes in PPG Pulse Wave Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ed/Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg/640px-Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ed/Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg/640px-Classes_of_photoplethysmogram_%28PPG%29_pulse_wave_shape.svg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessing-arterial-stiffness&#34;&gt;Assessing Arterial Stiffness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420004.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420004.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420009.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420009.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Age range&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Influence of HR and SV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would you think of using this technology to assess vascular age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How might it compare to other technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How could one assess the relative performance of such technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assessing Vascular Age from the Photoplethysmogram: A Systematic Review from VascAgeNet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-3&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-changes-in-pulse-pressure-amplification-with-age&#34;&gt;Case Study: Changes in Pulse Pressure Amplification with Age&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pulse-pressure-amplification&#34;&gt;Pulse Pressure Amplification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\mathrm{Pulse \ Pressure \ Amplification} = \frac{\mathrm{brachial \ pulse \ pressure}}{\mathrm{aortic \ pulse \ pressure}}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does pulse pressure amplification change with age?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigated the effects of age on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early systolic amplification (P1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Late systolic pressure augmentation (P2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;at the aorta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-1&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420008.jpeg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://journals.physiology.org/cms/10.1152/ajpheart.00218.2019/asset/images/large/zh40101929420008.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications-1&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database can be used to gain insight into the CV determinants of mechanisms of blood flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When might this be helpful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How should this approach be used:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instead of clinical studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as well as clinical studies, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not at all?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;related-work&#34;&gt;Related Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following for similar work, investigating the accuracy of methods for assessing pulse wave velocity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willemet M &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;A database of virtual healthy subjects to assess the accuracy of foot-to-foot pulse wave velocities for estimation of aortic stiffness&lt;/em&gt;, doi: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpheart.00175.2015&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10.1152/ajpheart.00175.2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-4&#34;&gt;Part 4&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;potential-studies-using-blood-flow-modelling&#34;&gt;Potential studies using blood flow modelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;exploring-potential-studies&#34;&gt;Exploring potential studies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a study in which pulse wave modelling could be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would need to be simulated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under what conditions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In which ways would the model need to be particularly accurate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;limitations&#34;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dependent on model accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which in turn, is dependent on input parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often requires specialist knowledge to perform studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allows pulse waves to be simulated under different conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control of physiology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free of measurement error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potentially cheap, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t require participant involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;opportunities&#34;&gt;Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preliminary pilot work in technology development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inform the design of &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the potential shortcomings of existing technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the mechanisms underlying haemodynamic observations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-resources&#34;&gt;Further Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/simulating_pulse_waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Accompanying article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/pwdb/pwdb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;User Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/peterhcharlton/pwdb/wiki/Case-Studies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code for case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible without:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/members/ja&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr Jordi Alastruey-Arimon&lt;/a&gt;, who provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://haemod.uk/nektar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;model&lt;/a&gt; and supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The British Heart Foundation, who funded the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COST Action CA18216 &amp;ldquo;Network for Research in Vascular Ageing&amp;rdquo; supported by COST (European Cooperation in Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-you&#34;&gt;Thank you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/introduction-to-modelling-arterial-pulse-waves/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;peterhcharlton.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See this website for resources.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
