<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>awards | Peter Charlton</title>
    <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/awards/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/awards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>awards</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2024 Peter Charlton</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/media/icon_hu5d370b2f3224e8711b194d151b733caa_16531_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>awards</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/awards/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>2023 Martin Black Prize</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/martin_black_prize/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/martin_black_prize/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;recognition-from-the-institute-of-physics-iop-and-institute-of-physics-in-engineering-and-medicine-ipem&#34;&gt;Recognition from the Institute of Physics (IOP) and Institute of Physics in Engineering and Medicine (IPEM)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, Peter Charlton and his colleagues received the &lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/journal/0967-3334/page/Martin_Black_award&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Martin Black Prize&lt;/a&gt; for the best paper published in &lt;em&gt;Physiological Measurement&lt;/em&gt; during the previous year. This award recognises the outstanding contribution made by their paper titled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/assess_ppg_beat_detectors/&#34;&gt;Detecting beats in the photoplethysmogram: benchmarking open-source algorithms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Institute of Physics in Engineering and Medicine announced the award &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/news/winners-of-ipem-s-international-journal-prizes-for-2023-announced/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;media-coverage-in-physics-world&#34;&gt;Media coverage in Physics World&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prize was covered in &lt;a href=&#34;https://physicsworld.com/a/heartbeat-detection-in-smartwatch-signals-wins-physiological-measurement-best-paper-award/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this Physics World article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-details&#34;&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out more, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/assess_ppg_beat_detectors/&#34;&gt;the paper&lt;/a&gt;, and the wider &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/ppg-beats/&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/a&gt; in which this paper sits, developing algorithms to detect heartbeats in photoplethysmography signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The award was covered by the Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/news/winners-of-ipem-s-international-journal-prizes-for-2023-announced/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funded PhD position</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/wd_armstrong_funding/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/wd_armstrong_funding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Charlton and his colleagues have received funding for a PhD studentship on the topic of &amp;lsquo;Using Artificial Intelligence to Enhance Screening for Atrial Fibrillation&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The student will have opportunity to develop a clinical decision support tool to aid ECG interpretation for use in AF screening studies. They will develop valuable skills in both engineering and clinical domains, supervised by researchers in clinical and engineering disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closing date has now passed for applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-details&#34;&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a 3.5-year studentship in the application of Engineering in Medicine funded by the W.D Armstrong Trust Fund at the University of Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atrial fibrillation (AF) is a heart arrhythmia which is associated with a fivefold increase in risk of stroke, and yet is undiagnosed in 425,000 people in England. We are investigating whether screening for AF could reduce the incidence of stroke in the SAFER Trial. During screening, patients use a handheld device to record their electrocardiogram (ECG) four times a day for three weeks. This results in a large number of ECG recordings which must be manually reviewed by clinicians to diagnose AF. This process is costly and time-consuming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to develop a clinical decision support tool to aid ECG interpretation for use in AF screening studies. The objectives are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To develop a model to prioritise ECGs for review using machine learning and signal processing;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To develop visualisation techniques to aid ECG interpretation using explainable artificial intelligence; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To assess the acceptability and performance of the resulting clinical decision support tool in collaboration with cardiologists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;research-environment&#34;&gt;Research Environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PhD studentship will be hosted at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.phpc.cam.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Department of Public Health and Primary Care&lt;/a&gt;. This department is running the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.safer.phpc.cam.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SAFER Trial&lt;/a&gt;, and has a labelled dataset of 100,000s of ECGs recorded in this real-world AF screening programme. The PhD will be co-supervised by Dr Peter Charlton and Prof Jonathan Mant from this department, and Dr Elena Punskaya from the Department of Engineering. The student will be encouraged to integrate into the SAFER Research Team, and to work with our academic, clinical and industrial partners to ensure their work could have real-world impact. Further details of the wider research project in which this PhD sits are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/screening-af/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;value-to-the-student&#34;&gt;Value to the Student&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The student will develop valuable skills in both engineering and clinical domains: machine learning, explainable artificial intelligence, signal processing, and the analysis of clinical trial data. The multi-disciplinary supervision provided will equip the student for a future career at the interface of engineering and medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short-term scientific mission</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/visit_to_ktu/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/visit_to_ktu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dr Peter Charlton spent 5 days at Kaunas University of Technology (KTU), hosted by Prof Vaidotas Marozas, Director of the Institute of Biomedical Engineering. Vaidotas and Peter are members of &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;, a network for research into vascular ageing. They&amp;rsquo;ve previously collaborated on several projects including a &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review/&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet review&lt;/a&gt; of techniques to assess vascular age from the photoplethysmogram (the PPG - the pulse wave signal measured by smartwatches and activity trackers). During this short-term scientific mission, Vaidotas and Peter worked with colleagues at KTU towards harmonising photoplethysmography-based techniques for the assessment of vascular ageing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, Peter and colleagues worked on developing PPG signal processing techniques for the assessment of vascular ageing. Specific tasks included: designing approaches to estimate blood pressure from the PPG pulse wave signal; developing PPG signal quality assessment tools which could help ensure that vascular ageing assessments performed in daily life are reliable; and investigating how well PPG signal processing algorithms perform with different types of sensors. This involved sharing knowledge, data, and signal processing algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, Peter and colleagues discussed the designs of two ongoing clinical studies at KTU and at the University of Cambridge. They identified ways to harmonise the methods used in the two studies so that they provide similar datasets. It is hoped that this will enable the two groups to test the generalisability of findings across the two datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, Peter and colleagues established a pipeline for simulating PPG signals containing artifact and arrhythmias. This involved using KTU&amp;rsquo;s tools for simulating PPG signals alongside data collected at the University of Cambridge. It is hoped that this will lead to the creation of a dataset of simulated PPG signals representative of those that would be measured from older adults in the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter received very warm hospitality from Vaidotas and his colleagues at KTU, sharing meals and sightseeing together. This helped Peter get to know his new colleagues well during a short space of time, establishing relationships which will enable them to continue to work together remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This short-term scientific mission was funded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;, the European COST ACTION-Network for Research in Vascular Ageing under Grant CA18216 supported by the European Cooperation in Science and Technology (COST). See &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/performed-stsms&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for further details of short-term scientific missions funded by the network.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Academic Early Career Award</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ipem_early_career_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ipem_early_career_award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;recognition-from-the-institute-of-physics-and-engineering-in-medicine&#34;&gt;Recognition from the Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2021, Peter Charlton received the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/AboutIPEM/PrizesandAwards.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Academic Early Career Award&lt;/a&gt; from the Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine. This award recognises his contribution to academic practice, including his research, generating income, collaboration, engagement with the scientific community, and his teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The President of the Institute of Physics and Engineering in Medicine, Professor O&amp;rsquo;Connor said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;This award highlights an early career member of IPEM who is destined to go far in their academic career. Peter has had a distinguished career to date and is a worthy winner.&#39;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details of the award are available on the Institute&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/NewsExternalAffairs/LatestNews/TabId/366/ArtMID/1595/ArticleID/612/Gold-Medal-and-Early-Career-awards-for-IPEM-members.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-resources&#34;&gt;Further resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As detailed on the Institute&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipem.ac.uk/AboutIPEM/PrizesandAwards.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;, individuals can apply for this award each year. Any potential applicants may be interested to read the content of my application &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/info/tips/past_applications/ipem_academic_early_career_award&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Prize</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ieee_paper_prize/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ieee_paper_prize/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;recognition-from-the-institute-of-electrical-and-electronic-engineering&#34;&gt;Recognition from the Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2021, Peter Charlton and his colleagues received a Best Paper Award from the Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineering. This award recognises the outstanding contribution made by their paper titled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_review/&#34;&gt;Breathing rate estimation from the electrocardiogram and photoplethysmogram: a review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is often amongst the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/topAccessedArticles.jsp?punumber=4664312&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;most popular papers&lt;/a&gt; published in the journal of &lt;em&gt;IEEE Reviews in Biomedical Engineering&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-details&#34;&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper received the 3rd Prize in the 2021 IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Prize Paper Award. To find out more, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_review/&#34;&gt;the paper&lt;/a&gt;, and the wider &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/rr-wearables/&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/a&gt; in which this paper sits, developing respiratory rate algorithms for wearables.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>British Heart Foundation Fellowship</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/bhf_fellowship/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/bhf_fellowship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;funding-from-the-british-heart-foundation&#34;&gt;Funding from the British Heart Foundation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Peter Charlton was awarded an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bhf.org.uk/research-projects/using-clinical-and-consumer-devices-to-enhance-screening-for-atrial-fibrillation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Immediate PostDoctoral Basic Science Research Fellowship&lt;/a&gt; from the British Heart Foundation. This fellowship will fund research into &amp;lsquo;Using clinical and consumer devices to enhance screening for atrial fibrillation&amp;rsquo;. The research will be based at the University of Cambridge, in collaboration with City, University of London. The project will last five years, running from 2020 to 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further details of the award are available on the British Heart Foundation&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bhf.org.uk/research-projects/using-clinical-and-consumer-devices-to-enhance-screening-for-atrial-fibrillation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
