<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>signal processing | Peter Charlton</title>
    <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/signal-processing/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/signal-processing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>signal processing</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Peter Charlton</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 15:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/media/icon_hu5d370b2f3224e8711b194d151b733caa_16531_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>signal processing</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/tag/signal-processing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysing cardiovascular signals to assess vascular age</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/analysing-cardiovascular-signals-to-assess-vascular-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/analysing-cardiovascular-signals-to-assess-vascular-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resources used in this workshop are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/bsp-book/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;workshop-synopsis&#34;&gt;Workshop Synopsis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This interactive workshop will provide an introduction to the analysis of cardiovascular signals for vascular ageing assessment, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a brief overview of the underlying theory;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hands-on experience of analysing cardiovascular signals in Python; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;opportunity to critically appraise analysis techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson will focus on selected signals (such as blood pressure, photoplethysmogram and electrocardiogram signals) and parameters which can be derived from them (such as pulse wave velocity, the augmentation index, and pulse arrival time). The principles of pulse wave propagation will be introduced, including the relationship between arterial stiffness and pulse wave velocity, and the origins of wave reflections. Participants will be encouraged to investigate how the design of the analysis influences performance (such as comparing pulse transit time to pulse arrival time), allowing them to appreciate the limitations and shortcomings of techniques, and critically appraise their potential clinical utility. The workshop is intended to be accessible to all, including those with no prior experience of programming or signal processing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal signal processing and learning for wearables</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/multimodal-signal-processing-and-learning-for-wearables/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/multimodal-signal-processing-and-learning-for-wearables/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;workshop-synopsis&#34;&gt;Workshop Synopsis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interactive, online workshop providing an introduction to the fundamentals of biomedical signal processing and learning for wearable signals of multiple modalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital wearable devices have great potential to improve health and wellbeing by monitoring physiology in daily life. A key challenge is making wearable data as rich and accurate as possible. The aim of this workshop is to equip attendees with knowledge and skills in processing wearable data, benefiting researchers in academia, device designers in industry, and ultimately the millions of people who use wearables to monitor their health and fitness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will consist of three parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will be introduced to the signals measured by wearables, including photoplethysmogram and electrocardiogram signals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will learn fundamental techniques for processing wearable signals through interactive tutorials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will gain hands-on experience of signal processing and machine learning with wearable data through a group exercise, applying data analysis to real-world problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will use pre-prepared teaching materials consisting of online Jupyter notebooks running Python code on the cloud, so no installation is required on participants&#39; computers. The teaching materials are designed to be highly accessible to the non-specialist, while also providing opportunity for people with experience in the field to explore the topic more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;registration&#34;&gt;Registration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event will be held on Zoom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://turing-uk.zoom.us/meeting/register/tJMofuiprjwiHdw3j6auc_oeuyXjoGyjyoYY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Register here&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;organisers&#34;&gt;Organisers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event is co-organised by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.phpc.cam.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Department of Public Health and Primary Care&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Cambridge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.turing.ac.uk/research/interest-groups/meta-learning-multimodal-data&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Turing&amp;rsquo;s meta-learning for multimodal data interest group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;turings-meta-learning-for-multimodal-data-interest-group&#34;&gt;Turing&amp;rsquo;s meta-learning for multimodal data interest group&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Interest Group, part of The Alan Turing Institute, brings together machine learning researchers, data scientists, and domain experts from diverse backgrounds, career stages, and disciplines to develop algorithms and tools that transfer knowledge across tasks and domains to improve the performance of learning algorithms on data of multiple modalities in real-world applications. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.turing.ac.uk/research/interest-groups/meta-learning-multimodal-data&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for further details of the group&amp;rsquo;s work. If you would like to sign-up and join the group then see &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.office.com/Pages/ResponsePage.aspx?id=p_SVQ1XklU-Knx-672OE-eUxyOQjGdZIurmvwym_4o5UOFhHNkY5WU1RVlczMjNWUVdYTDFDME1VNS4u&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;aiuk-2023&#34;&gt;AIUK 2023&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event is part of AI UK 2023. The Alan Turing Institute&amp;rsquo;s national showcase of data science, machine learning and artificial intelligence research and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a series of events between 6 - 31 March 2023, AI UK Fringe brings together leaders in academia from across the UK&amp;rsquo;s AI ecosystem to demonstrate, exhibit and update on their ground-breaking work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examining the current and future landscapes of data science and AI in real-world settings, leadings minds discuss solutions to the most pressing concerns of our times, from environmental sustainability and health and life sciences to national security, defence and a data-driven economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re excited to be part of AI UK Fringe this March and can&amp;rsquo;t wait for you to join our community and contribute to key conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find out more about AI UK at &lt;a href=&#34;ai-uk.turing.ac.uk&#34;&gt;ai-uk.turing.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resources used in this workshop are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/bsp-book/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PPG Beat Detection</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/ppg-beats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/ppg-beats/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to develop a high-performance algorithm to detect heartbeats in photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals - the signals measured by smartwatches and pulse oximeters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smart wearables such as smartwatches and wrist-worn fitness trackers use photoplethysmography to monitor heart rate and rhythm. They do so by using an optical sensor to measure the photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal, and then analysing this signal to obtain heart rate or rhythm. A key step in analysing the signal is to identify individual heartbeats in the signal. Several approaches have previously been proposed to identify heartbeats in the signal, although it is not yet clear how well they perform, and whether they perform sufficiently well for clinical use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aim&#34;&gt;Aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to identify, or develop, a high-performance algorithm to detect heartbeats in photoplethysmogram (PPG) signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performance of existing PPG beat detection algorithms was assessed in different use cases, when using the algorithms with clinical monitoring data, and also wearable data. In addition, the impact of patient demographics and physiology was also assessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are available in detail in &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/assess_ppg_beat_detectors&#34;&gt;this publication&lt;/a&gt;. They are summarised in the following leaderboards:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://paperswithcode.com/task/photoplethysmography-ppg-beat-detection&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PPG beat detection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://paperswithcode.com/task/photoplethysmography-ppg-heart-rate&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PPG heart rate estimation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study is accompanied by the following resources, which are being made available &lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/toolbox/ppg_beat_detectors&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PPG Beat Detection Algorithms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A selection of open-source algorithms for detecting beats in PPG signals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/toolbox/performance_assessment&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Performance Assessment Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Resources to assess the performance of PPG beat detectors, including:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/datasets/summary&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Datasets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: several publicly available datasets containing PPG and reference electrocardiogram (ECG) signals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/toolbox/performance_assessment&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: MATLAB code with which to assess performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ppg-beats.readthedocs.io/en/latest/tutorials/summary&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tutorials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on how to use the algorithms, datasets, and code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open research in Biomedical Signal Processing - Cuffless Blood Pressure Estimation Using the MIMIC-IV Database</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/open-research-in-biomedical-signal-processing-cuffless-blood-pressure-estimation-using-the-mimic-iv-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/talk/open-research-in-biomedical-signal-processing-cuffless-blood-pressure-estimation-using-the-mimic-iv-database/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;accompanying-resources&#34;&gt;Accompanying Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resources used in this workshop are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://wfdb.io/mimic_wfdb_tutorials/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;workshop-synopsis&#34;&gt;Workshop Synopsis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field of Biomedical Signal Processing stands to benefit greatly from open research. Reproducible studies, accompanied by code and data, allow others to build on the state-of-the-art and to quickly translate between academia and industry. Openly available tools are widely used. Indeed, the MIMIC Waveform Database (WFDB) was referenced in 125 EMBC papers between 2016 and 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this interactive workshop is to provide participants with the knowledge, skills and tools required to conduct open research in the field of Biomedical Signal Processing. It will include a formal announcement of the release of the MIMIC-IV Waveform Database, and hands-on experience of using MIMIC data for cuffless blood pressure estimation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the workshop will provide participants with an understanding of publicly available datasets containing physiological signals, focusing on those on PhysioNet. This will include an overview of the MIMIC Waveform Database, including its clinical context, structure and formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the workshop will provide participants with essential skills for conducting high quality research with openly available data. Participants will work through interactive tutorials in the Python programming language using the WFDB Toolbox, a library of Biomedical Signal Processing tools. The tutorials will introduce key aspects of signal processing, including: data exploration, selection and extraction; pre-processing; feature extraction; modelling; analysis; and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, participants will work in groups on a cuffless blood pressure estimation case study. This will provide hands-on experience and opportunity for networking. Example code will be provided, and researchers will be on hand to answer questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop will be led by researchers who develop MIMIC and the WFDB toolboxes, and who have a track-record in reproducible research. It will be of great interest to students, researchers, and engineers: bring a laptop to participate fully.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Photoplethysmography</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/understanding-ppg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/understanding-ppg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A set of resources to aid the beginner and expert alike in understanding photoplethysmography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-introduction-to-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;An introduction to photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A comprehensive overview:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_review/&#34;&gt;This review paper&lt;/a&gt; summarises the fundamentals of photoplethysmography, its use in wearables, signal processing, and its potential clinical applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A very quick overview:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HnXDvN4WNX8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This short video&lt;/a&gt; provides an introduction to photoplethysmography in a minute (and a bit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wearable-photoplethysmography-devices&#34;&gt;Wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The state-of-the-art in wearable photoplethysmography:&lt;/strong&gt; Our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/wearable_ppg_chapter/&#34;&gt;book chapter on wearable photoplethysmography devices&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of the state-of-the-art.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;signal-processing&#34;&gt;Signal processing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A comprehensive overview of PPG signal processing:&lt;/strong&gt; Our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/ppg_sig_proc_chapter/&#34;&gt;book chapter on photoplethysmography signal processing&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of a wide range of techniques for processing the photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detecting heartbeats in PPG signals:&lt;/strong&gt; If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in detecting beats in PPG signals, then see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/ppg-beats/&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; on PPG beat detection, including open-source algorithms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Respiratory rate estimation:&lt;/strong&gt; If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in estimating respiratory rate from the PPG, then see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_review/&#34;&gt;review paper&lt;/a&gt; on the topic for an introduction, and our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/rr-wearables/&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; on respiratory rate estimation algorithms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vascular age:&lt;/strong&gt; If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in assessing vascular age from the PPG, then see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/vascagenet_ppg_review/&#34;&gt;review paper&lt;/a&gt; on the topic. Includes: blood pressure estimation, assessing arterial stiffness, and identifying peripheral arterial disease. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in this topic, then you might consider joining &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/vascagenet_ppg_group/&#34;&gt;this working group&lt;/a&gt;, part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://vascagenet.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;VascAgeNet&lt;/a&gt;, a network for research into vascular ageing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;clinical-applications&#34;&gt;Clinical applications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities for photoplethysmography in public health:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fQ16Cdxxto&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This presentation&lt;/a&gt; provides an overview of some potential applications of photoplethysmography in Public Health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-latest-developments-in-photoplethysmography&#34;&gt;The latest developments in photoplethysmography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webinars:&lt;/strong&gt; To stay up to date with the latest developments in photoplethysmography by attending this &lt;a href=&#34;https://peterhcharlton.github.io/post/ppg_webinars/&#34;&gt;free webinar series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PulseAnalyse</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/pulse-analyse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/project/pulse-analyse/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel Pressure Wave Separation Analysis for Cardiovascular Function Assessment Highlights Major Role of Aortic Root</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/pressure_wave_separation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/pressure_wave_separation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new framework to estimate breathing rate from electrocardiogram, photoplethysmogram, and blood pressure signals</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/rr_framework/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relationship between fiducial points on the peripheral and central blood pressure waveforms: rate of rise of the central waveform is a determinant of peripheral systolic blood pressure</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/li-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/li-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating central blood pressure from aortic flow: development and assessment of algorithms</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/estimating_cbp_flow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/estimating_cbp_flow/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of mental stress on the pulse wave features of photoplethysmograms</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/mental_stress_clinical/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/mental_stress_clinical/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimising the Windkessel model for cardiac output monitoring during changes in vascular tone</title>
      <link>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/charlton-2014-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://peterhcharlton.github.io/publication/charlton-2014-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
